<CHAPTER>
  <NAME>Metalinguistic Abstraction</NAME>

  <HISTORY>
    % ** \label{ex:env-program-abstraction} should be at end of ex, not start?
    % 2/13/98 FIX TYPO: Extra period at end of ex 4.3
    % winter '97 Add tex '\label's for manual to reference.
    % 8/26/97  FIX TYPESETTING ERROR FOR THIRD PRINTING - - p.393
    %   FIX misplaced index command on p.416.  (This edit won't have
    %   direct effect now, as will edit index by hand.)

    % 4/15 'fix' a a pagebreak not wrapped in pagekludge
    % 4/15 fix multiple entries that landed on same page
    % 4/13-15 Indexing [after final printout of chapters]
    % 4/12 Pagination adjustments from proofreading
    % 4/11 Correction based on spell-checking
    % 4/10  trivial spacing changes based on comparison to before-indexing
    % 4/7-... Julie index fixes (and 4/8 change 'ns')
    % 4/5/96  Hal indexing
    % 4/4/96  paginated rest of chapter
    % 3/29/96 Julie: indexing fixes
    % 3/19/96 paginate the beginning!
    % 3/16/96 Minor edits
    % 3/14/96 (acually 3/15 00:xx) - start indexing
    % 3/9/96 fix spacing in some exercise parts
    % 3/5/96 fix typesetting/spacing
    % 3/4/96 reword to 'fix' most triple hyphenation
    % 2/26-3/3/96 fix some bad line breaks
    % 2/24/96 flush \noindent after {lisp} by closing up space with 
    % 2/24/96 fix a reference (caught by editor)
    % 2/22/96 new spec for epigraph
    % 2/19/96 fixed () in a reference
    % 2/19/96 fixed et al.
  </HISTORY>


  <EPIGRAPH>
    <P>
      <ELLIPSIS/>It<APOS/>s in words that the magic
      is<EMDASH/>Abracadabra, Open Sesame, and the rest<EMDASH/>but the magic 
      words in one story aren<APOS/>t magical in the next.  The real magic is to 
      understand which words work, and when, and for what; the trick is to learn 
      the trick.
    </P>
    <P>
      <ELLIPSIS/>And those words are made from the letters of our
      alphabet: a couple-dozen squiggles we can draw with the pen.  This is
      the key!  And the treasure, too, if we can only get our hands on it!
      It<APOS/>s as if<EMDASH/>as if the key to the treasure <EM>is</EM> 
      the treasure!
    </P>
    <INDEX>Barth, John</INDEX>

    <ATTRIBUTION><AUTHOR>John Barth</AUTHOR><TITLE>Chimera</TITLE></ATTRIBUTION>

  </EPIGRAPH>

  <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

  <TEXT>
    In our study of program design, we have seen that expert programmers
    control the complexity of their designs with the same general
    techniques used by designers of all complex systems.  They combine
    primitive elements to form compound objects, they abstract compound
    objects to form higher-level building blocks, and they preserve
    modularity by adopting appropriate large-scale views of system
    structure.  In illustrating these techniques, we have used 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    as a
    language for describing processes and for constructing computational
    data objects and processes to model complex phenomena in the real
    world.  However, as we confront increasingly complex problems, we will
    find that <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, or indeed any fixed programming language, is not
    sufficient for our needs.  We must constantly turn to new languages in
    order to express our ideas more effectively.  Establishing new
    languages is a powerful strategy for controlling complexity in
    engineering design; we can often enhance our ability to deal with a
    complex problem by adopting a new language that enables us to describe
    (and hence to think about) the problem in a different way, using
    primitives, means of combination, and means of abstraction that are
    particularly well suited to the problem at hand.<FOOTNOTE>The same idea
      is pervasive throughout all of engineering.  For example, electrical
      engineers use many different languages for describing circuits.  Two
      of these are the language of electrical <EM>networks</EM> and the
      language of electrical <EM>systems</EM>.  The network language emphasizes
      the physical modeling of devices in terms of discrete electrical
      elements.  The primitive objects of the network language are primitive
      electrical components such as resistors, capacitors, inductors, and
      transistors, which are characterized in terms of physical variables
      called voltage and current.  When describing circuits in the network
      language, the engineer is concerned with the physical characteristics
      of a design.  In contrast, the primitive objects of the system
      language are signal-processing modules such as filters and amplifiers.
      Only the functional behavior of the modules is relevant, and signals
      are manipulated without concern for their physical realization as
      voltages and currents.  The system language is erected on the network
      language, in the sense that the elements of signal-processing systems
      are constructed from electrical networks.  Here, however, the concerns
      are with the large-scale organization of electrical devices to solve a
      given application problem; the physical feasibility of the parts is
      assumed.  This layered collection of languages is another example of
      the stratified design technique illustrated by the picture
      language of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:graphics"/>.</FOOTNOTE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    <INDEX>high-level language, machine language vs.</INDEX>
    <INDEX>machine language<SUBINDEX>high-level language vs.</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    Programming is endowed with a multitude of languages.  There are
    physical languages, such as the machine languages for particular
    computers.  These languages are concerned with the representation of
    data and control in terms of individual bits of storage and primitive
    machine instructions.  The machine-language programmer is concerned
    with using the given hardware to erect systems and utilities for the
    efficient implementation of resource-limited computations.  High-level
    languages, erected on a machine-language substrate, hide concerns
    about the representation of data as collections of bits and the
    representation of programs as sequences of primitive instructions.
    These languages have means of combination and abstraction, such as
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    definition, that are appropriate to the larger-scale
    organization of systems.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    <INDEX>metalinguistic abstraction</INDEX><INDEX>abstraction<SUBINDEX>metalinguistic</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <EM>Metalinguistic abstraction</EM><EMDASH/>establishing new
    languages<EMDASH/>plays an important role in all branches of engineering
    design.  It is particularly important to computer programming, because
    in programming not only can we formulate new languages but we can also
    implement these languages by constructing evaluators.  An 
    <INDEX>evaluator</INDEX>
    <EM>
      evaluator</EM> (or <EM>interpreter</EM>) for a programming language is a
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    that, when applied to an expression of the language, performs the
    actions required to evaluate that expression.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    It is no exaggeration to regard this as the most fundamental idea in
    programming:
    <BLOCKQUOTE>
      The evaluator, which determines the meaning of
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>expressions</SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>statements and expressions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      in a programming language, is just another program.
    </BLOCKQUOTE>
    To appreciate this point is to change our images of ourselves as
    programmers.  We come to see ourselves as designers of languages,
    rather than only users of languages designed by others.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    In fact, we can regard almost any program as the evaluator for some
    language.  For instance, the polynomial manipulation system of
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:symbolic-algebra"/> embodies the rules of polynomial
    arithmetic and implements them in terms of operations on
    list-structured data.  If we augment this system with
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    to
    read and print polynomial expressions, we have the core of a
    special-purpose language for dealing with problems in symbolic
    mathematics.  The digital-logic simulator of
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:circuit-simulator"/> and the constraint propagator of
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:constraints"/> are legitimate languages in their own
    right, each with its own primitives, means of combination, and means
    of abstraction.  Seen from this perspective, the technology for coping
    with large-scale computer systems merges with the technology for
    building new computer languages, and 
    <INDEX>computer science</INDEX>
    computer science itself becomes
    no more (and no less) than the discipline of constructing appropriate
    descriptive languages.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    We now embark on a tour of the technology by which languages are
    established in terms of other languages.  In this chapter we shall use
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> 
    as a base, implementing evaluators as 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  
    <INDEX>Lisp<SUBINDEX>suitability for writing evaluators</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> is
    particularly well suited to this task, because of its ability to
    represent and manipulate symbolic expressions.  We will take the first
    step in understanding how languages are implemented by building an
    evaluator for <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    itself.  The language implemented by our evaluator
    will be a subset of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>the Scheme dialect of Lisp that we use in this
  book</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>. 
    Although the evaluator described in this chapter is written for
    a particular 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>dialect of Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>subset of JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>,
    it contains the essential structure of
    an evaluator for any expression-oriented language designed for writing
    programs for a sequential machine.  (In fact, most language processors
    contain, deep within them, a little 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><QUOTE>Lisp</QUOTE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> 
    evaluator.)  The evaluator has been simplified for the purposes of illustration and
    discussion, and some features have been left out that would be
    important to include in a production-quality 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> system.
    Nevertheless, this simple evaluator is adequate to execute most of the
    programs in this book.<FOOTNOTE>The most important features that our evaluator leaves out
      are mechanisms for handling errors and supporting debugging.  For a
      more extensive discussion of evaluators, see 
      <INDEX>Friedman, Daniel P.</INDEX><INDEX>Wand, Mitchell</INDEX><INDEX>Haynes, Christopher T.</INDEX>
      Friedman, Wand, and Haynes
      1992, which gives an exposition of programming languages that proceeds
      via a sequence of evaluators written in 
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Scheme</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>the Scheme 
    dialect of Lisp</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.</FOOTNOTE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    An important advantage of making the evaluator accessible as a 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    program is that we can implement alternative evaluation rules by
    describing these as modifications to the evaluator program.  One place
    where we can use this power to good effect is to gain extra control
    over the ways in which computational models embody the notion of time,
    which was so central to the discussion in chapter<SPACE/>3.  There, we
    mitigated some of the complexities of state and assignment by using
    streams to decouple the representation of time in the world from time
    in the computer.  Our stream programs, however, were
    sometimes cumbersome, because they were constrained by
    the applicative-order evaluation of 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Scheme</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
    In section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:lazy-evaluation"/>, we<APOS/>ll change
    the underlying language to provide for a more elegant approach, by modifying
    the evaluator to provide for <EM>normal-order evaluation</EM>.
  </TEXT>

  <SPLIT>
    <SCHEME>
  <TEXT>
    Section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:nondeterministic-evaluation"/> implements a more
    ambitious linguistic change, whereby expressions have many values,
    rather than just a single value.  In this language of <EM>
      nondeterministic computing</EM>, it is natural to express processes that
    generate all possible values for expressions and then search for those
    values that satisfy certain constraints.  In terms of models of
    computation and time, this is like having time branch into a set of
    <QUOTE>possible futures</QUOTE> and then searching for appropriate time lines.
    With our nondeterministic evaluator, keeping track of multiple values
    and performing searches are handled automatically by the underlying
    mechanism of the language.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    In section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:logic-programming"/> we implement a <EM>
      logic-programming</EM> language in which knowledge is expressed in terms
    of relations, rather than in terms of computations with inputs and
    outputs.  Even though this makes the language drastically different
    from <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, or indeed from any conventional language, we will see that
    the logic-programming evaluator shares the essential structure of the
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> evaluator.
  </TEXT>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <!-- FIXME: remove the split and keep the scheme text when the logic programming chapter is available in the JavaScript version  -->
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLIT>
  
  <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

  <!-- Section 1 : The Metacircular Evaluator -->
  &section4.1;
    
  <!-- Section 2 : Variations on a Scheme - Lazy Evaluation -->
  &section4.2;

  <!-- Section 3 : Variations on a Scheme - Nodeterministic Computing -->
  &section4.3;

  <!-- Section 4 : Logic Programming -->
  &section4.4;

</CHAPTER>
