<SUBSECTION>
  <NAME>
    Internal
    <SPLITINLINE>
      <SCHEME>Definitions</SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>Declarations</JAVASCRIPT>
    </SPLITINLINE>
  </NAME>

  <LABEL NAME="sec:internal-definitions"/>

  <INDEX>block structure<OPEN/></INDEX>

  <SPLIT>
    <SCHEME>
      <INDEX>internal definition<SUBINDEX>scope of name<OPEN/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>scope of a variable<SUBINDEX>internal <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      
      <TEXT>
	Our environment model of evaluation and our metacircular evaluator
	execute definitions in sequence, extending the environment frame one
	definition at a time. This is particularly convenient for interactive
	program development, in which the programmer needs to freely mix the
	application of procedures definition procedures. However, if we think
	carefully about the internal definitions used to implement block
	structure (introduced in section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:black-box"/>),
	we will find that name-by-name extension of the environment may not be
	the best way to define local variables.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
	Consider a procedure with internal definitions,	such as
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no">
	  <SCHEME>
(define (f x)
   (define (even? n)
      (if (= n 0)
          true
          (odd? (- n 1))))
   (define (odd? n)
      (if (= n 0)
          false
          (even? (- n 1))))
   ^rest of body of^ f)
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
	Our intention here is that the name <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>
	in the body of the procedure <SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE>	should
	refer to the procedure <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE> that is 
	defined after <SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE>.
	The scope of the name <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>	is the entire
	body of <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE>, not just the portion of the body
	of <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE> starting at the point where the
	<SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE> for <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>
	occurs. Indeed, when we consider that <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>
	is itself defined in terms of
	<SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE><EMDASH/>so that
	<SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>
	are mutually recursive procedures<EMDASH/>we see that the only
	satisfactory interpretation of the two
	<SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE>s is to regard them as if the names
	<SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>
	were being added to the environment simultaneously. More generally, in
	block structure, the scope of a local name is the entire procedure
	body in which the <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE> is evaluated.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
	As it happens, our interpreter will evaluate calls to
	<SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE> correctly, but for an
	<QUOTE>accidental</QUOTE> reason:    Since the definitions
	of the internal procedures come first, no calls to these procedures
	will be evaluated until all of them have been defined. Hence,
	<SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE> will have been defined by the time
	<SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE> is executed.  In fact, our sequential
	evaluation mechanism will give the same result as a mechanism that
	directly implements simultaneous definition for any
	procedure in which the 
	<INDEX>internal definition<SUBINDEX>restrictions on</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	internal definitions come first in a body and evaluation of the value
	expressions for the defined variables doesn<APOS/>t actually use any of
	the defined variables. (For an example of a procedure that doesn<APOS/>t
	obey these restrictions, so that sequential definition isn<APOS/>t
	equivalent to simultaneous definition, see
	exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:simultaneous-def_scheme"/>.)<FOOTNOTE>Wanting
	programs to not depend on this evaluation mechanism is the reason for the
	<QUOTE>management is not responsible</QUOTE> remark in
	footnote<SPACE/><REF NAME="foot:management"/> of chapter<SPACE/>1.
	By insisting that internal definitions come first and do not use each
	other while the definitions are being evaluated, the IEEE standard
	for Scheme leaves implementors some choice in the mechanism used to
	evaluate these definitions.  The choice of one evaluation rule rather
	than another here may seem like a small issue, affecting only the
	interpretation of <QUOTE>badly formed</QUOTE> programs. However, we will
	see in section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:lexical-addressing"/> that moving
	to a model of simultaneous scoping for internal definitions avoids some
	nasty difficulties that would otherwise arise in implementing a compiler.
	</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
	There is, however, a simple way to treat definitions
	so that internally defined names have truly simultaneous
	scope<EMDASH/>just create all local variables that will be in the
	current environment before evaluating any of the value expressions.
	One way to do this is by a syntax transformation on
	<SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE> expressions. Before evaluating the
	body of a <SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE> expression, we 
	<INDEX>scanning out internal definitions</INDEX>
	<INDEX>internal definition<SUBINDEX>scanning out</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<QUOTE>scan out</QUOTE> and eliminate all the internal definitions in
	the body.  The internally defined variables will be created with a
	<SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE> and then set to their values by
	assignment. For example, the procedure
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no" LATEX="yes">
	  <SCHEME>
(lambda ^vars^
   (define u ^e1^)
   (define v ^e2^)
   ^e3^)
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	would be transformed into
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no" LATEX="yes">
	  <SCHEME>
(lambda ^vars^
   (let ((u '*unassigned*)
         (v '*unassigned*))
      (set! u ^e1^)
      (set! v ^e2^)
      ^e3^))
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	where <SCHEMEINLINE>*unassigned*</SCHEMEINLINE> is a special symbol that
	causes looking up a variable to signal an error if an attempt is made to
	use the	value of the not-yet-assigned variable.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
	An alternative strategy for scanning out internal definitions is shown
	in exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:alternative-scanout_scheme"/>. Unlike the
	transformation shown above, this enforces the restriction that the
	defined variables<APOS/> values can be evaluated without using any of the
	variables<APOS/> values.<FOOTNOTE>The IEEE standard for Scheme allows
	for different implementation strategies by specifying that it is up to
	the programmer to obey this restriction, not up to the implementation to
	enforce	it.  Some Scheme implementations, including
	<INDEX>MIT Scheme<SUBINDEX>internal definitions</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	MIT Scheme, use the transformation shown above.  Thus, some programs that
	don<APOS/>t obey this restriction will in fact run in such
	implementations.</FOOTNOTE>
	<INDEX>internal definition<SUBINDEX>scope of name<CLOSE/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      </TEXT>
    </SCHEME>

    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <INDEX>internal declaration<SUBINDEX>scope of name<OPEN/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>scope of a name<SUBINDEX>internal declaration<OPEN/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>

      <TEXT>
	In JavaScript, the scope of a declaration
	is the entire block that immediately surrounds the declaration,
	not just the portion of the block starting at the point where
	the declaration occurs.
	This section takes a closer look at this design choice.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
	Consider a pair of functions
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> and
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	declared locally
	in the body of a function<SPACE/><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>f</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>.
	<SNIPPET LATEX="yes">
	  <NAME>f_is_even_is_odd</NAME>
	  <JAVASCRIPT>
function f(x) {
    function is_even(n) {
        return n === 0
               ? true
               : is_odd(n - 1);
    }
    function is_odd(n) {
        return n === 0
               ? false
               : is_even(n - 1);
    }
    <METAPHRASE>rest of body of <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>f</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></METAPHRASE>
}    
	  </JAVASCRIPT>
	</SNIPPET>
	Our intention here is that the name
	 <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	in the body of the function <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	should refer to the function <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	that is declared after <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>.
	The scope of the name <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> is the
	entire body block of <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE>, not just the portion of
	the body of <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE> starting at the point where
	the declaration of <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	occurs. Indeed, when we consider that
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> is itself defined in terms of
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE><EMDASH/>so
	that <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> and
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> are mutually recursive
	functions<EMDASH/>we see that the only satisfactory interpretation of
	the two declarations is to regard them as if the names
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> and
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	were being added to the environment simultaneously. More generally, in
	block structure, the scope of a local name is the entire block
	in which the declaration is evaluated.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
	The evaluation of blocks in the metacircular evaluator of
	section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:core-of-evaluator"/> achieves such
	a simultaneous scope for local names by
        <INDEX>scanning out declarations<SUBINDEX>in metacircular evaluator</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<INDEX>internal declaration<SUBINDEX>scanning out</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	scanning out the declarations in the block and 
	extending the current environment with bindings for the scanned-out names
	before evaluating the declarations.
	Thus the new environment with respect to which
	the block body is evaluated already contains bindings for 
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> and
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>, and all occurrences
	of these two names refer to the correct binding. Once their respective
	declarations are evaluated, these names refer to the correct values in
	the functions' environments. For example, 
	when
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> 	
	gets applied in the rest of
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>f</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>, its environment<EMDASH/>already containing
	the correct binding for the symbol
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE><EMDASH/>gets extended, and
	the evaluation of the name 
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> in the body  of
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> retrieves the correct value.
      </TEXT>
      <EXERCISE>
	Consider the function <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>f_3</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:lambda"/>:
        <SNIPPET PAGE="64" EVAL="no">
          <NAME>f_helper_definition3_repeated</NAME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
function f_3(x, y) {
    const a = 1 + x * y;
    const b = 1 - y;
    return x * square(a) + y * b + a * b;
}
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SNIPPET>
	<OL>
	  <LI>
	    Draw a diagram of the environment in effect during evaluation
	    of the return expression of
	    <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>f_3</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    When evaluating a function application, the evaluator creates two
	    frames: one for the parameters and one for the names declared 
	    <EM>directly</EM> in the function's body
	    block, as opposed to in an inner block.
	    Since all these names have
	    the same scope, an implementation could combine the two frames.
	    Change the evaluator
	    such that the evaluation of the body block does not create
	    a new frame.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    JavaScript forbids the redeclaration of a parameter
	    as a local name directly in the function's body block.
	    Modify your solution to part b
	    such that an error is generated whenever a function is
	    called in which this happens. Alternatively, modify the
	    evaluator such that it analyzes all function declarations
	    and lambda expressions of a given program and generates an error 
	    whenever
	    a parameter is redeclared directly in a function's body block,
	    regardless of
	    whether that function is ever applied. Which design
	    do you prefer? Why?
	  </LI>
	</OL>
      </EXERCISE>
      <EXERCISE>
	<LABEL NAME="ex:hoisting"/>    
	    Eva Lu Ator is writing programs with blocks in which
	    function declarations and other statements are interspersed.
	    She needs to make sure that the declarations are evaluated before
	    the functions are applied. She complains: <QUOTE>Why can't
	    the evaluator take care of this chore, and move all function
	    declarations to the beginning of the block in which they appear?</QUOTE>
	    <OL>
	      <LI>
		Modify the evaluator following Eva's suggestion.
	      </LI>
	      <LI>
		The designers of JavaScript decided to follow Eva's approach. Discuss 
		this decision.
	      </LI>
	      <LI>
		In addition, the designers of JavaScript decided to allow the name declared
		by a function declaration to be reassigned using assignments.
		Modify your solution
		accordingly and discuss this decision.
	      </LI>
	    </OL>
      </EXERCISE>
      <EXERCISE>
	<LABEL NAME="ex:lambda_calculus"/>
	Recursive functions are obtained in a
	<INDEX>recursive function<SUBINDEX>specifying without declaration</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	roundabout way in our
	interpreter: First declare the name that will refer to the recursive
	function and assign it to the special value
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>"*unassigned*"</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>; then define the
	recursive function in the scope of that name; and finally assign the
	name to the defined function. By the time the recursive function gets
	applied, any occurrences of the name in the body properly refer to
	the recursive function. Amazingly, it is possible to specify recursive
	functions without using declarations or assignment. The following program computes
	10 factorial by applying a recursive
	<INDEX>factorial<SUBINDEX><ORDER>declaration</ORDER>without declaration or assignment</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	factorial function:<FOOTNOTE>This example illustrates a programming
	trick for formulating recursive functions without using assignment. The
	most general trick of this sort is the
	<INDEX><ORDER>Y</ORDER><LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE> operator</INDEX>
	<INDEX>Scheme<SUBINDEX><ORDER>Y</ORDER><LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE> operator written in</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE>
	<EM>operator</EM>, which can be used to give a <QUOTE>pure
	<LATEXINLINE>$\lambda$</LATEXINLINE>-calculus</QUOTE> implementation of
	recursion.  (See
	<INDEX>Stoy, Joseph E.</INDEX><INDEX>Gabriel, Richard P.</INDEX>
	<CITATION>Stoy 1977</CITATION> for details on the lambda
	calculus, and <CITATION>Gabriel 1988</CITATION> for an exposition of the
	<LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE> operator in the language
	Scheme.)</FOOTNOTE>
	<SNIPPET>
	  <NAME>lambda_calculus_factorial</NAME>
	  <EXPECTED>3628800</EXPECTED>
	  <JAVASCRIPT>
(n => (fact => fact(fact, n))
      ( (ft, k) => k === 1
                   ? 1
                   : k * ft(ft, k - 1) 
      )
)
(10);
	  </JAVASCRIPT>
	</SNIPPET>
	<OL>
	  <LI>
	    Check (by evaluating the expression) that this really does compute
	    factorials.  Devise an analogous expression for computing Fibonacci
	    numbers.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    Consider the following function, which includes mutually recursive
	    internal declarations:
	    <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
	      <NAME>even_odd_4_1_6_example</NAME>
              <JAVASCRIPT>
f(99);
	      </JAVASCRIPT>
	    </SNIPPET>
	    <SNIPPET>
	      <NAME>even_odd_4_1_6</NAME>
	      <EXAMPLE>even_odd_4_1_6_example</EXAMPLE>
	      <EXPECTED>false</EXPECTED>
              <JAVASCRIPT>
function f(x) {
    function is_even(n) {
        return n === 0
               ? true
               : is_odd(n - 1);
    }
    function is_odd(n) {
        return n === 0
               ? false
               : is_even(n - 1);
    }
    return is_even(x);
}    
	      </JAVASCRIPT>
	    </SNIPPET>
	    Fill in the missing expressions to complete an alternative
	    declaration of <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE>, which has
	    no internal function declarations:
	    <SNIPPET EVAL="no" LATEX="yes">
	      <JAVASCRIPT>
function f(x) {
    return (
        (is_even, is_odd) => 
           is_even(is_even, is_odd, x)
      )
      ( (is_ev, is_od, n) =>
           n === 0 ? true : is_od(<METAPHRASE>??</METAPHRASE>, <METAPHRASE>??</METAPHRASE>, <METAPHRASE>??</METAPHRASE>),
        (is_ev, is_od, n) =>
           n === 0 ? false : is_ev(<METAPHRASE>??</METAPHRASE>, <METAPHRASE>??</METAPHRASE>, <METAPHRASE>??</METAPHRASE>) 
      );
}
	      </JAVASCRIPT>
	    </SNIPPET>
	  </LI>
	</OL>
      </EXERCISE>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLIT>

    <SPLIT>
      <SCHEME>
  <EXERCISE>
    <LABEL NAME="ex:internal-defs"/>
	In this exercise we implement the method just described for interpreting
	internal definitions.
	We assume that the evaluator supports <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE>
	(see exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:implement-let"/>).
	<OL>
	  <LI>
	    Change
	    <INDEX><USE>lookup-variable-value</USE><SUBINDEX>for scanned-out definitions</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>lookup-variable-value</SCHEMEINLINE>
	    (section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:operations-on-environments"/>)
	    to signal an error if the value it finds is the symbol
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>*unassigned*</SCHEMEINLINE>.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    Write a procedure
	    <INDEX><USE>scan-out-defines</USE></INDEX> 
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>scan-out-defines</SCHEMEINLINE>
	    that takes a procedure body and returns an equivalent one that has no
	    internal definitions, by making the transformation described above.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    Install <SCHEMEINLINE>scan-out-defines</SCHEMEINLINE> in the
	    interpreter, either in  <SCHEMEINLINE>make-procedure</SCHEMEINLINE>
	    or in <SCHEMEINLINE>procedure-body</SCHEMEINLINE> (see
	    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:eval-data-structures"/>).
	    Which place is better? Why?
	  </LI>
	</OL>
  </EXERCISE>

  <EXERCISE>
	Draw diagrams of the environment in effect when evaluating the
	expression <LATEXINLINE>e3</LATEXINLINE> in the procedure in the text,
	comparing how this will be structured when definitions are interpreted
	sequentially with how it will be structured if definitions are scanned
	out as described. Why is there an extra frame in the transformed program?
	Explain why this difference in environment structure can never make a
	difference in the behavior of a correct program.  Design a way to make
	the interpreter implement the <QUOTE>simultaneous</QUOTE> scope rule for
	internal definitions without constructing the extra frame.
  </EXERCISE>
      </SCHEME>
    </SPLIT>
  <SPLIT>
    <SCHEME>
      <EXERCISE>
	<LABEL NAME="ex:alternative-scanout_scheme"/>
	Consider an alternative strategy for scanning out definitions that
	translates the example in the text to
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no" LATEX="yes">
	  <SCHEME>
(lambda ^vars^
   (let ((u '*unassigned*)
         (v '*unassigned*))
      (let ((a ^e1^)
            (b ^e2^))
         (set! u a)
   (set! v b))
   ^e3^))
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	Here <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>
	are meant to represent new variable names, created by the interpreter,
	that do	not appear in the user<APOS/>s program. Consider the
	<INDEX><DECLARATION>solve</DECLARATION> differential equation<SUBINDEX><ORDER>scan</ORDER>with scanned-out definitions</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<SCHEMEINLINE>solve</SCHEMEINLINE> procedure from
	section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:streams-and-delayed-evaluation"/>:
	<SNIPPET>
	  <SCHEME>
(define (solve f y0 dt)
(define y (integral (delay dy) y0 dt))
(define dy (stream-map f y))
      y)
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	Will this procedure work if internal definitions are scanned out as
	shown in this exercise? What if they are scanned out as shown in the
	text?  Explain.
      </EXERCISE>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <SUBHEADING>
      <NAME>Sequential Declaration Processing</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>
      <TEXT>
	<INDEX>sequential declaration processing<SUBINDEX>scanning out declarations vs.<OPEN/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<INDEX>scanning out declarations<SUBINDEX>sequential declaration processing vs.<OPEN/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<LABEL NAME="add_binding_to_frame"/>	
	The design of our evaluator of
	section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:core-of-evaluator"/> imposes a
	runtime burden on the evaluation of blocks: It needs to scan
	the body of the block for locally declared names, extend the
	current environment with a new frame that binds those names, and evaluate the
	block body in this extended environment. Alternatively, the evaluation
	of a block could extend the current environment with an empty frame.
	The evaluation of each declaration in the block body would then add
	a new binding to that frame.
	To implement this design, we first simplify
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>eval_block</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>:
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no">
          <NAME>eval_block_simplified</NAME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
function eval_block(component, env) {
    const body = block_body(component);
    return evaluate(body, extend_environment(null, null, env);
}
          </JAVASCRIPT>
	</SNIPPET>
	The function 
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>eval_declaration</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> can no
	longer assume that the environment already has a binding for
	the name.
	Instead of using
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>assign_symbol_value</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> to
	change an existing binding, it calls a new function,
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>add_binding_to_frame</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>, to
	add to the first frame of the environment a binding of the name
	to the value of the value expression.
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no">
          <NAME>eval_declaration_simplified</NAME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
function eval_declaration(component, env) {
    add_binding_to_frame(declaration_symbol(component), 
                         evaluate(declaration_value_expression(component),
                                  env),
                         first_frame(env));
    return undefined;
}

function add_binding_to_frame(symbol, value, frame) {
    set_head(frame, pair(symbol, head(frame)));
    set_tail(frame, pair(value, tail(frame)));
}
	  </JAVASCRIPT>
	</SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLIT>
    <SPLIT>
      <SCHEME>
      <EXERCISE>
	Ben Bitdiddle, Alyssa P. Hacker, and Eva Lu Ator are arguing about
	the desired result of evaluating the expression
	<SNIPPET>
	  <SCHEME>
(let ((a 1))
   (define (f x)
      (define b (+ a x))
      (define a 5)
      (+ a b))
   (f 10))
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	Ben asserts that the result should be obtained using the sequential rule
	for <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE>: <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>
	is defined to be 11, then <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> is defined to
	be 5, so the result is 16.  Alyssa objects that mutual recursion requires
	the simultaneous scope rule for internal procedure definitions, and that
	it is unreasonable to treat procedure names differently from other names.
	Thus, she argues for the mechanism implemented in
	exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:internal-defs"/>. This would lead to
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> being unassigned at the time that the
	value for <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> is to be computed.  Hence, in
	Alyssa<APOS/>s view the procedure should produce an error.  Eva has a
	third opinion.  She says that if the definitions of
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> are
	truly meant to be simultaneous, then the value 5 for
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> should be used in evaluating
	<SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Hence, in Eva<APOS/>s view
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> should be 5,
	<SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> should be 15, and the result should be 20.
	Which (if any) of these	viewpoints do you support?  Can you devise a way
	to implement internal definitions so that they behave as Eva
	prefers?<FOOTNOTE>The MIT implementors of Scheme support Alyssa on the
	following grounds: Eva is in principle correct<EMDASH/>the definitions
	should be regarded as simultaneous.  But it seems difficult to implement
	a general, efficient mechanism that does what Eva requires. In the
	absence of such a mechanism, it is better to generate an error in the
	difficult cases of simultaneous definitions (Alyssa<APOS/>s notion) than
	to produce an incorrect answer (as Ben would have it).</FOOTNOTE>
	<LABEL NAME="ex:simultaneous-def_scheme"/>
      </EXERCISE>
      </SCHEME>
    </SPLIT>
  <SPLIT>
    <SCHEME>
      <EXERCISE>
	<LABEL NAME="ex:letrec"/>  
	Because internal definitions look sequential but are actually
	simultaneous, some people prefer to avoid them entirely, and use the
	special form
	<INDEX><DECLARATION>letrec</DECLARATION></INDEX>  
	<INDEX><DECLARATION>special forms (those marked <EM>ns</EM> are not in the IEEE Scheme standard)</DECLARATION><SUBINDEX><ORDER>letrec</ORDER><SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> instead.  
	<SCHEMEINLINE>Letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> looks like
	<SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE>, so it is not surprising that the
	variables it binds are bound simultaneously and have the same scope as
	each other.  The sample	procedure <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE> above
	can be written without internal definitions, but with exactly the same
	meaning, as
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no">
	  <SCHEME>
(define (f x)
   (letrec ((even?
               (lambda (n)
                  (if (= n 0)
                      true
                      (odd? (- n 1)))))
            (odd?
               (lambda (n)
                  (if (= n 0)
                      false
                      (even? (- n 1))))))
      ^rest of body of^ f))
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	<SCHEMEINLINE>Letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> expressions, which have the form
	<SNIPPET EVAL="no">
	  <SCHEME>
(letrec ((^var$_{1}$^ ^exp$_{1}$^) ^$\ldots$^ (^var$_{n}$^ ^exp$_{n}$^))
    ^body^)
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	are a variation on <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE> in which the
	expressions <LATEXINLINE>exp$_{k}$</LATEXINLINE> that provide the
	initial values for the variables <LATEXINLINE>var$_{k}$</LATEXINLINE>
	are evaluated in an environment that includes all the
	<SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> bindings.  This permits recursion in
	the bindings, such as the mutual recursion of
	<SCHEMEINLINE>even?</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>odd?</SCHEMEINLINE>
	in the example above, or the evaluation of 10
	<INDEX>factorial<SUBINDEX><ORDER>letrec</ORDER>with <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	factorial with
	<SNIPPET>
	  <SCHEME>
(letrec ((fact
            (lambda (n)
               (if (= n 1)
                   1
                   (* n (fact (- n 1)))))))
        (fact 10))
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	<OL>
	  <LI>
	    Implement <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> as a derived
	    expression, by transforming a <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE>
	    expression into a <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE> expression as
	    shown in  the text above or in
	    exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:alternative-scanout_scheme"/>. That is,
	    the <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> variables should be created
	    with a <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE> and then be assigned their
	    values with <SCHEMEINLINE>set!</SCHEMEINLINE>.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    Louis Reasoner is confused by all this fuss about internal
	    definitions.  The way he sees it, if you don<APOS/>t like to use
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE> inside a procedure, you can just
	    use <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE>. Illustrate what is loose about
	    his reasoning by drawing an environment diagram that shows the
	    environment in which the
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>^rest of body of^ f</SCHEMEINLINE> is evaluated during
	    evaluation of the expression <SCHEMEINLINE>(f 5)</SCHEMEINLINE>, with
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE> defined as in this exercise. Draw an
	    environment diagram for the same evaluation, but with
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE> in place of
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> in the definition of
	    <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE>.
	  </LI>
	</OL>
      </EXERCISE>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <TEXT>
	With sequential declaration processing, the scope of a
	declaration is no longer the entire block that immediately surrounds
	the declaration, but rather just the portion of the block starting at
	the point where the declaration occurs.
	Although we no longer have simultaneous scope, sequential
	declaration processing
	will evaluate calls to the function
	<SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE> at the beginning of this section
	correctly, but for an
	<QUOTE>accidental</QUOTE> reason: Since the declarations
	of the internal functions come first, no calls to these functions
	will be evaluated until all of them have been declared. Hence,
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_odd</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> will have been declared by the time
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>is_even</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> is executed.  In fact, 
	sequential declaration processing 
	will give the same result as our scanning-out-names evaluator in
	section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:core-of-evaluator"/>
	for any function
	in which the 
	<INDEX>internal declaration<SUBINDEX>restrictions on</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	internal declarations come first in a body and evaluation of the value
	expressions for the declared names doesn<APOS/>t actually use any of
	the declared names.
	Exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:simultaneous-def"/> shows
	an example of a function that doesn<APOS/>t
	obey these restrictions, so that the alternative evaluator isn<APOS/>t
	equivalent to our scanning-out-names evaluator.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
	Sequential declaration processing is more efficient and easier to
	implement than scanning out names.
	However, with sequential processing, the
	declaration to which a name refers may depend on the order in which
	the statements in a block are evaluated.
	In exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:simultaneous-def"/>, we see that
	views may differ as to whether that is desirable.

	<INDEX>sequential declaration processing<SUBINDEX>scanning out declarations vs.<CLOSE/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	<INDEX>scanning out declarations<SUBINDEX>sequential declaration processing vs.<CLOSE/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      </TEXT>
      <EXERCISE>
	<LABEL NAME="ex:simultaneous-def"/> 
	Ben Bitdiddle, Alyssa P. Hacker, and Eva Lu Ator are arguing about
	the desired result of evaluating the program
	<SNIPPET>
	  <NAME>mystery_f</NAME>
	  <JAVASCRIPT>
const a = 1;
function f(x) {      
    const b = a + x;
    const a = 5;
    return a + b;
}
f(10); 
	  </JAVASCRIPT>
	</SNIPPET>
	Ben asserts that the result should be obtained using the sequential
	processing of declarations:
	<SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> is declared to be 11, then
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> is declared to be 5, so the result is 16.
	Alyssa objects that mutual recursion requires the simultaneous scope
	rule for internal function declarations, and that it is unreasonable to
	treat function names differently from other names.  Thus, she argues for
	the mechanism implemented in
	section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:core-of-evaluator"/>. This would
	lead to <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> being unassigned at the time that
	the value for <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> is to be computed.  Hence,
	in Alyssa<APOS/>s view the function should produce an error.  Eva has a
	third opinion.  She says that if the declarations of
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>
	are truly meant to be simultaneous, then the value 5 for
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> should be used in evaluating
	<SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Hence, in Eva<APOS/>s view
	<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> should be 5,
	<SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> should be 15, and the result should be 20.
	Which (if any) of these	viewpoints do you support?  Can you devise a way
	to implement internal declarations so that they behave as Eva
	prefers?<FOOTNOTE>The designers of JavaScript support Alyssa on the
	following grounds: Eva is in principle correct<EMDASH/>the declarations
	should be regarded as simultaneous.  But it seems difficult to implement
	a general, efficient mechanism that does what Eva requires. In the
	absence of such a mechanism, it is better to generate an error in the
	difficult cases of simultaneous declarations (Alyssa<APOS/>s notion) than
	to produce an incorrect answer (as Ben would have it).</FOOTNOTE>
      </EXERCISE>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLIT>


  <SPLIT>
    <SCHEME>
  <EXERCISE>
    <LABEL NAME="ex:lambda_calculus_scheme"/>
	Amazingly, Louis<APOS/>s intuition in
	exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:letrec"/> is correct. It is indeed
	<INDEX>recursive procedure<SUBINDEX>specifying without <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	possible to specify recursive procedures without using
	<SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> (or even
	<SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE>), although the method for
	accomplishing this is much more subtle than Louis imagined.
	The following expression computes 10
	<INDEX>factorial<SUBINDEX><ORDER>letrec</ORDER>without <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE> or <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
	factorial by applying a recursive
	factorial procedure:<FOOTNOTE>This example illustrates a programming
	trick for formulating recursive procedures without using
	<SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE>. The
	most general trick of this sort is the
	<INDEX><ORDER>Y</ORDER><LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE> operator</INDEX>
	<LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE>
	<EM>operator</EM>, which can be used to give a <QUOTE>pure
	<LATEXINLINE>$\lambda$</LATEXINLINE>-calculus</QUOTE> implementation of
	recursion.  (See
	<INDEX>Stoy, Joseph E.</INDEX><INDEX>Gabriel, Richard P.</INDEX>
	<CITATION>Stoy 1977</CITATION> for details on the lambda
	calculus, and <CITATION>Gabriel 1988</CITATION> for an exposition of the
	<LATEXINLINE>$Y$</LATEXINLINE> operator in Scheme.)</FOOTNOTE>
	<SNIPPET>
	  <SCHEME>
((lambda (n)
    ((lambda (fact)
        (fact fact n))
     (lambda (ft k)
        (if (= k 1)
            1
            (* k (ft ft (- k 1)))))))
 10)
	  </SCHEME>
	</SNIPPET>
	<OL>
	  <LI>
	    Check (by evaluating the expression) that this really does compute
	    factorials.  Devise an analogous expression for computing Fibonacci
	    numbers.
	  </LI>
	  <LI>
	    Consider the following procedure, which includes mutually recursive
	    internal definitions:
	    <SNIPPET>
              <SCHEME>
(define (f x)
   (define (even? n)
      (if (= n 0)
          true
      (odd? (- n 1))))
   (define (odd? n)
      (if (= n 0)
          false
          (even? (- n 1))))
   (even? x))
              </SCHEME>
	    </SNIPPET>
	    Fill in the missing expressions to complete an alternative definition
	    of <SCHEMEINLINE>f</SCHEMEINLINE>, which uses neither internal
	    definitions nor <SCHEMEINLINE>letrec</SCHEMEINLINE>:
	    <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
              <SCHEME>
(define (f x)
   ((lambda (even? odd?)
  (even? even? odd? x))
    (lambda (ev? od? n)
  (if (= n 0) true (od? ^??^ ^??^ ^??^)))
    (lambda (ev? od? n)
  (if (= n 0) false (ev? ^??^ ^??^ ^??^)))))
              </SCHEME>
	    </SNIPPET>
	  </LI>
	</OL>
  </EXERCISE>
    </SCHEME>
  </SPLIT>

  <INDEX>block structure<CLOSE/></INDEX>
  <INDEX>internal declaration<SUBINDEX>scope of name<CLOSE/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>scope of a name<SUBINDEX>internal declaration<CLOSE/></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
</SUBSECTION>
