<CHAPTER>
  <NAME>Building Abstractions with Data</NAME>

  <HISTORY> 
    % fall '97 Add tex '\label's for manual to reference.
    % 8/26/97  FIX TYPOS FOR THIRD PRINTING -- p.112, 179, 181

    % 4/15 fix multiple entries that landed on same page
    % 4/13-15 Indexing [after final printout of chapters]
    % 4/11 Corrections and adjustments based on <QUOTE>final</QUOTE> check and spell-checking
    % 4/9  trivial fixes based on comparison to before-indexing
    % 4/7-... Julie index fixes (and 4/8 change 'ns')
    % 4/6/96 Julie: pagination change; add Thatcher reference; index fixes
    % 4/5/96 Hal indexing
    % 4/5/96 Julie: index fixes; typo fixes
    % 4/4/96 content fixes; pagination adjustments; rest of pagination
    % 4/3/96 indexing changes
    % 4/2/96 paginate through 2.2
    % 4/1/96 Julie: paginate up to Rogers footnote
    % 4/1/96 Julie misc improvements
    % 3/29/96 Julie indexing fixes
    % 3/20/96 Julie indexing fixes
    % 3/18/96 'atan' edit &amp; minor indexing fixes
    % 3/17/96 Julie minor indexing changes
    % 3/15/96 Julie minor indexing changes
    % 3/10-3/13/96 indexing by Hal, minor indexing fixes/additions by Julie

    % 3/9/96 fix spacing in some exercise parts; break out lines in get/put spec;
    %        other minor edits
    % 3/6/96 minor wording and line-break improvements
    % 3/4/96 reword to 'fix' most triple hyphenation; misc other typesetting fixes
    % 3/3/96 change countleaves to count-leaves (makes things fit)
    % 3/3/96 fix bug in poly gcd footnote (pointed out by Albert Meyer)
    % 2/26-3/2/96 fix some bad line breaks
    % 2/24/96 flush \noindent after {lisp} by closing up space with 
    % 2/24/96 fix loose footnote (#49)
    % 2/23/96 move 8-queens fig into ex to avoid extra inter-ex space
    % 2/22/96 new spec for epigraph
    % 2/21/96 fixed format of a tabular
    % 2/19/96 fixed () in a reference
  </HISTORY>

  <EPIGRAPH>

    We now come to the decisive step of mathematical abstraction: we
    forget about what the symbols stand for. <ELLIPSIS/> [The mathematician]
    need not be idle; there are many operations which he may carry out
    with these symbols, without ever having to look at the things they
    stand for.

    <INDEX>Weyl, Hermann</INDEX>
    <ATTRIBUTION><AUTHOR>Hermann Weyl</AUTHOR>
      <TITLE>The Mathematical Way of Thinking</TITLE>
    </ATTRIBUTION>

  </EPIGRAPH>

  <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

  <TEXT>
    <INDEX>compound data, need for|(</INDEX>
    <INDEX>data<SUBINDEX>compound|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    We concentrated in chapter<SPACE/>1 on computational processes and on the
    role of
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    in program design.  We saw how to use primitive
    data (numbers) and primitive operations (arithmetic operations), how to
    combine
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    to form compound
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    through composition,
    conditionals, and the use of parameters, and how to abstract
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>processes</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    by using <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function declarations</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  
      We saw that a
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    can be
    regarded as a pattern for the local evolution of a process, and we
    classified, reasoned about, and performed simple algorithmic analyses
    of some common patterns for processes as embodied in
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  We
    also saw that higher-order
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    enhance the power of our
    language by enabling us to manipulate, and thereby to reason in terms
    of, general methods of computation.  This is much of the essence of
    programming.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    In this chapter we are going to look at more complex data.  All the
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    in chapter<SPACE/>1 operate on simple numerical data, and simple
    data are not sufficient for many of the problems we wish to address
    using computation.  Programs are typically designed to model complex
    phenomena, and more often than not one must construct computational
    objects that have several parts in order to model real-world phenomena
    that have several aspects.  Thus, whereas our focus in chapter<SPACE/>1 was
    on building abstractions by combining
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    to form compound
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, we turn in this chapter to another key aspect of any
    programming language: the means it provides for building abstractions
    by combining data objects to form <EM>compound data</EM>.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    Why do we want compound data in a programming language?  For the same
    reasons that we want compound
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>: to elevate the conceptual
    level at which we can design our programs, to increase the modularity
    of our designs, and to enhance the expressive power of our language.
    Just as the ability to 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>define procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>declare functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    enables us to deal with
    processes at a higher conceptual level than that of the primitive
    operations of the language, the ability to construct compound data
    objects enables us to deal with data at a higher conceptual level than
    that of the primitive data objects of the language.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    <INDEX>rational-number arithmetic<SUBINDEX>need for compound data</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    Consider the task of designing a system to perform arithmetic with
    rational numbers.  We could imagine an operation <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>add-rat</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>add_rat</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> that takes
    two rational numbers and produces their sum.  In terms of
    simple data, a rational number can be thought of as two integers: a
    numerator and a denominator.  Thus, we could design a program in which
    each rational number would be represented by two integers (a numerator
    and a denominator) and where
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>add-rat</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>add_rat</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    would be implemented by two
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    (one producing the numerator of the sum and one producing
    the denominator).  But this would be awkward, because we would then
    need to explicitly keep track of which numerators corresponded to
    which denominators.  In a system intended to perform many operations
    on many rational numbers, such bookkeeping details would clutter the
    programs substantially, to say nothing of what they would do to our
    minds.  It would be much better if we could <QUOTE>glue together</QUOTE> a
    numerator and denominator to form a pair<EMDASH/>a <EM>compound data
      object</EM><EMDASH/>that our programs could manipulate in a way that would be
    consistent with regarding a rational number as a single conceptual
    unit.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    The use of compound data also enables us to increase the modularity of
    our programs.  If we can manipulate rational numbers directly as
    objects in their own right, then we can separate the part of our
    program that deals with rational numbers per se from the details of
    how rational numbers may be represented as pairs of integers.  The
    general technique of isolating the parts of a program that deal with
    how data objects are represented from the parts of a program that deal
    with how data objects are used is a powerful design methodology called
    <INDEX>data abstraction</INDEX>
    <EM>data abstraction</EM>.  We will see how data abstraction makes
    programs much easier to design, maintain, and modify.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    The use of compound data leads to a real increase in the expressive
    power of our programming language.  Consider the idea of forming a
    <QUOTE>linear combination</QUOTE> <LATEXINLINE>$ax+by$</LATEXINLINE>.  We might like to write a
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    that would accept <LATEXINLINE>$a$</LATEXINLINE>, <LATEXINLINE>$b$</LATEXINLINE>, <LATEXINLINE>$x$</LATEXINLINE>, and <LATEXINLINE>$y$</LATEXINLINE> as arguments and return the
    value of <LATEXINLINE>$ax+by$</LATEXINLINE>.  This presents no difficulty if the arguments are to
    be numbers, because we can readily 
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>define the procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>declare the function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>

    <SNIPPET>
      <EXAMPLE>linear_combination_example</EXAMPLE>
      <SCHEME>
(define (linear-combination a b x y) 
   (+ (* a x) (* b y)))
      </SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
function linear_combination(a, b, x, y) {
    return a * x + b * y;
}
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>
    <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
      <NAME>linear_combination_example</NAME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
linear_combination(1, 2, 3, 4);
</JAVASCRIPT>
</SNIPPET>

  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    But suppose we are not concerned only with numbers.  Suppose we would
    like to <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>express, in procedural terms, the idea that one can form</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>describe a process that forms</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    linear combinations whenever addition and multiplication are
    defined<EMDASH/>for rational numbers, complex numbers, polynomials, or
    whatever.  We could express this as a
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    of the form

    <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
      <SCHEME>
(define (linear-combination a b x y)
   (add (mul a x) (mul b y)))
      </SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
function linear_combination(a, b, x, y) {
    return add(mul(a, x), mul(b, y));
}
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>

    where <SCHEMEINLINE>add</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>mul</SCHEMEINLINE> are not the primitive
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEMEINLINE>+</SCHEMEINLINE>
    and <SCHEMEINLINE>*</SCHEMEINLINE> but rather more complex things that will perform the
    appropriate operations for whatever kinds of data we pass in as the
    arguments <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE>. The key point is
    that the only thing <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>linear-combination</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>linear_combination</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> should need to know about
    <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> is that the
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEMEINLINE>add</SCHEMEINLINE>
    and <SCHEMEINLINE>mul</SCHEMEINLINE> will perform the appropriate manipulations.  From the
    perspective of the
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>linear-combination</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>linear_combination</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, it is
    irrelevant what <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> are and even
    more irrelevant how they might happen to be represented in terms of
    more primitive data.  This same example shows why it is important that
    our programming language provide the ability to manipulate compound
    objects directly: Without this, there is no way for a
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    such
    as <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>linear-combination</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>linear_combination</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> to pass its arguments along to <SCHEMEINLINE>add</SCHEMEINLINE>
    and <SCHEMEINLINE>mul</SCHEMEINLINE> without having to know their detailed
    structure.<FOOTNOTE>The ability to directly manipulate
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      provides an analogous increase in the expressive power of a
      programming language.  For example, in
      section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:procedures-as-parameters"/> we introduced the <SCHEMEINLINE>sum</SCHEMEINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, which takes a
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      <SCHEMEINLINE>term</SCHEMEINLINE> as an argument and
      computes the sum of the values of <SCHEMEINLINE>term</SCHEMEINLINE> over some specified
      interval.  In order to define <SCHEMEINLINE>sum</SCHEMEINLINE>, it is crucial that we be able
      to speak of a
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      such as <SCHEMEINLINE>term</SCHEMEINLINE> as an entity in its own
      right, without regard for how <SCHEMEINLINE>term</SCHEMEINLINE> might be expressed with more
      primitive operations.  Indeed, if we did not have the notion of <QUOTE>a
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>,</QUOTE> it is doubtful that we would ever even think of the
      possibility of defining an operation such as <SCHEMEINLINE>sum</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Moreover,
      insofar as performing the summation is concerned, the details of how
      <SCHEMEINLINE>term</SCHEMEINLINE> may be constructed from more primitive operations are
      irrelevant.</FOOTNOTE>
    <INDEX>compound data, need for|)</INDEX>
    <INDEX>data<SUBINDEX>compound|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    We begin this chapter by implementing the rational-number arithmetic
    system mentioned above.  This will form the background for our
    discussion of compound data and data abstraction.  As with compound
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, the main issue to be addressed is that of abstraction as a
    technique for coping with complexity, and we will see how data
    abstraction enables us to erect suitable 
    <INDEX>abstraction barriers</INDEX>
    <EM>abstraction barriers</EM>
    between different parts of a program.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    We will see that the key to forming compound data is that a
    programming language should provide some kind of <QUOTE>glue</QUOTE> so that data
    objects can be combined to form more complex data objects.  There are
    many possible kinds of glue.  Indeed, we will discover how to form
    compound data using no special <QUOTE>data</QUOTE> operations at all, only
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  This will further blur the distinction between
    <QUOTE><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></QUOTE> and <QUOTE>data,</QUOTE> which was already becoming tenuous toward
    the end of chapter<SPACE/>1.  We will also explore some conventional
    techniques for representing sequences and trees.  One key idea in
    dealing with compound data is the notion of 
    <INDEX>closure</INDEX>
    <EM>closure</EM><EMDASH/>that the
    glue we use for combining data objects should allow us to combine not
    only primitive data objects, but compound data objects as well.
    Another key idea is that compound data objects can serve as 
    <INDEX>conventional interface</INDEX>
    <EM>
      conventional interfaces</EM> for combining program modules in
    mix-and-match ways.  We illustrate some of these ideas by presenting a
    simple graphics language that exploits closure.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    We will then augment the representational power of our language by
    introducing 
    <INDEX>symbolic expression</INDEX><INDEX>expression<SUBINDEX>symbolic</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <EM>symbolic expressions</EM><EMDASH/>data whose elementary parts
    can be arbitrary symbols rather than only numbers.  We explore various
    alternatives for representing sets of objects.  We will find that,
    just as a given numerical function can be computed by many different
    computational processes, there are many ways in which a given data
    structure can be represented in terms of simpler objects, and the
    choice of representation can have significant impact on the time and
    space requirements of processes that manipulate the data.  We will
    investigate these ideas in the context of symbolic differentiation,
    the representation of sets, and the encoding of information.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    Next we will take up the problem of working with data that may be
    represented differently by different parts of a program.  This leads
    to the need to implement 
    <INDEX>generic operation</INDEX>
    <INDEX>operation<SUBINDEX>generic</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <EM>generic operations</EM>, which must handle
    many different types of data.  Maintaining modularity in the
    presence of generic operations requires more powerful abstraction
    barriers than can be erected with simple data abstraction alone.  In
    particular, we introduce <EM>data-directed programming</EM> as a
    technique that allows individual data representations to be designed
    in isolation and then combined 
    <INDEX>additivity</INDEX>
    <EM>additively</EM> (i.e., without
    modification).  To illustrate the power of this approach to system
    design, we close the chapter by applying what we have learned to the
    implementation of a package for performing symbolic arithmetic on
    polynomials, in which the coefficients of the polynomials can be
    integers, rational numbers, complex numbers, and even other
    polynomials.
  </TEXT>

  <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

  <!-- Section 1 : Introduction to Data Abstraction -->
  &section2.1;

  <!-- Section 2 : Hierarchical Data and the Closure Property -->
  &section2.2;

  <!-- Section 3 : Symbolic Data -->
  &section2.3;

  <!-- Section 4 : Multiple Representations for Abstract Data -->
  &section2.4;

  <!-- Section 5 : Systems with Generic Operations -->
  &section2.5;

</CHAPTER>
