  <SECTION>
    <NAME>Hierarchical Data and the Closure Property</NAME>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>

    <LABEL NAME="sec:hierarchical-data"/>
    <TEXT>
      As we have seen, pairs provide a primitive <QUOTE>glue</QUOTE> that we can use to
      construct compound data objects.
      Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:first-box-and-pointer"/> shows a standard way to
      visualize a 
      <INDEX>pair(s)<SUBINDEX>box-and-pointer notation for</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      pair<EMDASH/>in this case, the pair formed by <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cons 1 2)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair(1,2)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.

      <SPLIT>
	<SCHEME>
              <FIGURE src="img_original/ch2-Z-G-11.svg">
                <LABEL NAME="fig:first-box-and-pointer"/>
                <CAPTION>Box-and-pointer representation of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cons 1 2)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair(1,2)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
                </CAPTION>
              </FIGURE>

      In this representation, which is called 
      <INDEX>box-and-pointer notation</INDEX>
      <EM>box-and-pointer
        notation</EM>, each object is shown as a 
      <INDEX>pointer<SUBINDEX>in box-and-pointer notation</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>pointer</EM> to a box.  The box
      for a primitive object contains a representation of the object.  For
      example, the box for a number contains a numeral.  The box for a pair
      is actually a double box, the left part containing (a pointer to) the
      <SCHEMEINLINE>car</SCHEMEINLINE> of the pair and the right part containing
      the <SCHEMEINLINE>cdr</SCHEMEINLINE>.
	</SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT>

              <FIGURE src="img_javascript/ch2-Z-G-11.svg">
                <LABEL NAME="fig:first-box-and-pointer"/>
                <CAPTION>Box-and-pointer representation of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cons 1 2)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair(1,2)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
                </CAPTION>
              </FIGURE>

      In this representation, which is called 
      <INDEX>box-and-pointer notation</INDEX>
      <EM>box-and-pointer
        notation</EM>, each compound object is shown as a 
      <INDEX>pointer<SUBINDEX>in box-and-pointer notation</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>pointer</EM> to a box.  The box for a pair
      has two parts, the left part containing the head of the pair and the
      right part containing the tail.<FOOTNOTE>In this JavaScript adaptation, we choose
      to draw primitive objects directly inside of the boxes of the pairs that contain
      them, in an attempt to be consistent with a similar practice introduced in
      section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:environment-model"/>. The box-and-pointer diagrams
      in the original version of the textbook include separate boxes for primitive
      objects, such as 1 and 2, each containing a representation of the object.</FOOTNOTE>
	  
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SPLIT>


    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      We have already seen that <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> can be used to combine not
      only numbers but pairs as well.  (You made use of this fact, or
      should have, in doing exercises<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:segments1"/>
      and<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:rectangles"/>.)  As a consequence, pairs provide a universal
      building block from which we can construct all sorts of data
      structures.  Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:box-and-pointer-two-ways"/> 
      shows two ways to use pairs to combine the numbers 1, 2, 3, and 4.

      <SPLIT>
	<SCHEME>
              <FIGURE src="img_original/ch2-Z-G-12.svg">
                <LABEL NAME="fig:box-and-pointer-two-ways"/>
                <CAPTION>Two ways to combine 1, 2, 3, and 4 using pairs.
                </CAPTION>
              </FIGURE>
	</SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT>
              <FIGURE src="img_javascript/ch2-Z-G-12.svg">
                <LABEL NAME="fig:box-and-pointer-two-ways"/>
                <CAPTION>Two ways to combine 1, 2, 3, and 4 using pairs.
                </CAPTION>
              </FIGURE>
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SPLIT>
    </TEXT>


    <TEXT>
      The ability to create pairs whose elements are pairs is the essence of
      list structure<APOS/>s importance as a representational tool.  We refer to
      this ability as the 
      <INDEX>closure<SUBINDEX>closurecons@closure property of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <!--\indprim{cons}[closure property of]-->
      <EM>closure property</EM> of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  In general,
      an operation for combining data objects satisfies the closure property
      if the results of combining things with that operation can themselves
      be combined using the same 
      operation.<FOOTNOTE>The use of the word 
        <INDEX>closure<SUBINDEX>abstract@in abstract algebra</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        <QUOTE>closure</QUOTE> here comes from abstract algebra,
        where a set of elements is said to be closed under an operation if
        applying the operation to elements in the set produces an element that
        is again an element of the set.  The Lisp community
        also (unfortunately) uses the word <QUOTE>closure</QUOTE> to describe a totally unrelated
        concept: A closure is an implementation technique for representing
        <SPLITINLINE>
	  <SCHEME>procedures with free variables.
	  </SCHEME>
	  <JAVASCRIPT>functions with free names.
	  </JAVASCRIPT>
	</SPLITINLINE>
	We do not use the word <QUOTE>closure</QUOTE> in
        this second sense in this book.</FOOTNOTE>
      Closure is the key to power in
      any means of combination because it permits us to create 
      <INDEX>hierarchical data structures</INDEX>
      <INDEX>data<SUBINDEX>hierarchical</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>
        hierarchical</EM> structures<EMDASH/>structures made up of parts, which
      themselves are made up of parts, and so on.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      From the outset of chapter<SPACE/>1, we<APOS/>ve made essential use of closure in
      dealing with
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, because all but the very simplest programs
      rely on the fact that the elements of a combination can themselves be
      combinations.  In this section, we take up the consequences of closure
      for compound data.  We describe some conventional techniques for using
      pairs to represent sequences and trees, and we exhibit a graphics
      language that illustrates closure in a vivid 
      way.<FOOTNOTE>The notion that a means of
        <INDEX>closure<SUBINDEX>lack of in many languages</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        combination should satisfy closure is a straightforward idea.
        Unfortunately, the data combiners provided in many popular programming
        languages do not satisfy closure, or make closure cumbersome to
        exploit.  In 
        <INDEX>Fortran<SUBINDEX>restrictions on compound data</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        Fortran or 
        <INDEX>Basic<SUBINDEX>restrictions on compound data</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        Basic, one typically combines data elements by
        assembling them into arrays<EMDASH/>but one cannot form arrays whose
        elements are themselves arrays.  
        <INDEX>Pascal<SUBINDEX>restrictions on compound data</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        Pascal and 
        <INDEX>C<SUBINDEX>restrictions on compound data</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        C admit structures whose
        elements are structures.  However, this requires that the programmer
        manipulate pointers explicitly, and adhere to the restriction that
        each field of a structure can contain only elements of a prespecified form.
        Unlike
        Lisp with its pairs, these languages have no built-in general-purpose
        glue that makes it easy to manipulate compound data in a uniform way.
        This limitation lies behind Alan 
        <INDEX>Perlis, Alan J.</INDEX>
        Perlis<APOS/>s comment in his foreword to
        this book: <QUOTE>In Pascal the plethora of declarable data structures
          induces a specialization within functions that inhibits and penalizes
          casual cooperation.  It is better to have 100 functions operate on one
          data structure than to have 10 functions operate on 10 data
          structures.</QUOTE></FOOTNOTE>
    </TEXT>

    <!-- Subsection 1 : Representing Sequences -->
    &subsection2.2.1;

    <!-- Subsection 2 : Hierarchical Structures -->
    &subsection2.2.2;

    <!-- Subsection 3 : Sequences as Conventional Interfaces -->
    &subsection2.2.3;

    <!-- Subsection 4 : Example: A Picture Language -->
    &subsection2.2.4;

  </SECTION>
