  <SECTION>
    <NAME>Assignment and Local State</NAME>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>

    <LABEL NAME="sec:assignment"/>
    <INDEX>assignment|(</INDEX>
    <INDEX>local state|(</INDEX>

    <TEXT>
      We ordinarily view the world as populated by independent objects, each
      of which has a state that changes over time.  An object is said to
      <QUOTE>have state</QUOTE> if its behavior is influenced by its history.  A bank
      account, for example, has state in that the answer to the question
      <QUOTE>Can I withdraw <DOLLAR/>100?</QUOTE>  depends upon the history of deposit and
      withdrawal transactions.  We can characterize an object<APOS/>s state by one
      or more 
      <INDEX>state variable</INDEX>
      <EM>state variables</EM>, which among them maintain enough
      information about history to determine the object<APOS/>s current behavior.
      In a simple banking system, we could characterize the state of an
      account by a current balance rather than by remembering the entire
      history of account transactions.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      In a system composed of many objects, the objects are rarely
      completely independent.  Each may influence the states of others
      through interactions, which serve to couple the state variables of one
      object to those of other objects.  Indeed, the view that a system is
      composed of separate objects is most useful when the state variables
      of the system can be grouped into closely coupled subsystems that are
      only loosely coupled to other subsystems.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      This view of a system can be a powerful framework for organizing
      computational models of the system.  For such a model to be modular,
      it should be decomposed into computational objects that model the
      actual objects in the system.  Each computational object must have its
      own <EM>local state variables</EM> describing the actual object<APOS/>s state.
      Since the states of objects in the system being modeled change over
      time, the state variables of the corresponding computational objects
      must also change.  If we choose to model the flow of time in the
      system by the elapsed time in the computer, then we must have a way to
      construct computational objects whose behaviors change as our programs
      run.  In particular, if we wish to model state variables by ordinary
      symbolic names in the programming language, then the language must
      provide an 
      <INDEX>assignment operator</INDEX>
      <EM>assignment operator</EM> to enable us to change the value
      associated with a name.
    </TEXT>

    <!-- Subsection 1 : Local State Variables -->
    &subsection3.1.1;

    <!-- Subsection 2 : The Benefits of Introducing Assignment -->
    &subsection3.1.2;

    <!-- Subsection 3 : The Costs of Introducing Assignment -->
    &subsection3.1.3;

  </SECTION>
