  <SECTION>
    <NAME>Designing Register Machines</NAME>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>

    <LABEL NAME="sec:designing-register-machines"/>
    <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>design of|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>data paths|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>controller|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>data paths for register machine|(</INDEX>
    <INDEX>controller for register machine|(</INDEX>
    <INDEX>operation<SUBINDEX>in register machine|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

    <TEXT>
      To design a register machine, we must design its <EM>data paths</EM>
      (registers and operations) and the <EM>controller</EM> that sequences
      these operations.  To illustrate the design of a simple register
      machine, let us examine Euclid<APOS/>s Algorithm, which is used to compute
      <!--  \indcode{gcd}[register machine for|(] -->
      the greatest common divisor (GCD) of two integers.  As we saw in
      <INDEX>Euclid<APOS/>s Algorithm</INDEX>
      section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:gcd"/>, Euclid<APOS/>s Algorithm can be carried out by an iterative
      process, as specified by the following
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>:

      <SNIPPET>
  <SCHEME>
    (define (gcd a b)
    (if (= b 0)
    a
    (gcd b (remainder a b))))
  </SCHEME>
  <JAVASCRIPT>
function gcd(a, b) {
    return b === 0 ? a : gcd(b, a % b);
}
  </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      A machine to carry out this algorithm must keep track of two numbers,
      <LATEXINLINE>$a$</LATEXINLINE> and <LATEXINLINE>$b$</LATEXINLINE>, so let us assume that these numbers are stored in two
      registers with those names.  The basic operations required are testing
      whether the contents of register <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> is zero and computing the
      remainder of the contents of register <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> divided by the contents
      of register <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>.  The remainder operation is a complex process,
      but assume for the moment that we have a primitive device that
      computes remainders.  On each cycle of the GCD algorithm, the contents
      of register <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> must be replaced by the contents of register <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>, and the contents of <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> must be replaced by the remainder of
      the old contents of <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> divided by the old contents of <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>.
      It would be convenient if these replacements could be done
      simultaneously, but in our model of register machines we will assume
      that only one register can be assigned a new value at each step.  To
      accomplish the replacements, our machine will use a third
      <QUOTE>temporary</QUOTE> register, which we call <SCHEMEINLINE>t</SCHEMEINLINE>.  (First the remainder
      will be placed in <SCHEMEINLINE>t</SCHEMEINLINE>, then the contents of <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> will be placed
      in <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>, and finally the remainder stored in <SCHEMEINLINE>t</SCHEMEINLINE> will be placed
      in <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>.)
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      <INDEX>data paths for register machine<SUBINDEX>data-path diagram</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>data-path diagram</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      We can illustrate the registers and operations required for this
      machine by using the data-path diagram shown in
      figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:gcd-machine"/>.  In this
      diagram, the registers (<SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>t</SCHEMEINLINE>) are represented
      by rectangles.  Each way to assign a value to a register is
      indicated by an arrow with an <SCHEMEINLINE>X</SCHEMEINLINE> behind the head, pointing from
      the source of data to the register.  We can think of the <SCHEMEINLINE>X</SCHEMEINLINE> as a
      button that, when pushed, allows the value at the source to <QUOTE>flow</QUOTE>
      into the designated register.  The label next to each button is the
      name we will use to refer to the button.  The names are arbitrary, and
      can be chosen to have mnemonic value (for example, <SCHEMEINLINE>a&lt;-b</SCHEMEINLINE> denotes
      pushing the button that assigns the contents of register <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> to
      register <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>).  The source of data for a register can be another
      register (as in the <SCHEMEINLINE>a&lt;-b</SCHEMEINLINE> assignment), an operation result (as in
      the <SCHEMEINLINE>t&lt;-r</SCHEMEINLINE> assignment), or a constant (a built-in value that
      cannot be changed, represented in a data-path diagram by a triangle
      containing the constant).
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      An operation that computes a value from constants and the contents
      of registers is represented in a data-path diagram by a trapezoid
      containing a name for the operation.  For example, the box marked <SCHEMEINLINE>rem</SCHEMEINLINE> in figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:gcd-machine"/> represents an
      operation that computes the remainder of the contents of the
      registers <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> to which it is attached.  Arrows
      (without buttons) point from the input registers and constants to the
      box, and arrows connect the operation<APOS/>s output value to registers.
      A test is represented by a circle containing a name for the test.  For
      example, our GCD machine has an operation that
      tests whether the contents of register
      <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE> is zero.  A test also has arrows from its input
      <INDEX>test operation in register machine</INDEX>
      <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>test operation</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      registers and constants, but it has no output
      arrows; its value is used by the controller rather than by the data
      paths.  Overall, the data-path diagram shows the registers and
      operations that are required for the machine and how they must be
      connected.  If we view the arrows as wires and the <SCHEMEINLINE>X</SCHEMEINLINE> buttons as
      switches, the data-path diagram is very like the wiring diagram for a
      machine that could be constructed from electrical components.
      
      <FIGURE>
	<FIGURE src="img_original/Fig5.1a.std.svg"/>
        <LABEL NAME="fig:gcd-machine"/>
        <CAPTION>Data paths for a GCD machine. </CAPTION>
      </FIGURE>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>controller diagram</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>controller for register machine<SUBINDEX>controller diagram</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      In order for the data paths to actually compute GCDs, the buttons must
      be pushed in the correct sequence.  We will describe this sequence in
      terms of a controller diagram, as illustrated in
      figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:gcd-controller"/>.  The elements of the controller
      diagram indicate how the
      data-path components should be operated.  The rectangular boxes in the
      controller diagram identify data-path buttons to be pushed, and the
      arrows describe the sequencing from one step to the next.  The diamond
      in the diagram represents a decision.  One of the two sequencing
      arrows will be followed, depending on the value of the data-path test
      identified in the diamond.  We can interpret the controller in terms
      of a physical analogy: Think of the diagram as a maze in which a
      marble is rolling.  When the marble rolls into a box, it pushes the
      data-path button that is named by the box.  When the marble rolls into
      a decision node (such as the test for <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE><LATEXINLINE>$\, =0$</LATEXINLINE>), it leaves the
      node on the path determined by the result of the indicated test.
      Taken together, the data paths and the controller completely describe
      a machine for computing GCDs.  We start the controller (the rolling
      marble) at the place marked <SCHEMEINLINE>start</SCHEMEINLINE>, after placing numbers in
      registers <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>.  When the controller reaches <SCHEMEINLINE>done</SCHEMEINLINE>, we will find the value of the GCD in register <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>.
      <!--  \indcode{gcd}[register machine for|)] -->

      <FIGURE>
	<FIGURE src="img_original/Fig5.2.std.svg"/>
        <LABEL NAME="fig:gcd-controller"/>
        <CAPTION>Controller for a GCD machine.</CAPTION>
      </FIGURE>
    </TEXT>

    <EXERCISE><LABEL NAME="ex:iterative-fact"/>
      <!--  \indcode{factorial}[register machine for (iterative)] -->
      Design a register machine to compute factorials using the iterative
      algorithm specified by the following
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Draw data-path and
      controller diagrams for this machine.

      <SNIPPET>
  <SCHEME>
    (define (factorial n)
    (define (iter product counter)
    (if (&gt; counter n)
          product
          (iter (* counter product)
          (+ counter 1))))
    (iter 1 1))
  </SCHEME>
  <JAVASCRIPT>
function factorial(n) {
    function iter(product, counter) {
        return counter &gt; n 
               ? product
               : iter(counter * product,
                      counter + 1);
   }
   return iter(1, 1);
}    
  </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
    </EXERCISE>
    <INDEX>data paths for register machine|)</INDEX>
    <INDEX>controller for register machine|)</INDEX>
    <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>data paths|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>controller|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>operation<SUBINDEX>in register machine|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

    <!-- Subsection 1 : A Language for Describing Register Machines -->
    &subsection5.1.1;

    <!-- Subsection 2 : Abstraction in Machine Design -->
    &subsection5.1.2;

    <!-- Subsection 3 : Subroutines -->
    &subsection5.1.3;

    <!-- Subsection 4 : Using a Stack to Implement Recursion -->
    &subsection5.1.4;

    <!-- Subsection 5 : Instruction Summary -->
    &subsection5.1.5;

  </SECTION>
