    <SUBSECTION>
      <NAME>
  Using a Stack to Implement Recursion
      </NAME>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:stack-recursion"/>
      <INDEX>stack<SUBINDEX>recursion@for recursion in register machine|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>stack|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>recursive process<SUBINDEX>register machine for|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>iterative process<SUBINDEX>register machine for</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  With the ideas illustrated so far, we can implement any iterative
  process by specifying a register machine that has a register
  corresponding to each state variable of the process.  The machine
  repeatedly executes a controller loop, changing the contents
  of the registers, until some termination condition is satisfied.  At
  each point in the controller sequence, the state of the machine
  (representing the state of the iterative process) is completely
  determined by the contents of the registers (the values of the state
  variables).
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>recursive process<SUBINDEX>iterative process vs.</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>iterative process<SUBINDEX>recursive process vs.</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <!--  \indcode{factorial}[register machine for (recursive)|(] -->
  Implementing recursive processes, however, requires an additional
  mechanism.  Consider the following recursive method for computing
  factorials, which we first examined in
  section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:recursion-and-iteration"/>:

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (define (factorial n)
      (if (= n 1)
      1
      (* (factorial (- n 1)) n)))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
function factorial(n) {
    return n === 1 
           ? 1
           : n * factorial(n - 1);
}      
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  As we see from the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, computing <LATEXINLINE>$n!$</LATEXINLINE> requires computing
  <LATEXINLINE>$(n-1)!$</LATEXINLINE>.  Our GCD machine, modeled on the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (define (gcd a b)
      (if (= b 0)
      a
      (gcd b (remainder a b))))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
function gcd(a, b) {
    return b === 0 ? a : gcd(b, a % b);
}
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  similarly had to compute another GCD.  But there is an important
  difference between the <SCHEMEINLINE>gcd</SCHEMEINLINE>
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, which reduces the original
  computation to a new GCD computation, and <SCHEMEINLINE>factorial</SCHEMEINLINE>, which
  requires computing another factorial as a subproblem.  In GCD, the
  answer to the new GCD computation is the answer to the original
  problem.  To compute the next GCD, we simply place the new arguments
  in the input registers of the GCD machine and reuse the
  machine<APOS/>s data paths by executing the same controller sequence.  When
  the machine is finished solving the final GCD problem, it has
  completed the entire computation.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  In the case of factorial (or any recursive process) the answer to the
  new factorial subproblem is not the answer to the original problem.
  The value obtained for <LATEXINLINE>$(n-1)!$</LATEXINLINE> must be multiplied by <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE> to get the
  final answer.  If we try to imitate the GCD design, and solve
  the factorial subproblem by decrementing the <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE> register and
  rerunning the factorial machine, we will no longer have available the
  old value of <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE> by which to multiply the result.  We thus need a
  second factorial machine to work on the subproblem.  This second
  factorial computation itself has a factorial subproblem, which
  requires a third factorial machine, and so on.  Since each factorial
  machine contains another factorial machine within it, the total
  machine contains an infinite nest of similar machines and hence cannot
  be constructed from a fixed, finite number of parts.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Nevertheless, we can implement the factorial process as a register
  machine if we can arrange to use the same components for each nested
  instance of the machine.  Specifically, the machine that computes <LATEXINLINE>$n!$</LATEXINLINE>
  should use the same components to work on the subproblem of computing
  <LATEXINLINE>$(n-1)!$</LATEXINLINE>, on the subproblem for <LATEXINLINE>$(n-2)!$</LATEXINLINE>, and so on.  This is
  plausible because, although the factorial process dictates that an
  unbounded number of copies of the same machine are needed to perform a
  computation, only one of these copies needs to be active at any given
  time.  When the machine encounters a recursive subproblem, it can
  suspend work on the main problem, reuse the same physical parts to
  work on the subproblem, then continue the suspended computation.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  In the subproblem, the contents of the registers will be different
  than they were in the main problem. (In this case the <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE> register
  is decremented.)  In order to be able to continue the suspended
  computation, the machine must save the contents of any registers that
  will be needed after the subproblem is solved so that these can be
  restored to continue the suspended computation.  In the case of
  factorial, we will save the old value of <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE>, to be restored when
  we are finished computing the factorial of the decremented <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE>
  register.<FOOTNOTE>One might argue that we don<APOS/>t need to save the old
    <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE>; after we decrement it and solve the subproblem, we could
    simply increment it to recover the old value.  Although this strategy
    works for factorial, it cannot work in general, since the old value of
    a register cannot always be computed from the new one.</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Since there is no <EM>a priori</EM> limit on the depth of nested
  recursive calls, we may need to save an arbitrary number of register
  values.  These values must be restored in the reverse of the order in
  which they were saved, since in a nest of recursions the last
  subproblem to be entered is the first to be finished.  This dictates
  the use of a <EM>stack</EM>, or <QUOTE>last in, first out</QUOTE> data structure, to
  save register values.  We can extend the register-machine language to
  include a stack by adding two kinds of instructions: Values are placed
  <INDEX>register-machine language<SUBINDEX>save@<SCHEMEINLINE>save</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <!-- \indcodeplus{save}{(in register machine)}-->
  <INDEX>register-machine language<SUBINDEX>restore@<SCHEMEINLINE>restore</SCHEMEINLINE></SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <!-- \indcodeplus{restore}{(in register machine)}-->
  on the stack using a <SCHEMEINLINE>save</SCHEMEINLINE> instruction and restored from the
  stack using a <SCHEMEINLINE>restore</SCHEMEINLINE> instruction.  After a sequence of values
  has been <SCHEMEINLINE>save</SCHEMEINLINE>d on the stack, a sequence of <SCHEMEINLINE>restore</SCHEMEINLINE>s will
  retrieve these values in reverse order.<FOOTNOTE>In
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:storage-allocation"/> we will see how to implement a
    stack in terms of more primitive operations.</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  With the aid of the stack, we can reuse a single copy of the factorial
  machine<APOS/>s data paths for each factorial subproblem.  There is a
  similar design issue in reusing the controller sequence that operates
  the data paths.  To reexecute the factorial computation, the
  controller cannot simply loop back to the beginning, as with
  an iterative process, because after solving the <LATEXINLINE>$(n-1)!$</LATEXINLINE> subproblem
  the machine must still multiply the result by <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>.  The controller
  must suspend its computation of <LATEXINLINE>$n!$</LATEXINLINE>, solve the <LATEXINLINE>$(n-1)!$</LATEXINLINE> subproblem,
  then continue its computation of <LATEXINLINE>$n!$</LATEXINLINE>.  This view of the factorial
  computation suggests the use of the subroutine mechanism described in
  section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:subroutines"/>, which has the controller use a
  <!-- \indcodeplus{continue}{register}[recursion and]-->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> register to transfer to the part of the sequence that
  solves a subproblem and then continue where it left off on the main
  problem.  We can thus make a factorial subroutine that returns to the
  entry point stored in the <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> register.  Around each subroutine
  call, register, since each <QUOTE>level</QUOTE> of the factorial computation will use
  the same <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> register.  That is, the factorial subroutine
  must put a new value in <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> when it calls itself for a
  subproblem, but it will need the old value in order to return to the
  place that called it to solve a subproblem.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:fact-machine"/> shows the data paths and controller for
  a machine that implements the recursive <SCHEMEINLINE>factorial</SCHEMEINLINE>
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
  The machine has a stack and three registers, called <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>val</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE>.  To simplify the data-path diagram, we have
  not named the register-assignment buttons, only the stack-operation
  buttons (<SCHEMEINLINE>sc</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>sn</SCHEMEINLINE> to save registers, <SCHEMEINLINE>rc</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>rn</SCHEMEINLINE> to restore registers).  To operate the machine, we put in register
  <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE> the number whose factorial we wish to compute and start the
  machine.  When the machine reaches <SCHEMEINLINE>fact-done</SCHEMEINLINE>, the computation is
  finished and the answer will be found in the <SCHEMEINLINE>val</SCHEMEINLINE> register.  In
  the controller sequence, <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> are saved before
  each recursive call and restored upon return from the call.  Returning
  from a call is accomplished by branching to the location stored in
  <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE>.  <SCHEMEINLINE>Continue</SCHEMEINLINE> is initialized when the machine starts
  so that the last return will go to <SCHEMEINLINE>fact-done</SCHEMEINLINE>.  The <SCHEMEINLINE>val</SCHEMEINLINE>
  register, which holds the result of the factorial computation, is not
  saved before the recursive call, because the old contents of <SCHEMEINLINE>val</SCHEMEINLINE>
  is not useful after the subroutine returns.  Only the new value, which
  is the value produced by the subcomputation, is needed.
  <!--  \indcode{factorial}[register machine for (recursive)|)] -->
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Although in principle the factorial computation requires an infinite
  machine, the machine in Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:fact-machine"/> is actually
  finite except for the stack, which is potentially unbounded.  Any
  particular physical implementation of a stack, however, will be of
  finite size, and this will limit the depth of recursive calls that can
  be handled by the machine.  This implementation of factorial
  illustrates the general strategy for realizing recursive algorithms as
  ordinary register machines augmented by stacks.  When a recursive
  subproblem is encountered, we save on the stack the registers whose
  current values will be required after the subproblem is solved, solve
  the recursive subproblem, then restore the saved registers and
  continue execution on the main problem.  The <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> register
  must always be saved.  Whether there are other registers that need to
  be saved depends on the particular machine, since not all recursive
  computations need the original values of registers that are modified
  during solution of the subproblem (see exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:design-reg-machines"/>).
      </TEXT>


      <SUBHEADING>
  <NAME>A double recursion</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <TEXT>
  <!--  \indcode{fib}[register machine for (tree-recursive)] -->
  Let us examine a more complex recursive process, the tree-recursive
  computation of the Fibonacci numbers, which we introduced in
  section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:tree-recursion"/>:
  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (define (fib n)
      (if (&lt; n 2)
      n
      (+ (fib (- n 1)) (fib (- n 2)))))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
function fib(n) {
    return n === 0
           ? 0
           : n === 1
             ? 1
             : fib(n - 1) + fib(n - 2);
}
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Just as with factorial, we can implement the recursive Fibonacci
  computation as a register machine with registers <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>val</SCHEMEINLINE>,
  and <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE>.  The machine is more complex than the one for
  factorial, because there are two places in the controller sequence
  where we need to perform recursive calls<EMDASH/>once to compute Fib<LATEXINLINE>$(n-1)$</LATEXINLINE>
  and once to compute Fib<LATEXINLINE>$(n-2)$</LATEXINLINE>.  To set up for each of these calls, we
  save the registers whose values will be needed later, set the <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE>
  register to the number whose Fib we need to compute recursively (<LATEXINLINE>$n-1$</LATEXINLINE>
  or <LATEXINLINE>$n-2$</LATEXINLINE>), and assign to <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> the entry point in the main sequence
  to which to return (<SCHEMEINLINE>afterfib-n-1</SCHEMEINLINE> or <SCHEMEINLINE>afterfib-n-2</SCHEMEINLINE>,
  respectively).  We then go to <SCHEMEINLINE>fib-loop</SCHEMEINLINE>.  When we return from the
  recursive call, the answer is in <SCHEMEINLINE>val</SCHEMEINLINE>.
  Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:fib-machine"/> shows the controller sequence for this
  machine.

  <SPLIT>
    <SCHEME>
      <FIGURE src="img_original/Fig5.11b.std.svg">
        <SNIPPET>
          <SCHEME>
    <!-- 
        %(registers n val continue)
        %(operations * - =)
      -->
      (controller
      (assign continue (label fact-done))     <EM>; set up final return address</EM>
      fact-loop
      (test (op =) (reg n) (const 1))
      (branch (label base-case))
      <EM>;; Set up for the recursive call by saving <SCHEMEINLINE>n</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE>.</EM>
      <EM>;; Set up <SCHEMEINLINE>continue</SCHEMEINLINE> so that the computation will continue</EM>
      <EM>;; at <SCHEMEINLINE>after-fact</SCHEMEINLINE> when the subroutine returns.</EM>
      (save continue)
      (save n)
      (assign n (op -) (reg n) (const 1))
      (assign continue (label after-fact))
      (goto (label fact-loop))
      after-fact
      (restore n)
      (restore continue)
      (assign val (op *) (reg n) (reg val))   ; val ^now contains $n(n-1)!$^
      (goto (reg continue))                   ; ^return to caller^
      base-case
      (assign val (const 1))                  ; ^base case: $1!=1$^
      (goto (reg continue))                   ; ^return to caller^
      fact-done)
          </SCHEME>
        </SNIPPET>
        <CAPTION>A recursive factorial machine.</CAPTION>
        <!--  \indcode{factorial}[register machine for (recursive)] -->
        <LABEL NAME="fig:fact-machine"/>
      </FIGURE>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <FIGURE> 
	<FIGURE src="img_javascript/Fig5.11b.std.svg"/> 
        <SNIPPET>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
controller(
    list(      
       assign("continue", label("fact-done")), // set up final return address
       "fact-loop",
       test(list(op("="), reg("n"), constant(1))),
       branch(label("base-case")),
       // Set up for the recursive call by saving "n" and "continue".
       // Set up "continue" so that the computation will continue
       // at "after-fact" when the subroutine returns.
       save("continue"),
       save("n"),
       assign("n", list(op("-"), reg("n"), const(1))),
       assign("continue", label("after-fact")),
       go_to(label("fact-loop")),
       "after-fact",
       restore("n"),
       restore("continue"),
       assign("val", list(op("*"), reg("n"), reg("val"))),
       // "val" now contains n(n-1)!
       go_to(reg("continue")),        // return to caller
       "base-case",
       assign("val", constant(1)),       // base case: val = 1
       go_to(reg("continue")),        // return to caller
       "fact-done"));
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SNIPPET>
        <CAPTION>A recursive factorial machine.</CAPTION>
        <!--  \indcode{factorial}[register machine for (recursive)] -->
        <LABEL NAME="fig:fact-machine"/>
      </FIGURE>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLIT>

  <FIGURE>
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <!-- 
        %(registers n val continue)
        %(operations &lt; - +)
      -->
    <SCHEME>
      (controller
      (assign continue (label fib-done))
      fib-loop
      (test (op &lt;) (reg n) (const 2))
      (branch (label immediate-answer))
      ;; set up to compute ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-1)$^
      (save continue)
      (assign continue (label afterfib-n-1))
      (save n)                            ; save old value of ^$n$^
      (assign n (op -) (reg n) (const 1)) ; clobber ^$n$^ to ^$n-1$^
      (goto (label fib-loop))             ; perform recursive call
      afterfib-n-1                          ; upon return, ^val^ contains ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-1)$^
      (restore n)
      (restore continue)
      ;; set up to compute ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-2)$^
      (assign n (op -) (reg n) (const 2))
      (save continue)
      (assign continue (label afterfib-n-2))
      (save val)                          ; save ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-1)$^
      (goto (label fib-loop))
      afterfib-n-2                          ; upon return, ^val^ contains ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-2)$^
      (assign n (reg val))                ; ^$n$^ now contains ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-2)$^
      (restore val)                       ; ^val^ now contains ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-1)$^
      (restore continue)
      (assign val                         ; ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n-1)+{\textrm{Fib}}(n-2)$^
            (op +) (reg val) (reg n)) 
      (goto (reg continue))               ; return to caller, answer is in ^val^
      immediate-answer
      (assign val (reg n))                ; base case: ^${\textrm{Fib}}(n)=n$^
      (goto (reg continue))
      fib-done)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
controller(
    list(      
       assign("continue", label("fib-done")),
       "fib-loop",
       test(list(op("&lt;"), reg("n"), constant(2))),
       branch(label("immediate-answer")),
       // set up to compute Fib(n-1)
       save("continue"),
       assign("continue", label("afterfib-n-1")),
       save("n"),                  // save old value of n
                                   // clobber n to n - 1       
       assign("n", list(op("-"), reg("n"), constant(1))), 
       go_to(label("fib-loop")),   // perform recursive call
       "afterfib-n-1",                                
                                   // upon return, "val" contains Fib(n-1)
       restore("n"),
       restore("continue"),        // set up to compute Fib(n-2)
       assign("n", list(op("-"), reg("n"), constant(2))),
       save("continue"),
       assign("continue", label("afterfib-n-2")),
       save("val"),                // save Fib(n-1)
       go_to(label("fib-loop")),
       "afterfib-n-2",             // upon return, "val" contains Fib(n-2)
       assign("n", reg("val")),    // "n" now contains Fib(n-2)
       restore("val"),             // "val" now contains Fib(n-1)
       restore("continue"),
       assign("val",               // Fib(n-1) + Fib(n-2)
           list(op("+"), reg("val"), reg("n"))),
       go_to(reg("continue")),     // return to caller, answer is in "val"
       "immediate-answer",
       assign("val", reg("n")),    // base case: Fib(n) = n
       go_to(reg("continue")),
       "fib-done"));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
  <CAPTION>Controller for a machine to compute Fibonacci numbers.</CAPTION>
  <LABEL NAME="fig:fib-machine"/>
  </FIGURE>
      </TEXT>

      <EXERCISE><LABEL NAME="ex:design-reg-machines"/>
  Specify register machines that implement each of the following
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  For each machine, write a controller instruction sequence
  and draw a diagram showing the data paths.
  <OL>
    <LI>
      Recursive exponentiation:

      <SNIPPET>
        <SCHEME>
    <!--  \indcode{expt}[register machine for] -->
    (define (expt b n)
    (if (= n 0)
    1
    (* b (expt b (- n 1)))))
        </SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT>
function expt(b, n) {
    return n === 0
        ? 1
        : b * expt(b, n - 1);
}
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
    </LI>
    <LI>
      Iterative exponentiation:

      <SNIPPET>
        <SCHEME>
    (define (expt b n)
    (define (expt-iter counter product)
    (if (= counter 0)
    product
    (expt-iter (- counter 1) (* b product))))
    (expt-iter n 1))
        </SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT>
function expt(b, n) {	  
    function expt_iter(counter, product) {
        return counter === 0
            ? product
            : expt_iter(counter - 1, b * product);
    }
    return expt_iter(n, 1);
}
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
    </LI>
  </OL>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  Hand-simulate the factorial and Fibonacci machines, using some
  nontrivial input (requiring execution of at least one recursive call).
  Show the contents of the stack at each significant point in the
  execution.
  <LABEL NAME="ex:hand-sim"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  Ben Bitdiddle observes that the Fibonacci machine<APOS/>s controller sequence
  has an extra <SCHEMEINLINE>save</SCHEMEINLINE> and an extra <SCHEMEINLINE>restore</SCHEMEINLINE>, which can be
  removed to make a faster machine.  Where are these instructions?
      </EXERCISE>
      <INDEX>stack<SUBINDEX>recursion@for recursion in register machine|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>register machine<SUBINDEX>stack|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>recursive process<SUBINDEX>register machine for|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

    </SUBSECTION>
