    <SUBSECTION>
      <NAME>
        Example: Huffman Encoding Trees
      </NAME>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:huffman"/>
      <INDEX>Huffman code|(</INDEX>

      <TEXT>
      This section provides practice in the use of list structure and data
      abstraction to manipulate sets and trees.  The application is to
      methods for representing data as sequences of ones and zeros (bits).
      For example, the
      <INDEX>ASCII code</INDEX>
      <INDEX>code<SUBINDEX>ASCII</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      ASCII standard code used to represent text in
      computers encodes each
      <INDEX>character, ASCII encoding</INDEX>
      character as a sequence of seven bits.  Using
      seven bits allows us to distinguish <LATEXINLINE>$2^7$</LATEXINLINE>, or 128, possible different
      characters.  In general, if we want to distinguish <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE> different
      symbols, we will need to use <LATEXINLINE>$\log_2 n$</LATEXINLINE> bits per symbol.  If all our
      messages are made up of the eight symbols A, B, C, D, E, F, G, and H,
      we can choose a code with three bits per character, for example
      <FIGURE src="img_tex/ch2_3_4-1.png"></FIGURE>
      With this code, the message
      <BLOCKQUOTE>
BACADAEAFABBAAAGAH
      </BLOCKQUOTE>
      is encoded as the string of 54 bits
      <BLOCKQUOTE>
001000010000011000100000101000001001000000000110000111
      </BLOCKQUOTE>
      Codes such as ASCII and the A-through-H code above are known as
      <INDEX>fixed-length code</INDEX>
      <INDEX>code<SUBINDEX>fixed-length</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>fixed-length</EM> codes, because they represent each symbol in the message
      with the same number of bits.  It is sometimes advantageous to use
      <INDEX>variable-length code</INDEX>
      <INDEX>code<SUBINDEX>variable-length</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>variable-length</EM> codes, in which different symbols may be
      represented by different numbers of bits.  For example,
      <INDEX>Morse code</INDEX>
      <INDEX>code<SUBINDEX>Morse</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      Morse code
      does not use the same number of dots and dashes for each letter of the
      alphabet.  In particular, E, the most frequent letter, is represented
      by a single dot.  In general, if our messages are such that some
      symbols appear very frequently and some very rarely, we can encode
      data more efficiently (i.e., using fewer bits per message) if we
      assign shorter codes to the frequent symbols.  Consider the following
      alternative code for the letters A through H:

      <FIGURE src="img_tex/ch2_3_4-2.png"></FIGURE>

      With this code, the same message as above is encoded as the string
      <BLOCKQUOTE>
100010100101101100011010100100000111001111
      </BLOCKQUOTE>
      This string contains 42 bits, so it saves more than 20% in space in
      comparison with the fixed-length code shown above.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      One of the difficulties of using a variable-length code is knowing
      when you have reached the end of a symbol in reading a sequence of
      zeros and ones.  Morse code solves this problem by using a special
      <INDEX>separator code</INDEX>
      <EM>separator code</EM> (in this case, a pause) after the sequence of
      dots and dashes for each letter.  Another solution is to design the
      code in such a way that no complete code for any symbol is the
      beginning (or <EM>prefix</EM>) of the code for another symbol.  Such a
      code is called a
      <INDEX>prefix code</INDEX>
      <INDEX>code<SUBINDEX>prefix</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>prefix code</EM>.  In the example above, A is
      encoded by 0 and B is encoded by 100, so no other symbol can have a
      code that begins with 0 or with 100.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      In general, we can attain significant savings if we use
      variable-length prefix codes that take advantage of the relative
      frequencies of the symbols in the messages to be encoded.  One
      particular scheme for doing this is called the Huffman encoding
      method, after its discoverer,
      <INDEX>Huffman, David</INDEX>
      David Huffman.  A Huffman code can be
      represented as a
      <INDEX>binary tree<SUBINDEX>for Huffman encoding</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>tree<SUBINDEX>Huffman</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      binary tree whose leaves are the symbols that are
      encoded.  At each non-leaf node of the tree there is a set containing
      all the symbols in the leaves that lie below the node.  In addition,
      each symbol at a leaf is assigned a weight (which is its
      relative frequency), and each non-leaf
      node contains a weight that is the sum of all the weights of the
      leaves lying below it.  The weights are not used in the encoding or
      the decoding process.  We will see below how they are used to help
      construct the tree.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      <FIGURE>
        <FIGURE src="img_original/ch2-Z-G-53.svg"></FIGURE>
        <CAPTION>A Huffman encoding tree.</CAPTION>
        <LABEL NAME="fig:huffman"/>
      </FIGURE>
      Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:huffman"/> shows the Huffman tree for the A-through-H
      code given above.  The weights at the leaves
      indicate that the tree was designed for messages in which A appears
      with relative frequency 8, B with relative frequency 3, and the
      other letters each with relative frequency 1.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      Given a Huffman tree, we can find the encoding of any symbol by
      starting at the root and moving down until we reach the leaf that
      holds the symbol.  Each time we move down a left branch we add a 0 to
      the code, and each time we move down a right branch we add a 1.  (We
      decide which branch to follow by testing to see which branch either is
      the leaf node for the symbol or contains the symbol in its set.)  For
      example, starting from the root of the tree in
      Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:huffman"/>, we arrive at the leaf for D by following a
      right branch, then a left branch, then a right branch, then a right
      branch; hence, the code for D is 1011.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      To decode a bit sequence using a Huffman tree, we begin at the root
      and use the successive zeros and ones of the bit sequence to determine
      whether to move down the left or the right branch.  Each time we come
      to a leaf, we have generated a new symbol in the message, at which
      point we start over from the root of the tree to find the next symbol.
      For example, suppose we are given the tree above and the sequence
      10001010.  Starting at the root, we move down the right branch, (since
      the first bit of the string is<SPACE/>1), then down the left branch (since
      the second bit is<SPACE/>0), then down the left branch (since the third bit
      is also<SPACE/>0).  This brings us to the leaf for<SPACE/>B, so the first symbol of
      the decoded message is<SPACE/>B.  Now we start again at the root, and we make
      a left move because the next bit in the string is<SPACE/>0.  This brings us
      to the leaf for<SPACE/>A.  Then we start again at the root with the rest of
      the string 1010, so we move right, left, right, left and reach<SPACE/>C.
      Thus, the entire message is BAC.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
        <NAME>Generating Huffman trees</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <TEXT>
      Given an <QUOTE>alphabet</QUOTE> of symbols and their relative frequencies, how
      do we construct the <QUOTE>best</QUOTE> code?  (In other words, which tree will
      encode messages with the fewest bits?)  Huffman gave an algorithm for
      doing this and showed that the resulting code is indeed the best
      variable-length code for messages where the relative frequency of the
      symbols matches the frequencies with which the code was constructed.
      <INDEX>optimality<SUBINDEX>of Huffman code</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>Huffman code<SUBINDEX>optimality of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      We will not prove this optimality of Huffman codes here, but we will
      show how Huffman trees are constructed.<FOOTNOTE>See
        <CITATION>Hamming 1980</CITATION>
        <INDEX>Hamming, Richard Wesley</INDEX>
        for a discussion of the mathematical properties of Huffman codes.</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      The algorithm for generating a Huffman tree is very simple. The idea
      is to arrange the tree so that the symbols with the lowest frequency
      appear farthest away from the root. Begin with the set of leaf nodes,
      containing symbols and their frequencies, as determined by the initial data
      from which the code is to be constructed. Now find two leaves with
      the lowest weights and merge them to produce a node that has these
      two nodes as its left and right branches. The weight of the new node
      is the sum of the two weights. Remove the two leaves from the
      original set and replace them by this new node. Now continue this
      process. At each step, merge two nodes with the smallest weights,
      removing them from the set and replacing them with a node that has
      these two as its left and right branches. The process stops when
      there is only one node left, which is the root of the entire tree.
      Here is how the Huffman tree of Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:huffman"/> was generated:
      <SPLIT>
        <SCHEME>

      <FIGURE src="img_tex/ch2_3_4-3.png"></FIGURE>

        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>


      <FIGURE src="img_tex/ch2_3_4-3.png"></FIGURE>

        </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SPLIT>
      The algorithm does not always specify a unique tree, because there may
      not be unique smallest-weight nodes at each step.  Also, the choice of
      the order in which the two nodes are merged (i.e., which will be the
      right branch and which will be the left branch) is arbitrary.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
        <NAME>Representing Huffman trees</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <TEXT>
      In the exercises below we will work with a system that uses
      Huffman trees to encode and decode messages and generates Huffman
      trees according to the algorithm outlined above.  We will begin by
      discussing how trees are represented.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      Leaves of the tree are represented by a list consisting of the
      symbol <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>leaf</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>leaf</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, the symbol at the leaf, and the weight:

      <SNIPPET>
        <NAME>make_leaf</NAME>
	<EXAMPLE>make_leaf_example</EXAMPLE>
        <SCHEME>
          <!-- \indcode*{make-leaf} -->
(define (make-leaf symbol weight)
  (list 'leaf symbol weight))

          <!-- \indcode*{leaf?} -->
(define (leaf? object)
  (eq? (car object) 'leaf))

          <!-- \indcode*{symbol-leaf} -->
(define (symbol-leaf x) (cadr x))

          <!-- \indcode*{weight-leaf} -->
(define (weight-leaf x) (caddr x))
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
function make_leaf(symbol, weight) {
   return list("leaf", symbol, weight);
}
function is_leaf(object) {
   return head(object) === "leaf";
}
function symbol_leaf(x) {
  return head(tail(x));
}
function weight_leaf(x) {
   return head(tail(tail(x)));
}
        </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>

      <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
        <NAME>make_leaf_example</NAME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
const my_leaf = make_leaf("A", 8);

weight_leaf(my_leaf);
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>

      
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      A general tree will be a list of a left branch, a right branch, a set
      of symbols, and a weight.  The set of symbols will be simply a list of
      the symbols, rather than some more sophisticated set representation.
      When we make a tree by merging two nodes, we obtain the weight of the
      tree as the sum of the weights of the nodes, and the set of symbols as
      the union of the sets of symbols for the nodes.  Since our symbol sets are
      represented as lists, we can form the union by using the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>append</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      we defined in section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:sequences"/>:

      <SNIPPET>
        <NAME>make_code_tree</NAME>
        <EXAMPLE>make_code_tree_example</EXAMPLE>
        <REQUIRES>tree_property</REQUIRES>
        <SCHEME>
          <!-- \indcode*{make-code-tree} -->
(define (make-code-tree left right)
  (list left
    right
    (append (symbols left) (symbols right))
    (+ (weight left) (weight right))))
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
function make_code_tree(left,right) {
    return list(left,
                right,
                append(symbols(left), symbols(right)),
                weight(left) + weight(right));
}
      </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>

      <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
        <NAME>make_code_tree_example</NAME>
        <SCHEME>
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
const my_leaf_1 = make_leaf("A", 8);
const my_leaf_2 = make_leaf("B", 3);

make_code_tree(my_leaf_1, my_leaf_2);
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
      
      If we make a tree in this way, we have the following selectors:

      <SNIPPET>
        <NAME>tree_property</NAME>
        <REQUIRES>make_leaf</REQUIRES>
	<EXAMPLE>tree_property_example</EXAMPLE>
        <SCHEME>
          <!-- \indcode*{left-branch} -->
(define (left-branch tree) (car tree))

          <!-- \indcode*{right-branch} -->
(define (right-branch tree) (cadr tree))

          <!-- \indcode*{symbols} -->
(define (symbols tree)
  (if (leaf? tree)
    (list (symbol-leaf tree))
    (caddr tree)))

          <!-- \indcode*{weight} -->
(define (weight tree)
  (if (leaf? tree)
    (weight-leaf tree)
    (cadddr tree)))
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
function left_branch(tree) {
    return head(tree);
}
function right_branch(tree) {
    return head(tail(tree));
}
function symbols(tree) {
    return is_leaf(tree)
           ? list(symbol_leaf(tree))
           : head(tail(tail(tree)));
}
function weight(tree) {
    return is_leaf(tree)
           ? weight_leaf(tree)
           : head(tail(tail(tail(tree))));
}
        </JAVASCRIPT>
       </SNIPPET>

      <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
        <NAME>tree_property_example</NAME>
        <REQUIRES>make_code_tree</REQUIRES>
        <REQUIRES>make_leaf</REQUIRES>
	<EXAMPLE>tree_property_example</EXAMPLE>
	<JAVASCRIPT>
const my_leaf_1 = make_leaf("A", 8);
const my_leaf_2 = make_leaf("B", 3);
const my_tree = make_code_tree(my_leaf_1, my_leaf_2);

weight(my_tree);
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      The
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>symbols</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>symbols</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>weight</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>weight</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> must do something
      slightly different depending on whether they are called with a leaf or
      a general tree.  These are simple examples of
      <INDEX>generic
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></INDEX>
      <INDEX><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE><SUBINDEX>generic</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <EM>generic
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></EM> (<SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      that can handle more than one kind of data),
      which we will have much more to say about in
      sections<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:multiple-reps"/> and<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:generic-operators"/>.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
        <NAME>The decoding
          <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <TEXT>
      The following
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      implements the decoding algorithm.
      It takes as arguments a list of zeros and ones, together with
      a Huffman tree.

      <SNIPPET>
        <NAME>decode_function</NAME>
        <REQUIRES>make_leaf</REQUIRES>
        <REQUIRES>make_code_tree</REQUIRES>
        <REQUIRES>tree_property</REQUIRES>
        <EXAMPLE>decode_function_example</EXAMPLE>
        <REQUIRES>Error</REQUIRES>
        <SCHEME>
          <!-- \indcode*{decode} -->
(define (decode bits tree)
  (define (decode-1 bits current-branch)
    (if (null? bits)
      '()
      (let ((next-branch
              (choose-branch (car bits) current-branch)))
        (if (leaf? next-branch)
          (cons (symbol-leaf next-branch)
                (decode-1 (cdr bits) tree))
          (decode-1 (cdr bits) next-branch)))))
  (decode-1 bits tree))

(define (choose-branch bit branch)
  (cond ((= bit 0) (left-branch branch))
        ((= bit 1) (right-branch branch))
        (else (error "bad bit -- CHOOSE-BRANCH" bit))))
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
function decode(bits, tree) {
    function decode_1(bits, current_branch) {
        if (is_null(bits)) {
            return null;
        } else {
            const next_branch = choose_branch(head(bits),
                                    current_branch);
            return is_leaf(next_branch)
                   ? pair(symbol_leaf(next_branch),
                          decode_1(tail(bits), tree))
                   : decode_1(tail(bits), next_branch);
        }
    }
    return decode_1(bits, tree);
}
function choose_branch(bit, branch) {
    return bit === 0
           ? left_branch(branch)
           : bit === 1
             ? right_branch(branch)
             : Error("bad bit -- choose_branch",bit);
}
        </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>


     <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
        <NAME>decode_function_example</NAME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
const my_leaf_1 = make_leaf("A", 8);
const my_leaf_2 = make_leaf("B", 3);

const my_tree = make_code_tree(my_leaf_1, my_leaf_2);

decode(list(0, 1, 1, 0), my_tree);
	</JAVASCRIPT>
     </SNIPPET>
      
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      The
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>decode-1</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>decode_1</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> takes two arguments: the list of remaining bits
      and the current position in the tree.  It keeps moving
      <QUOTE>down</QUOTE> the tree, choosing a left or a right branch according to
      whether the next bit in the list is a zero or a one.  (This is done
      with the
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>choose-branch</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>choose_branch</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.)  When it reaches a leaf, it
      returns the symbol at that leaf as the next symbol in the message by
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>ing it onto the result of decoding
      the rest of the message, starting at the root of the tree.
      Note the error check in the final clause of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>choose-branch</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>choose_branch</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, which
      complains if the
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      finds something other than a zero or a one in the
      input data.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
        <NAME>Sets of weighted elements</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <TEXT>
      In our representation of trees, each non-leaf node contains a set of
      symbols, which we have represented as a simple list.  However, the
      tree-generating algorithm discussed above requires that we also work
      with sets of leaves and trees, successively merging the two smallest
      items.  Since we will be required to repeatedly find the smallest item
      in a set, it is convenient to use an ordered representation for this
      kind of set.
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      We will represent a set of leaves and trees as a list of elements,
      arranged in increasing order of weight.
      The following
      <SPLITINLINE>
	<SCHEME>
	<SCHEMEINLINE>adjoin-set</SCHEMEINLINE>
	</SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT>
	  <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>adjoin_set</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SPLITINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      for constructing sets is similar to the one
      described in exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:adjoin-set"/>; however, items are compared
      by their weights, and the element being added to the set is
      never already in it.

      <SNIPPET>
        <NAME>adjoin_set3</NAME>
        <REQUIRES>tree_property</REQUIRES>
        <EXAMPLE>adjoin_set3_example</EXAMPLE>
        <SCHEME>
          <!-- \indcode*{adjoin-set}[weighted@for weighted sets] -->
(define (adjoin-set x set)
  (cond ((null? set) (list x))
        ((&lt; (weight x) (weight (car set))) (cons x set))
        (else (cons (car set)
                    (adjoin-set x (cdr set))))))
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
function adjoin_set(x, set) {
    return is_null(set)
           ? list(x)
           : weight(x) &lt; weight(head(set))
             ? pair(x, set)
             : pair(head(set), adjoin_set(x, tail(set)));
}
      </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>

     <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
        <NAME>adjoin_set3_example</NAME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
const my_leaf_1 = make_leaf("A", 8);
const my_leaf_2 = make_leaf("B", 3);

adjoin_set(my_leaf_1, adjoin_set(my_leaf_2, null));
	</JAVASCRIPT>
     </SNIPPET>
      
      </TEXT>
      <TEXT>
      The following
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      takes a list of
      symbol-frequency pairs such as
      <SPLITINLINE>
	<SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((A 4) (B 2) (C 1) (D 1))</SCHEMEINLINE>
	</SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT>
	  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
	    <JAVASCRIPT>
list(list("A", 4), list("B", 2), list("C", 1), list("D", 1))
	    </JAVASCRIPT>
	  </SNIPPET>
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SPLITINLINE>
      and constructs an initial ordered set of leaves, ready to be merged
      according to the Huffman algorithm:

      <SNIPPET>
        <NAME>make_leaf_set</NAME>
        <REQUIRES>make_leaf</REQUIRES>
        <REQUIRES>adjoin_set3</REQUIRES>
	<EXAMPLE>make_leaf_set_example</EXAMPLE>
        <SCHEME>
          <!-- \indcode*{make-leaf-set} -->
(define (make-leaf-set pairs)
  (if (null? pairs)
    '()
    (let ((pair (car pairs)))
      (adjoin-set (make-leaf (car pair)    ; symbol
                             (cadr pair))  ; frequency
                  (make-leaf-set (cdr pairs))))))
        </SCHEME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
function make_leaf_set(pairs) {
   if (is_null(pairs)) {
      return null;
   }
   else {
      const first_pair = head(pairs);
      return adjoin_set(
                 make_leaf(head(first_pair),        // symb
                           head(tail(first_pair))), // freq
                 make_leaf_set(tail(pairs)));
   }
}
        </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>

      <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
        <NAME>make_leaf_set_example</NAME>
        <JAVASCRIPT>
make_leaf_set( list( make_leaf("A", 4),
                     make_leaf("B", 2),
                     make_leaf("C", 1),
                     make_leaf("D", 1) ) );
	</JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <EXERCISE>
        Define an encoding tree and a sample message:

        <SNIPPET>
	  <NAME>sample_tree</NAME>
          <REQUIRES>make_leaf</REQUIRES>
          <REQUIRES>make_code_tree</REQUIRES>
          <SCHEME>
(define sample-tree
  (make-code-tree (make-leaf 'A 4)
                  (make-code-tree
                    (make-leaf 'B 2)
                    (make-code-tree (make-leaf 'D 1)
                                    (make-leaf 'C 1)))))

(define sample-message '(0 1 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 1 1 0))
          </SCHEME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
const sample_tree =
    make_code_tree(make_leaf("A",4),
        make_code_tree(make_leaf("B",2),
            make_code_tree(make_leaf("D",1),
                make_leaf("C",1))));
const sample_message =						 
    list(0, 1, 1, 0, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 1, 1, 0);
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SNIPPET>

        Use the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>decode</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>decode</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        to decode the
        message, and give the result.
        <LABEL NAME="ex:sample-tree"/>

	<SOLUTION>
	  <SNIPPET>
          <REQUIRES>decode_function</REQUIRES>
	  <REQUIRES>sample_tree</REQUIRES>
	    <JAVASCRIPT>
decode(sample_message, sample_tree);
// should be: ["A", ["D", ["A", ["B", ["B", ["C", ["A", null]]]]]]]
	    </JAVASCRIPT>
	  </SNIPPET>
	  
	</SOLUTION>
	
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE><LABEL NAME="ex:encode-symbol"/>
        The <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>encode</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>encode</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        takes as arguments a message and a tree and
        produces the list of bits that gives the encoded message.

        <SNIPPET>
          <NAME>encode</NAME>
          <REQUIRES>encode_symbol</REQUIRES>
          <SCHEME>
            <!-- \indcode*{encode} -->
(define (encode message tree)
  (if (null? message)
    '()
    (append (encode-symbol (car message) tree)
            (encode (cdr message) tree))))
          </SCHEME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
function encode(message, tree) {
    return is_null(message)
           ? null
           : append(encode_symbol(head(message), tree),
                    encode(tail(message), tree));
}
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SNIPPET>
<SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
  <NAME>encode_symbol</NAME>
  <JAVASCRIPT>
// encode_symbol function to be written by students
  </JAVASCRIPT>
</SNIPPET>

        <SPLIT><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>Encode-symbol</SCHEMEINLINE> is a procedure,
            which you must write, that returns the list of bits that encodes a given symbol
            according to a given tree.
          </SCHEME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>Write the function <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>encode_symbol</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
            that returns the list of bits that encodes a given symbol according to a given tree.
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SPLIT>
        You should design <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>encode-symbol</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>encode_symbol</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> so that it signals an
        error if the symbol is not in the tree at all.  Test your
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        by
        encoding the result you obtained in exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:sample-tree"/> with
        the sample tree and seeing whether it is the same as the original
        sample message.

	<SOLUTION>

	  <SNIPPET>
	    <NAME>encode_symbol_solution</NAME>
	    <EXAMPLE>encode_symbol_example</EXAMPLE>
	    <JAVASCRIPT>
function encode_symbol(symbol, tree) {
    function contains_symbol(symbol, current_tree) {
        return member(symbol, symbols(current_tree)) !== null;
    }
    if (is_leaf(tree)) {
        return null;
    } else {
        const left_tree = left_branch(tree);
	const right_tree = right_branch(tree);
	return contains_symbol(symbol, left_tree)
               ? pair(0, encode_symbol(symbol, left_tree))
                 : contains_symbol(symbol, right_tree)
                   ? pair(1, encode_symbol(symbol, right_tree))
                   : error("symbol not found");
    }
}
	    </JAVASCRIPT>
	  </SNIPPET>

	  <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
	    <NAME>encode_symbol_example</NAME>
	    <REQUIRES>decode_function</REQUIRES>
	    <REQUIRES>encode</REQUIRES>
	    <REQUIRES>sample_tree</REQUIRES>
	    <REQUIRES>is_equal</REQUIRES>
	    <JAVASCRIPT>
is_equal(encode(decode(sample_message, sample_tree),
                sample_tree),
         sample_message);
	    </JAVASCRIPT>
	  </SNIPPET>
	  
	</SOLUTION>

      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
        The following
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        takes as its argument a list of
        symbol-frequency pairs (where no symbol appears in more than one pair)
        and generates a Huffman encoding tree according to the Huffman
        algorithm.

        <SNIPPET>
	  <NAME>generate_huffman_tree</NAME>
          <REQUIRES>make_leaf_set</REQUIRES>
          <REQUIRES>successive_merge</REQUIRES>
          <SCHEME>
            <!-- \indcode*{generate-huffman-tree} -->
(define (generate-huffman-tree pairs)
  (successive-merge (make-leaf-set pairs)))
          </SCHEME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
function generate_huffman_tree(pairs) {
   return successive_merge(make_leaf_set(pairs));
}
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SNIPPET>

<SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
<NAME>successive_merge</NAME>
<JAVASCRIPT>
// successive_merge function to be written by student
</JAVASCRIPT>
</SNIPPET>

        <SPLIT>
          <SCHEME>
            <SCHEMEINLINE>Make-leaf-set</SCHEMEINLINE> is the procedure
            given above that transforms the
        list of pairs into an ordered set of leaves.  <SCHEMEINLINE>Successive-merge</SCHEMEINLINE>
            is the procedure
            you must write, using <SCHEMEINLINE>make-code-tree</SCHEMEINLINE> to
            successively merge the smallest-weight elements of the set until there
            is only one element left, which is the desired Huffman tree.
          </SCHEME>
          <JAVASCRIPT>
            The function <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>make_leaf_set</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> 
            that transforms the
            list of pairs into an ordered set of leaves is given above.
            Write the function <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>successive_merge</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
            using <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>make_code_tree</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> to
            successively merge the smallest-weight elements of the set until there
            is only one element left, which is the desired Huffman tree.
          </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SPLIT>
        (This
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        is slightly tricky, but not really complicated.  If you find
        yourself designing a complex
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, then you are almost certainly
        doing something wrong.  You can take significant advantage of the fact
        that we are using an ordered set representation.)
        <LABEL NAME="ex:generate-huffman-tree"/>
  <SOLUTION>
    <SNIPPET>
      <NAME>successive_merge_solution</NAME>
      <REQUIRES>make_code_tree</REQUIRES>
      <REQUIRES>adjoin_set3</REQUIRES>
      <REQUIRES>generate_huffman_tree</REQUIRES>
      <EXAMPLE>generate_huffman_tree_example</EXAMPLE>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
function successive_merge(leaves) {
    return length(leaves) === 1
           ? head(leaves)
           : successive_merge(
                 adjoin_set(
                     make_code_tree(head(leaves),
                                    head(tail(leaves))),
                     tail(tail(leaves))));
}
    </JAVASCRIPT>
    <SCHEME>
    </SCHEME>
    </SNIPPET>

    <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
      <NAME>generate_huffman_tree_example</NAME>
      <REQUIRES>is_equal</REQUIRES>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
const sample_tree =
    make_code_tree(make_leaf("A", 4),
                   make_code_tree(
                       make_leaf("B", 2),
                       make_code_tree(
                           make_leaf("D", 1),
                           make_leaf("C", 1))));
const sample_frequencies = list(list("A", 4), 
                                list("B", 2), 
                                list("C", 1), 
                                list("D", 1));

is_equal(sample_tree, 
         generate_huffman_tree(sample_frequencies));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>
    
  </SOLUTION>


      </EXERCISE>


      <EXERCISE>
        <INDEX>rock songs, 1950s</INDEX>
        The following eight-symbol alphabet with associated relative
        frequencies was designed to efficiently encode the lyrics of 1950s
        rock songs.  (Note that the <QUOTE>symbols</QUOTE> of an <QUOTE>alphabet</QUOTE> need not be
        individual letters.)
        <FIGURE src="img_tex/ch2_3_4-4.png"></FIGURE>
        Use <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>generate-huffman-tree</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>generate_huffman_tree</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> (exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:generate-huffman-tree"/>)
        to generate a corresponding Huffman tree, and use
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>encode</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>encode</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> (exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:encode-symbol"/>)
        to encode the following message:

<P>
Get a job <BR/>
Sha na na na na na na na na <BR/>
Get a job <BR/>
Sha na na na na na na na na <BR/>
Wah yip yip yip yip yip yip yip yip yip <BR/>
Sha boom
</P>
        How many bits are required for the encoding?  What is the smallest
        number of bits that would be needed to encode this song if we
        used a fixed-length code for the eight-symbol alphabet?

	<SOLUTION>

	  <SNIPPET>
	    <REQUIRES>successive_merge_solution</REQUIRES>
	    <REQUIRES>generate_huffman_tree</REQUIRES>
	    <REQUIRES>encode_symbol_solution</REQUIRES>
	    <REQUIRES>encode</REQUIRES>
	    <JAVASCRIPT>
const lyrics_frequencies = 	  
    list(list("A", 2),
         list("NA", 16),
         list("BOOM", 1),
         list("SHA", 3),
         list("GET", 2),
         list("YIP", 9),
         list("JOB", 2),
         list("WAH", 2));
const lyrics_tree = generate_huffman_tree(lyrics_frequencies);
const lyrics = list(
    'GET', 'A', 'JOB',
    'SHA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA',
    'GET', 'A', 'JOB', 'SHA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 
    'NA', 'NA', 'NA', 'WAH', 'YIP', 'YIP', 'YIP', 'YIP',
    'YIP', 'YIP', 'YIP', 'YIP', 'YIP', 'SHA', 'BOOM'
   );
 
length(encode(lyrics, lyrics_tree));
// 84
	    </JAVASCRIPT>
	  </SNIPPET>
We have an alphabet of <LATEXINLINE>$n = 8$</LATEXINLINE> symbols,    
and a message of <LATEXINLINE>$m = 36$</LATEXINLINE> symbols.
Then the minimum number of bits to encode a specific symbol using a fixed-length
code is <LATEXINLINE>$\lceil \log_2{n} \rceil = 3$</LATEXINLINE>. Thus
the minimum number of bits to encode all the lyrics is 
<LATEXINLINE>$m \lceil \log_2{n} \rceil = 36 \times 3 = 108$</LATEXINLINE>.
	  
      </SOLUTION>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
        Suppose we have a Huffman tree for an alphabet of <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE> symbols, and
        that the relative frequencies of the symbols are 1, 2, 4, <ELLIPSIS/>,
        <LATEXINLINE>$2^{n-1}$</LATEXINLINE>.  Sketch the tree for <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>=5; for <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>=10.  In such a tree
        (for general <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>) how may bits are required to encode the most
        frequent symbol?  the least frequent symbol?
        <LABEL NAME="ex:huffman-count"/>
  <SOLUTION>
    <TEXT>
      The tree will be unbalanced, similar to the tree given in
      figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:unbalanced-tree"/>.
      Encoding the most frequent symbol requires one bit,
      whereas <LATEXINLINE>$n - 1$</LATEXINLINE>
      bits are required to encode the least frequent symbol.
    </TEXT>
  </SOLUTION>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
        <INDEX>Huffman code<SUBINDEX>order of growth of encoding</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        Consider the encoding
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        that you designed in
        exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:encode-symbol"/>.  What is the order of growth in the
        number of steps needed to encode a symbol?  Be sure to include the
        number of steps needed to search the symbol list at each node
        encountered.  To answer this question in general is difficult.
        Consider the special case where the relative frequencies of the <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>
        symbols are as described in exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:huffman-count"/>, and give
        the order of growth (as a function of <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>) of the number of steps
        needed to encode the most frequent and least frequent symbols in the
        alphabet.
    <SOLUTION>
Consider the special case in exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:encode-symbol"/>.
At each step down the
path of length <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>, we need to do a linear
search in a list of length <LATEXINLINE>$n, n-1, \ldots, 1$</LATEXINLINE>.
In the worst case, there are <LATEXINLINE>$O(n \times n / 2) = O(n^2)$</LATEXINLINE>
number of steps.
<LATEXINLINE>$O(n^2)$</LATEXINLINE>.
 </SOLUTION>
      </EXERCISE>
      <INDEX>Huffman code|)</INDEX>

    </SUBSECTION>
