    <SUBSECTION>
      <NAME>
  Lexical Addressing
      </NAME>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:lexical-addressing"/>
      <INDEX>compiler for Scheme<SUBINDEX>lexical addressing|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>lexical addressing|(</INDEX>
      <TEXT>
  One of the most common optimizations performed by compilers is the
  optimization of variable lookup.  Our compiler, as we have implemented
  it so far, generates code that uses the <SCHEMEINLINE>lookup-variable-value</SCHEMEINLINE>
  operation of the evaluator machine.  This searches for a variable by
  comparing it with each variable that is currently bound, working frame
  by frame outward through the run-time environment.  This search can be
  expensive if the frames are deeply nested or if there are many
  variables.  For example, consider the problem of looking up the value
  of <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> while evaluating the expression <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(* x y z)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> in an
  application of the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  that is returned by

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (let ((x 3) (y 4))
      (lambda (a b c d e)
      (let ((y (* a b x))
            (z (+ c d x)))
      (* x y z))))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Since a <SCHEMEINLINE>let</SCHEMEINLINE> expression is just syntactic sugar for a <SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE> combination, this expression is equivalent to

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      ((lambda (x y)
      (lambda (a b c d e)
      ((lambda (y z) (* x y z))
      (* a b x)
      (+ c d x))))
      3
      4)
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  Each time <SCHEMEINLINE>lookup-variable-value</SCHEMEINLINE> searches for <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE>, it must
  determine that the symbol <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> is not <SCHEMEINLINE>eq?</SCHEMEINLINE> to <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> or <SCHEMEINLINE>z</SCHEMEINLINE> (in the first frame), nor to <SCHEMEINLINE>a</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>b</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>c</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>d</SCHEMEINLINE>, or
  <SCHEMEINLINE>e</SCHEMEINLINE> (in the second frame).  We will assume, for the moment, that
  our programs do not use <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE><EMDASH/>that variables are
  bound only with <SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Because our language is 
  <INDEX>lexical scoping<SUBINDEX>environment structure and</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  lexically
  scoped, the run-time environment for any expression will have a
  structure that parallels the lexical structure of the program in which
  the expression appears.<FOOTNOTE>This is not true if we allow
    internal definitions, unless we scan them out.
    See exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:compile-internal-defs"/>.</FOOTNOTE>
  Thus, the compiler can know, when it analyzes the
  above expression, that each time the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  is applied the variable
  <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> in <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(* x y z)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> will be found two frames out from the
  current frame and will be the first variable in that frame.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>lexical addressing<SUBINDEX>lexical address</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  We can exploit this fact by inventing a new kind of variable-lookup
  operation, <SCHEMEINLINE>lexical-address-lookup</SCHEMEINLINE>, that takes as arguments an
  environment and a <EM>lexical address</EM> that consists of two numbers:
  a <EM>frame number</EM>, which specifies how many frames to pass over,
  and a <EM>displacement number</EM>, which specifies how many variables to
  pass over in that frame.  
  <!--  \indcode{lexical-address-lookup} -->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>Lexical-address-lookup</SCHEMEINLINE> will produce
  the value of the variable stored at that lexical address relative to
  the current environment.  If we add the <SCHEMEINLINE>lexical-address-lookup</SCHEMEINLINE>
  operation to our machine, we can make the compiler generate code that
  references variables using this operation, rather than <SCHEMEINLINE>lookup-variable-value</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Similarly, our compiled code can use a new
  <!--  \indcode{lexical-address-set!} -->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>lexical-address-set!</SCHEMEINLINE>  operation instead of <SCHEMEINLINE>set-variable-value!</SCHEMEINLINE>.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  In order to generate such code, the compiler must be able to determine
  the lexical address of a variable it is about to compile a reference
  to.  The lexical address of a variable in a program depends on where
  one is in the code.  For example, in the following program, the
  address of <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> in expression <LATEXINLINE>e1</LATEXINLINE> is (2,0)<EMDASH/>two frames back
  and the first variable in the frame.  At that point <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> is at
  address (0,0) and <SCHEMEINLINE>c</SCHEMEINLINE> is at address (1,2).  In expression
  <LATEXINLINE>e2</LATEXINLINE>,<LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> is at (1,0), <LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> is at (1,1), and <SCHEMEINLINE>c</SCHEMEINLINE> is at (0,2).

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      ((lambda (x y)
      (lambda (a b c d e)
      ((lambda (y z) ^e1^)
      ^e2^
      (+ c d x))))
      3
      4)
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>compile-time environment</INDEX>
  One way for the compiler to produce code that uses lexical addressing
  is to maintain a data structure called a <EM>compile-time
    environment</EM>.  This keeps track of which variables will be at which
  positions in which frames in the run-time environment when a
  particular variable-access operation is executed.  The compile-time
  environment is a list of frames, each containing a list of variables.
  (There will of course be no values bound to the variables, since
  values are not computed at compile time.)  The compile-time
  environment becomes an additional argument to <SCHEMEINLINE>compile</SCHEMEINLINE> and is
  passed along to each code generator.  The top-level call to <SCHEMEINLINE>compile</SCHEMEINLINE> uses an empty compile-time environment.
  When a <SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE> body is compiled, <SCHEMEINLINE>compile-lambda-body</SCHEMEINLINE>
  extends the compile-time environment by a frame containing the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE><APOS/>s parameters, so that the sequence making up the body
  is compiled with that extended environment.
  At each point in the compilation, <SCHEMEINLINE>compile-variable</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>compile-assignment</SCHEMEINLINE> use the compile-time
  environment in order to generate the appropriate lexical addresses.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Exercises<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:lexical-address-start"/>
  through<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:lexical-address-end"/> describe how to complete this sketch of
  the lexical-addressing strategy in order to incorporate lexical lookup
  into the compiler.
  Exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:cte-open-code"/> describes another use for the
  compile-time environment.
  <INDEX>compiler for Scheme<SUBINDEX>lexical addressing|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>lexical addressing|)</INDEX>
      </TEXT>

      <EXERCISE>
  <!--  \indcode{lexical-address-lookup}\indcode{lexical-address-set!} -->
  Write a
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  <SCHEMEINLINE>lexical-address-lookup</SCHEMEINLINE> that implements the new
  lookup operation.  It should take two arguments<EMDASH/>a lexical address
  and a run-time environment<EMDASH/>and return the value of the variable
  stored at the specified lexical address.  <SCHEMEINLINE>Lexical-address-lookup</SCHEMEINLINE>
  should signal an error if the value of the variable is the symbol <SCHEMEINLINE>*unassigned*</SCHEMEINLINE>.<FOOTNOTE>This is the modification to variable lookup
    <INDEX>scanning out internal definitions<SUBINDEX>compiler@in compiler</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>compiler for Scheme<SUBINDEX>scanning out internal definitions</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    required if we implement the scanning method to eliminate internal
    definitions (exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:compile-internal-defs"/>).  We will need
    to eliminate these definitions in order for lexical addressing to
    work.</FOOTNOTE> Also write a
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  <SCHEMEINLINE>lexical\?address\?set!</SCHEMEINLINE> that
  implements the operation that changes the value of the variable at a
  specified lexical address.
  <LABEL NAME="ex:lexical-address-lookup"/>
  <LABEL NAME="ex:lexical-address-start"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <INDEX>compile-time environment</INDEX>
  Modify the compiler to maintain the compile-time environment as
  described above.  That is, add a compile-time-environment argument to
  <SCHEMEINLINE>compile</SCHEMEINLINE> and the various code generators, and extend it in
  <SCHEMEINLINE>compile-lambda-body</SCHEMEINLINE>.
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE><LABEL NAME="ex:find-variable"/>
  <INDEX>compile-time environment</INDEX>
  Write a
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  <SCHEMEINLINE>find-variable</SCHEMEINLINE> that takes as arguments a
  variable and a compile-time environment and returns the lexical
  address of the variable with respect to that environment.  For
  example, in the program fragment that is shown above, the compile-time
  environment during the compilation of expression <LATEXINLINE>e1</LATEXINLINE> is <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((y z) (a b c d e) (x y))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  <SCHEMEINLINE>Find-variable</SCHEMEINLINE> should produce

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (find-variable 'c '((y z) (a b c d e) (x y)))
    </SCHEME>
    <SCHEMEOUTPUT>
      (1 2)
    </SCHEMEOUTPUT>
    
  </SNIPPET>

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (find-variable 'x '((y z) (a b c d e) (x y)))
    </SCHEME>
    <SCHEMEOUTPUT>
      (2 0)
    </SCHEMEOUTPUT>
    
  </SNIPPET>

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (find-variable 'w '((y z) (a b c d e) (x y)))
    </SCHEME>
    <SCHEMEOUTPUT>
      not-found
    </SCHEMEOUTPUT>
    
  </SNIPPET>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  Using <SCHEMEINLINE>find-variable</SCHEMEINLINE> from exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:find-variable"/>,
  rewrite <SCHEMEINLINE>compile-variable</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>compile-assignment</SCHEMEINLINE> to output
  lexical-address instructions.  In cases where <SCHEMEINLINE>find-variable</SCHEMEINLINE>
  returns <SCHEMEINLINE>not-found</SCHEMEINLINE> (that is, where the variable is not in the
  compile-time environment), you should have the code generators use the
  evaluator operations, as before, to search for the binding.
  (The only place a variable that is not found at compile time can be is in
  the global environment, which is part of the run-time environment but
  is not part of the compile-time 
  environment.<FOOTNOTE>Lexical addresses cannot be used to access variables in the global
    environment, because these names can be defined and redefined
    interactively at any time.  With internal definitions scanned out, as
    in exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:compile-internal-defs"/>, the only definitions the
    compiler sees are those at top level, which act on the global
    environment.  Compilation of a definition does not cause the defined
    name to be entered in the compile-time environment.</FOOTNOTE>
  Thus, if you wish, you may have the evaluator operations look directly in
  the global environment, which can be obtained with the operation <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(op<SPACE/>get-global-environment)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, instead of having them search the whole run-time
  environment found in <SCHEMEINLINE>env</SCHEMEINLINE>.)
  Test the modified compiler on a few simple cases, such as the nested
  <SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE> combination at the beginning of this section.
  <LABEL NAME="ex:impl-lex-addr"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <INDEX>scanning out internal definitions<SUBINDEX>compiler@in compiler</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>compiler for Scheme<SUBINDEX>scanning out internal definitions</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  We argued in section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:internal-definitions"/> that internal definitions
  for block structure should not be considered <QUOTE>real</QUOTE> <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE>s.  Rather,
  a
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  body should be interpreted as if the internal variables being
  defined were installed as ordinary <SCHEMEINLINE>lambda</SCHEMEINLINE> variables initialized to their
  correct values using <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>set!</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>assignment</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:internal-definitions"/> and
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:internal-defs"/> showed how to modify the metacircular
  interpreter to accomplish this by scanning out internal definitions.  Modify
  the compiler to perform the same transformation before it compiles a
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  body.
  <LABEL NAME="ex:compile-internal-defs"/>
  <LABEL NAME="ex:lexical-address-end"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <INDEX>compiler for Scheme<SUBINDEX>open coding of primitives</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>open coding of primitives</INDEX>
  <INDEX>reserved words</INDEX>
  <INDEX>compile-time environment<SUBINDEX>open coding and</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  In this section we have focused on the use of the compile-time
  environment to produce lexical addresses.  But there are other uses
  for compile-time environments.  For instance, in
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:open-code"/> we increased the efficiency of compiled
  code by open-coding primitive
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Our implementation treated
  the names of open-coded
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  as reserved words.  If a program
  were to rebind such a name, the mechanism described in
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:open-code"/> would still open-code it as a primitive,
  ignoring the new binding.  For example, consider the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (lambda (+ * a b x y)
      (+ (* a x) (* b y)))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  which computes a linear combination of <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE>.  We might
  call it with arguments <SCHEMEINLINE>+matrix</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>*matrix</SCHEMEINLINE>, and four
  matrices, but the open-coding compiler would still open-code the <SCHEMEINLINE>+</SCHEMEINLINE> and the <SCHEMEINLINE>*</SCHEMEINLINE> in <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(+ (* a x) (* b y))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> as primitive <SCHEMEINLINE>+</SCHEMEINLINE>
  and <SCHEMEINLINE>*</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Modify the open-coding compiler to consult the
  compile-time environment in order to compile the correct code for
  expressions involving the names of primitive
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
  (The code will work correctly as long as the program does not <SCHEMEINLINE>define</SCHEMEINLINE> or <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>set!</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>assignment</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> these names.)
  <LABEL NAME="ex:cte-open-code"/>
      </EXERCISE>

    </SUBSECTION>
