  <SECTION WIP="yes">
    <NAME>Logic Programming</NAME>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>

    <LABEL NAME="sec:logic-programming"/>
    <INDEX>logic programming|(</INDEX>

    <TEXT>
      <INDEX>declarative vs.<SPACE/>imperative knowledge</INDEX>
      <INDEX>imperative vs.<SPACE/>declarative knowledge</INDEX>
      <INDEX>mathematics<SUBINDEX>computer science vs.</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>computer science<SUBINDEX>mathematics vs.</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      In chapter<SPACE/>1 we stressed that computer science deals with imperative
      (how to) knowledge, whereas mathematics deals with declarative (what
      is) knowledge.  Indeed, programming languages require that the
      programmer express knowledge in a form that indicates the step-by-step
      methods for solving particular problems.  On the other hand,
      high-level languages provide, as part of the language implementation,
      a substantial amount of methodological knowledge that frees
      the user from concern with numerous details of how a specified
      computation will progress.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      Most programming languages, including
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp,</SCHEME>
      <JAVSCRIPT>JavaScript,</JAVSCRIPT>
      </SPLITINLINE>
      are organized around
      computing the values of mathematical functions.  Expression-oriented
      languages (such as Lisp, Fortran, and Algol) capitalize on the <QUOTE>pun</QUOTE>
      that an expression that describes the value of a function may also be
      interpreted as a means of computing that value.  Because of this, most
      programming languages are strongly biased toward unidirectional
      computations (computations with well-defined inputs and outputs).
      There are, however, radically different programming languages that
      relax this bias.  We saw one such example in
      section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:constraints"/>, where the objects of computation were
      arithmetic constraints.  In a constraint system the direction and the
      order of computation are not so well specified; in carrying out a
      computation the system must therefore provide more detailed <QUOTE>how to</QUOTE>
      knowledge than would be the case with an ordinary arithmetic
      computation.  This does not mean, however, that the user is released
      altogether from the responsibility of providing imperative knowledge.
      There are many constraint networks that implement the same set of
      constraints, and the user must choose from the set of mathematically
      equivalent networks a suitable network to specify a particular
      computation.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      The nondeterministic program evaluator of
      section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:nondeterministic-evaluation"/> also moves away from the
      view that programming is about constructing algorithms for computing
      unidirectional functions.  In a nondeterministic language, expressions
      can have more than one value, and, as a result, the computation is
      <INDEX>relations, computing in terms of</INDEX>
      dealing with relations rather than with
      single-valued functions.  Logic programming extends this idea by
      combining a relational vision of programming with a powerful kind of
      symbolic pattern matching called 
      <EM>unification</EM>.<FOOTNOTE>Logic programming has grown out of a long
  <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>history of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>theorem proving (automatic)</INDEX>
  history of research in automatic theorem proving.  Early
  theorem-proving programs could accomplish very little, because they
  exhaustively searched the space of possible proofs.  The major
  breakthrough that made such a search plausible was the discovery in
  the early 1960s of the 
  <INDEX>unification<SUBINDEX>discovery of algorithm</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <EM>unification algorithm</EM> and the 
  <INDEX>resolution principle</INDEX>
  <EM>
    resolution principle</EM> (<CITATION>Robinson 1965</CITATION>).  
  Resolution was used, for
  example, by 
  <INDEX>Raphael, Bertram</INDEX><INDEX>Green, Cordell</INDEX>
  Green and Raphael (1968) (see also <CITATION>Green 1969</CITATION>) as the
  basis for a deductive question-answering system.  During most of this
  period, researchers concentrated on algorithms that are guaranteed to
  find a proof if one exists.  Such algorithms were difficult to control
  and to direct toward a proof.  
  <INDEX>Hewitt, Carl Eddie</INDEX>
  Hewitt (1969) recognized the
  possibility of merging the control structure of a programming language
  with the operations of a logic-manipulation system, leading to the
  work in automatic search mentioned in section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:amb"/>
  (footnote<SPACE/><REF NAME="foot:backtrack"/>).  At the same time that this was being done,
  <INDEX>Colmerauer, Alain</INDEX>
  Colmerauer, in Marseille, was developing rule-based systems for
  manipulating natural language 
  (see <CITATION>Colmerauer et al.<SPACE/>1973</CITATION>).  He
  invented a programming language called 
  <INDEX>Prolog</INDEX>
  Prolog for representing those
  rules.  
  <INDEX>Kowalski, Robert</INDEX>
  Kowalski (<CITATION><TEXT>1973</TEXT>Kowalski 1973</CITATION>; 
  <CITATION><TEXT>1979</TEXT>Kowalski 1979</CITATION>), 
  in Edinburgh, recognized that execution
  of a Prolog program could be interpreted as proving theorems (using a
  proof technique called linear 
  <INDEX>resolution, Horn-clause</INDEX>
  Horn-clause resolution).  The merging of
  the last two strands led to the logic-programming movement.  Thus, in
  assigning credit for the development of logic programming, the French
  can point to Prolog<APOS/>s genesis at the 
  <INDEX>University of Marseille</INDEX>
  University of Marseille, while
  the British can highlight the work at the 
  <INDEX>University of Edinburgh</INDEX>
  University of Edinburgh.
  According to people at 
  <INDEX>MIT</INDEX>
  MIT, logic programming was developed by these
  groups in an attempt to figure out what Hewitt was talking about in
  his brilliant but impenetrable Ph.D. thesis.  For a history of logic
  <INDEX>Robinson, J. A.</INDEX>
  programming, see <CITATION>Robinson 1983</CITATION>.</FOOTNOTE>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      <INDEX>declarative vs.<SPACE/>imperative knowledge<SUBINDEX>logic programming and|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>imperative vs.<SPACE/>declarative knowledge<SUBINDEX>logic programming and|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      This approach, when it works, can be a very powerful way to write
      programs.  Part of the power comes from the fact that a single <QUOTE>what
  is</QUOTE> fact can be used to solve a number of different problems that
      would have different <QUOTE>how to</QUOTE> components.  As an example, consider
      the 
      <!--  \indcode{append}[what@<QUOTE>what is</QUOTE> (rules) vs.\ <QUOTE>how to</QUOTE> (<SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>)|(] -->
      <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> operation, which takes two lists as arguments and
      combines their elements to form a single list.  In a procedural
      language such as <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, we could define <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> in terms of the
      basic list constructor <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, as we did in
      section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:sequences"/>:

      <SNIPPET>
  <SCHEME>
    (define (append x y)
    (if (null? x)
    y
    (cons (car x) (append (cdr x) y))))
  </SCHEME>
  <JAVASCRIPT>
function append(x, y) {    
    return is_null(x)
        ? y
        : pair(head(x), append(tail(x), y));
}
  </JAVASCRIPT>
      </SNIPPET>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      This
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      can be regarded as a translation into <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> of the
      following two rules, the first of which covers the case where the
      first list is empty and the second of which handles the case of a
      nonempty list, which is a <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> of two parts:

      <UL>
  <LI>For any list <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE>, the empty list and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> to form <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE>.

  </LI>
  <LI>For any <SCHEMEINLINE>u</SCHEMEINLINE>,<LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>v</SCHEMEINLINE>,<LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>z</SCHEMEINLINE>,
    <LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cons u v)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair(u, v)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> to form <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cons<SPACE/>u<SPACE/>z)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair(u, z)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    if <SCHEMEINLINE>v</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> to form <SCHEMEINLINE>z</SCHEMEINLINE>.<FOOTNOTE>To
      see the correspondence between the rules and the
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, let <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> in the
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      (where <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> is nonempty) correspond to <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cons u v)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair(u, v)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> in the rule.  Then <SCHEMEINLINE>z</SCHEMEINLINE> in the rule corresponds to the
      <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(cdr x)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>tail(x)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE>.</FOOTNOTE>
  </LI>
      </UL>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      Using the <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE>
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, we can answer questions such as
      <BLOCKQUOTE>
  Find the <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(a b)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list("a", "b")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(c d)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list("c", "d")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
      </BLOCKQUOTE>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      But the same two rules are also sufficient for answering the following
      sorts of questions, which the
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      can<APOS/>t answer:

      <BLOCKQUOTE>
  Find a list <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> that <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE>s with <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(a b)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list("a", "b")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> 
  to produce <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(a b c d)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list("a", "b", "c", "d")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.

  Find all <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE> that <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> to form <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(a b c
        d)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list("a", "b", "c", "d")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
      </BLOCKQUOTE>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>logic programming languages</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>programming language<SUBINDEX>logic</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      In a logic programming language, the programmer writes an <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE>
      <QUOTE><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></QUOTE> by stating the two rules about <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> given above.
      <QUOTE>How to</QUOTE> knowledge is provided automatically by the interpreter to
      allow this single pair of rules to be used to answer all three types
      of questions about <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE>.<FOOTNOTE>This certainly does not
  relieve the user of the entire problem of how to compute the answer.
  There are many different mathematically equivalent sets of rules for
  formulating the <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE> relation, only some of which can be
  turned into effective devices for computing in any direction.  In
  addition, sometimes <QUOTE>what is</QUOTE> information gives no clue <QUOTE>how to</QUOTE>
  compute an answer.  For example, consider the problem of computing the
  <LATEXINLINE>$y$</LATEXINLINE> such that <LATEXINLINE>$y^2 = x$</LATEXINLINE>.</FOOTNOTE>
      <!--  \indcode{append}[what@<QUOTE>what is</QUOTE> (rules) vs.<SPACE/><QUOTE>how to</QUOTE> (<SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>)|)] -->
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      Contemporary logic programming languages (including the one we
      implement here) have substantial deficiencies, in that their general
      <QUOTE>how to</QUOTE> methods can lead them into spurious infinite loops or other
      undesirable behavior.
      Logic programming is an active field of research in computer 
      science.<FOOTNOTE>Interest in logic programming peaked
  <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>history of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>in Japan</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>computers for</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  during the early 80s when the Japanese government began an ambitious
  project aimed at building superfast computers optimized to run logic
  programming languages.  The speed of such computers was to be measured
  in LIPS (Logical Inferences Per Second) rather than the usual FLOPS
  (FLoating-point Operations Per Second).  Although the project
  succeeded in developing hardware and software as originally planned,
  the international computer industry moved in a different direction.
  See 
  <INDEX>Feigenbaum, Edward</INDEX><INDEX>Shrobe, Howard E.</INDEX>
  <CITATION>Feigenbaum and Shrobe 1993</CITATION> for an overview evaluation of the
  Japanese project.  The logic programming community has also moved on
  to consider relational programming based on techniques other than
  simple pattern matching, such as the ability to deal with numerical
  constraints such as the ones illustrated in the constraint-propagation
  system of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:constraints"/>.</FOOTNOTE>
      <INDEX>declarative vs.<SPACE/>imperative knowledge<SUBINDEX>logic programming and|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>imperative vs.<SPACE/>declarative knowledge<SUBINDEX>logic programming and|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      Earlier in this chapter we explored the technology of implementing
      interpreters and described the elements that are essential to an
      interpreter for a <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>-like language (indeed, to an interpreter for
      any conventional language).  Now we will apply these ideas to discuss
      an interpreter for a logic programming language.  We call this
      <INDEX>query language</INDEX>
      language the <EM>query language</EM>, because it is very useful for
      retrieving information from data bases by formulating 
      <INDEX>query</INDEX>
      <EM>queries</EM>,
      or questions, expressed in the language.  Even though the query
      language is very different from <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, we will find it convenient to
      describe the language in terms of the same general framework we have
      been using all along: as a collection of primitive elements, together
      with means of combination that enable us to combine simple elements to
      create more complex elements and means of abstraction that enable us
      to regard complex elements as single conceptual units.  An interpreter
      for a logic programming language is considerably more complex than an
      interpreter for a language like <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Nevertheless, we will see
      <INDEX>query interpreter</INDEX>
      that our query-language interpreter contains many of the same elements
      found in the interpreter of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:mc-eval"/>.  In particular,
      there will be an <QUOTE>eval</QUOTE> part that classifies expressions according
      to type and an <QUOTE>apply</QUOTE> part that implements the language<APOS/>s
      abstraction mechanism (<SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      in the case of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, and <EM>rules</EM>
      in the case of logic programming).  Also, a central role is played in
      the implementation by a frame data structure, which determines the
      correspondence between symbols and their associated values.  One
      additional interesting aspect of our query-language implementation is
      that we make substantial use of streams, which were introduced in
      chapter<SPACE/>3.
      <INDEX>logic programming|)</INDEX>
    </TEXT>

    <!-- Subsection 1 : Deductive Information Retrieval -->
    &subsection4.4.1;

    <!-- Subsection 2 : How the Query System Works -->
    &subsection4.4.2;

    <!-- Subsection 3 : Is Logic Programming Mathematical Logic? -->
    &subsection4.4.3;

    <!-- Subsection 4 : Implementing the Query System -->
    &subsection4.4.4;
    
  </SECTION>
