    <SUBSECTION>
      <NAME>
  Is Logic Programming Mathematical Logic?
      </NAME>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:math-logic"/>
      <INDEX>query language<SUBINDEX>mathematical logic vs.|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>mathematical logic vs.|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <TEXT>
  The means of combination used in the query language may at first seem
  identical to the operations <SCHEMEINLINE>and</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>or</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> of
  mathematical logic, and the application of query-language rules is in
  fact accomplished through a legitimate method of
  <INDEX>inference, method of</INDEX>
  inference.<FOOTNOTE>That a particular method of inference is
    legitimate is not a trivial assertion.  One must prove that if one
    starts with true premises, only true conclusions can be derived.  The
    method of inference represented by rule applications is 
    <INDEX><ORDER>modus</ORDER><EM>modus ponens</EM></INDEX>
    <EM>modus
      ponens</EM>, the familiar method of inference that says that if <EM>A</EM> is
    true and <EM>A implies B</EM> is true, then we may conclude that <EM>B</EM>
    is true.</FOOTNOTE> This identification of the query language with mathematical
  logic is not really valid, though, because the query language provides
  a 
  <INDEX>control structure</INDEX>
  <EM>control structure</EM> that interprets the logical statements
  procedurally.  We can often take advantage of this control structure.
  For example, to find all of the supervisors of programmers we could
  formulate a query in either of two logically equivalent forms:

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (and (job ?x (computer programmer))
      (supervisor ?x ?y))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
and(job(x, list("computer", "programmer")),
    supervisor(x, y));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  or
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (and (supervisor ?x ?y)
      (job ?x (computer programmer)))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
and(supervisor(x, y),
    job(x, list("computer", "programmer")));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>bureaucracy</INDEX>
  If a company has many more supervisors than programmers (the usual
  case), it is better to use the first form rather than the second
  because the data base must be scanned for each intermediate result
  (frame) produced by the first clause of the <SCHEMEINLINE>and</SCHEMEINLINE>.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>declarative vs.<SPACE/>imperative knowledge<SUBINDEX>logic programming and</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>imperative vs.<SPACE/>declarative knowledge<SUBINDEX>logic programming and</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  The aim of logic programming is to provide the programmer with
  techniques for decomposing a computational problem into two separate
  problems: <QUOTE>what</QUOTE> is to be computed, and <QUOTE>how</QUOTE> this should be
  computed.  This is accomplished by selecting a subset of the
  statements of mathematical logic that is powerful enough to be able to
  describe anything one might want to compute, yet weak enough to have a
  controllable procedural interpretation.  The intention here is that,
  on the one hand, a program specified in a logic programming language
  should be an effective program that can be carried out by a computer.
  Control (<QUOTE>how</QUOTE> to compute) is effected by using the order of
  evaluation of the language.  We should be able to arrange the order of
  clauses and the order of subgoals within each clause so that the
  computation is done in an order deemed to be effective and efficient.
  At the same time, we should be able to view the result of the
  computation (<QUOTE>what</QUOTE> to compute) as a simple consequence of the laws
  of logic.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Our query language can be regarded as just such a procedurally
  interpretable subset of mathematical logic.  An assertion represents a
  simple fact (an atomic proposition).  A rule represents the
  implication that the rule conclusion holds for those cases where the
  rule body holds.  A rule has a natural procedural interpretation: To
  establish the conclusion of the rule, establish the body of the rule.
  Rules, therefore, specify computations.  However, because rules can
  also be regarded as statements of mathematical logic, we can justify any <QUOTE>inference</QUOTE> accomplished by a logic program by asserting that
  the same result could be obtained by working entirely within
  mathematical logic.<FOOTNOTE>We must qualify this statement by
    agreeing that, in speaking of the <QUOTE>inference</QUOTE> accomplished by a
    logic program, we assume that the computation terminates.
    Unfortunately, even this qualified statement is false for our
    implementation of the query language (and also false for programs in
    Prolog and most other current logic programming languages) because of
    our use of <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> and
  <SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEME>
      <SCHEMEINLINE>lisp-value</SCHEMEINLINE>.
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>javascript_value</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>.
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLITINLINE>
    As we will describe below,
    the <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> implemented in the query language is not always
    consistent with the <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> of mathematical logic, and
  <SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEME>
      <SCHEMEINLINE>lisp-value</SCHEMEINLINE>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>javascript_value</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLITINLINE>
    introduces additional complications.  We could implement a
    language consistent with mathematical logic by simply removing <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> and
  <SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEME>
      <SCHEMEINLINE>lisp-value</SCHEMEINLINE>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>javascript_value</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLITINLINE>
    from the language and agreeing to write
    programs using only simple queries, <SCHEMEINLINE>and</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>or</SCHEMEINLINE>.  However,
    this would greatly restrict the expressive power of the language.  One
    of the major concerns of research in logic programming is to find ways
    to achieve more consistency with mathematical logic without unduly
    sacrificing expressive power.</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
  <NAME>Infinite loops</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <INDEX>query interpreter<SUBINDEX>infinite loops|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <TEXT>
  A consequence of the procedural interpretation of logic programs is
  that it is possible to construct hopelessly inefficient programs for
  solving certain problems.  An extreme case of inefficiency occurs when
  the system falls into infinite loops in making deductions.  As a
  simple example, suppose we are setting up a data base of famous
  marriages, including

  <INDEX>Mouse, Minnie and Mickey</INDEX>
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (assert! (married Minnie Mickey))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
assert(married("Minnie", "Mickey"));      
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  If we now ask
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (married Mickey ?who)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
married("Mickey", who);      
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  we will get no response, because the system doesn<APOS/>t know that if <LATEXINLINE>$A$</LATEXINLINE>
  is married to <LATEXINLINE>$B$</LATEXINLINE>, then <LATEXINLINE>$B$</LATEXINLINE> is married to <LATEXINLINE>$A$</LATEXINLINE>.  So we assert the rule

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (assert! (rule (married ?x ?y)
            (married ?y ?x)))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
assert(rule(married(x, y), married(y, x)));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  and again query

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (married Mickey ?who)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
married("Mickey", who);      
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  Unfortunately, this will drive the system into an infinite loop, as
  follows:

  <UL>
    <LI>The system finds that the <SCHEMEINLINE>married</SCHEMEINLINE> rule is applicable;
      that is, the rule conclusion <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married ?x ?y)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married(x, y)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> successfully
      unifies with the query pattern <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married Mickey ?who)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married("Mickey", who)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> to produce
      a frame in which
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>?x</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>x</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      is bound to
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>Mickey</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>"Mickey"</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
      and
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>?y</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>y</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>      
      is bound to
      <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>?who</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>who</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
      So the interpreter proceeds to evaluate the rule
      body <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married ?y ?x)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married(x, y)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> in this frame<EMDASH/>in effect, to process the
      query <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married ?who Mickey)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married(who, "Mickey")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.

    </LI>
    <LI>One answer appears directly as an assertion in the data
      base: <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married Minnie Mickey)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married("Minnie", "Mickey")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.

    </LI>
    <LI>The <SCHEMEINLINE>married</SCHEMEINLINE> rule is also applicable, so the
      interpreter again evaluates the rule body, which this time is
      equivalent to <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married Mickey ?who)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married("Mickey", who)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
    </LI>

  </UL>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  The system is now in an infinite loop.  Indeed, whether the system
  will find the simple answer <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(married Minnie Mickey)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>married("Minnie", "Mickey")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> before it
  goes into the loop depends on implementation details concerning the
  order in which the system checks the items in the data base.  This is
  a very simple example of the kinds of loops that can occur.
  Collections of interrelated rules can lead to loops that are much
  harder to anticipate, and the appearance of a loop can depend on the order
  of clauses in an <SCHEMEINLINE>and</SCHEMEINLINE> (see exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:query-simple-loop"/>)
  or on low-level details concerning the order in which the system
  processes queries.<FOOTNOTE>This is not a problem of the logic but one of the
    procedural interpretation of the logic provided by our interpreter.
    We could write an interpreter that would not fall into a loop here.
    For example, we could enumerate all the proofs derivable from our
    assertions and our rules in a breadth-first rather than a depth-first
    order.  However, such a system makes it more difficult to take
    advantage of the order of deductions in our programs.  One attempt to
    build sophisticated control into such a program is described in
    <INDEX>deKleer, Johan</INDEX>
    <CITATION>deKleer et al.<SPACE/>1977</CITATION>.  
    Another technique, which does not lead to such
    serious control problems, is to put in special knowledge, such as
    detectors for particular kinds of loops
    (exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:query-loop-detector"/>).  However, there can be no
    general scheme for reliably preventing a system from going down
    infinite paths in performing deductions.  Imagine a diabolical rule of
    the form <QUOTE>To show <LATEXINLINE>$P(x)$</LATEXINLINE> is true, show that <LATEXINLINE>$P(f(x))$</LATEXINLINE> is true,</QUOTE> for
    some suitably chosen function <LATEXINLINE>$f$</LATEXINLINE>.</FOOTNOTE>
  <INDEX>query interpreter<SUBINDEX>infinite loops|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
  <NAME>Problems with <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE></NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <INDEX>query interpreter<SUBINDEX>problems with <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>lisp-value</SCHEMEINLINE>|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <TEXT>
  <!-- \indcodeplus{not}{(query language)}-->
  Another quirk in the query system concerns <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Given the data
  base of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:deductive-info-retrieval"/>, consider the
  following two queries:

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (and (supervisor ?x ?y)
      (not (job ?x (computer programmer))))

      (and (not (job ?x (computer programmer)))
      (supervisor ?x ?y))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
and(supervisor(x, y),
    not(job(x, list("computer", "programmer"))));

and(not(job(x, list("computer", "programmer"))),
    supervisor(x, y));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  These two queries do not produce the same result.  The first query
  begins by finding all entries in the data base that match <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(supervisor ?x ?y)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>supervisor(x, y)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, and then filters the resulting frames by removing
  the ones in which the value of
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>?x</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>x</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  satisfies <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(job ?x (computer programmer))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>job(x, list("computer", "programmer"))</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  The second query begins by filtering the
  incoming frames to remove those that can satisfy <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(job ?x (computer programmer))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>job(x, list("computer", "programmer"))</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Since the only incoming frame is empty, it
  checks the data base to see if there are any patterns that satisfy
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(job ?x (computer programmer))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>job(x, list("computer", "programmer"))</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Since there generally are
  entries of this form, the <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> clause filters out the empty frame
  and returns an empty stream of frames.  Consequently, the entire
  compound query returns an empty stream.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  The trouble is that our implementation of <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> really is meant to
  serve as a filter on values for the variables.  If a <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> clause
  is processed with a frame in which some of the variables remain
  unbound (as does
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>?x</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>x</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  in the example above), the system will
  produce unexpected results. Similar problems occur with the use of
  <!-- \indcodeplus{lisp-value}{(query language)}-->
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>lisp-value</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>javascript_value</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE><EMDASH/>the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> predicate can<APOS/>t work if some of its
  arguments are unbound.  See exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:not-query-filter"/>.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  There is also a much more serious way in which the <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> of the
  query language differs from the <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> of mathematical logic.  In
  logic, we interpret the statement <QUOTE>not <LATEXINLINE>$P$</LATEXINLINE></QUOTE> to mean that <LATEXINLINE>$P$</LATEXINLINE> is not
  true.  In the query system, however, <QUOTE>not <LATEXINLINE>$P$</LATEXINLINE></QUOTE> means that <LATEXINLINE>$P$</LATEXINLINE> is not
  deducible from the knowledge in the data base.  For example, given the
  personnel data base of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:deductive-info-retrieval"/>, the
  system would happily deduce all sorts of <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> statements, such as
  that Ben Bitdiddle is not a baseball fan, that it is not raining
  outside, and that <LATEXINLINE>$2 + 2$</LATEXINLINE> is not 4.<FOOTNOTE>Consider the query <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(not (baseball-fan (Bitdiddle Ben)))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>not(baseball_fan(list("Bitdiddle", "Ben")))</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  The system finds that <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(baseball-fan (Bitdiddle Ben))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>baseball_fan(list("Bitdiddle", "Ben"))</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> is not in the data base, so the empty
    frame does not satisfy the pattern and is not filtered out of the
    initial stream of frames.  The result of the query is thus the empty
    frame, which is used to instantiate the input query to produce
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(not (baseball-fan (Bitdiddle Ben)))</SCHEMEINLINE>.</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>not(baseball_fan(list("Bitdiddle", "Ben")))</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>.</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE></FOOTNOTE> In other words, the <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE>
  of logic programming languages reflects the so-called 
  <INDEX>closed world assumption</INDEX>
  <EM>closed
    world assumption</EM> that all relevant information has been included in
  the data base.<FOOTNOTE>A discussion and justification of this
    <INDEX>Clark, Keith L.</INDEX>
    treatment of <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> can be found in the article by Clark (1978).</FOOTNOTE>
  <INDEX>query interpreter<SUBINDEX>problems with <SCHEMEINLINE>not</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>lisp-value</SCHEMEINLINE>|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      </TEXT>

      <EXERCISE>
  <!-- \indcodeplus{outranked-by}{(rule)}-->
  Louis Reasoner mistakenly deletes the
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>outranked-by</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>outranked_by</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  rule
  (section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:deductive-info-retrieval"/>) from the data base.  When
  he realizes this, he quickly reinstalls it.  Unfortunately, he makes a
  slight change in the rule, and types it in as

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (rule (outranked-by ?staff-person ?boss)
      (or (supervisor ?staff-person ?boss)
            (and (outranked-by ?middle-manager ?boss)
            (supervisor ?staff-person ?middle-manager))))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
rule(outranked_by(staff_person, boss),      
     or(supervisor(staff_person, boss),
        and(outranked_by(middle_manager, boss),
            supervisor(staff_person, middle_manager))));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  Just after Louis types this information into the system, DeWitt
  Aull comes by to find out who outranks Ben Bitdiddle. He issues
  the query

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (outranked-by (Bitdiddle Ben) ?who)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
outanked_by(list("Bitdiddle", "Ben"), who);      
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  After answering, the system goes into an infinite loop.  Explain why.
  <LABEL NAME="ex:query-simple-loop"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <!-- \indcodeplus{wheel}{(rule)}-->
  Cy D. Fect, looking forward to the day when he will rise in the
  organization, gives a query to find all the wheels
  (using the <SCHEMEINLINE>wheel</SCHEMEINLINE> rule of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:deductive-info-retrieval"/>):

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (wheel ?who)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
wheel(who);      
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  To his surprise, the system responds

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEMEOUTPUT>
      ;;; Query results:
      (wheel (Warbucks Oliver))
      (wheel (Bitdiddle Ben))
      (wheel (Warbucks Oliver))
      (wheel (Warbucks Oliver))
      (wheel (Warbucks Oliver))
    </SCHEMEOUTPUT>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
// Query results:
wheel(list("Warbucks", "Oliver"))
wheel(list("Bitdiddle", "Ben"))
wheel(list("Warbucks", "Oliver"))
wheel(list("Warbucks", "Oliver"))
wheel(list("Warbucks", "Oliver"))
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  Why is Oliver Warbucks listed four times?
  <LABEL NAME="ex:multiple-query"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <INDEX>query language<SUBINDEX>extensions to</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  Ben has been generalizing the query system to provide statistics
  about the company.  For example, to find the total salaries of all the
  computer programmers one will be able to say

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (sum ?amount
      (and (job ?x (computer programmer))
            (salary ?x ?amount)))
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
sum(amount,      
    and(job(x, list("computer", "programmer")),
        salary(x, amount)));
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  In general, Ben<APOS/>s new system allows expressions of the form

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no" LATEX="yes">
    <SCHEME>
      (accumulation-function ^variable^
            ^query pattern^)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
accumulation_function($\textit{variable}$, $\textit{query-pattern}$)
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SNIPPET>

  where
  <SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEME>
      <SCHEMEINLINE>accumulation-function</SCHEMEINLINE>
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>accumulation_function</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLITINLINE>
  can be things like <SCHEMEINLINE>sum</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>average</SCHEMEINLINE>, or <SCHEMEINLINE>maximum</SCHEMEINLINE>.
  Ben reasons that it should be a
  cinch to implement this.  He will simply feed the query pattern to
  <SCHEMEINLINE>qeval</SCHEMEINLINE>.  This will produce a stream of frames.  He will then pass
  this stream through a mapping function that extracts the value of the
  designated variable from each frame in the stream and feed the
  resulting stream of values to the accumulation function.  Just as Ben
  completes the implementation and is about to try it out, Cy walks by,
  still puzzling over the <SCHEMEINLINE>wheel</SCHEMEINLINE> query result in
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:multiple-query"/>.  When Cy shows Ben the system<APOS/>s
  response, Ben groans, <QUOTE>Oh, no, my simple accumulation scheme won<APOS/>t
    work!</QUOTE>

  What has Ben just realized?  Outline a method he can use to
  salvage the situation.
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <INDEX>query interpreter<SUBINDEX>improvements to</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>query interpreter<SUBINDEX>infinite loops</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  Devise a way to install a loop detector in the query system so as to
  avoid the kinds of simple loops illustrated in the text and in
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:query-simple-loop"/>.  The general idea is that the
  system should maintain some sort of history of its current chain of
  deductions and should not begin processing a query that it is already
  working on.  Describe what kind of information (patterns and frames)
  is included in this history, and how the check should be made.  (After
  you study the details of the query-system implementation in
  section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:implementing-the-query-system"/>, you may want to
  modify the system to include your loop detector.)
  <LABEL NAME="ex:query-loop-detector"/>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <!--  \indcode{reverse}[rules] -->
  Define rules to implement the <SCHEMEINLINE>reverse</SCHEMEINLINE> operation of
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:reverse"/>, which returns a list containing the same
  elements as a given list in reverse order.  (Hint: Use
    <SPLITINLINE>
    <SCHEME>
      <SCHEMEINLINE>append-to-form</SCHEMEINLINE>.)
    </SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>append_to_form</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>.
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLITINLINE>
  Can your rules answer both
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(reverse (1 2 3) ?x)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>reverse(list(1, 2, 3), x)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(reverse ?x (1 2 3))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>reverse(x, list(1, 2, 3)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>?
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  Beginning with the data base and the rules you formulated in
  exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:genesis"/>, devise a rule for adding <QUOTE>greats</QUOTE> to
  a grandson relationship. This should enable the system to deduce that
  Irad is the great-grandson of Adam, or that Jabal and Jubal are
  the great-great-great-great-great-grandsons of Adam.  (Hint: Represent
  the fact about Irad, for example, as <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((great grandson) Adam Irad)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list(list("great", "grandson"), "Adam", "Irad")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Write rules that determine if a list ends in the word
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>grandson</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>"grandson"</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
  Use this to express a rule that allows one to derive
  the relationship <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((great .  ?rel) ?x ?y)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list(pair("great", rel), x, y)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, where
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>?rel</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>rel</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  is a
  list ending in
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>grandson</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>"grandson"</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.)
  Check your rules on queries such as
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((great grandson) ?g ?ggs)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list(list("great", "grandson"), g, ggs)</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(?relationship Adam Irad)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>list(relationship, "Adam", "Irad")</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
  <LABEL NAME="ex:great-grandson"/>
      </EXERCISE>
      <INDEX>query language<SUBINDEX>mathematical logic vs.|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>logic programming<SUBINDEX>mathematical logic vs.|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

    </SUBSECTION>
