    <SECTION>
      <NAME>
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>Functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
            and the Processes They Generate
      </NAME>

      <SECTIONCONTENT/>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:procedures-and-processes"/> 

          <TEXT>
            We have now considered the elements of programming: We have used
            primitive arithmetic operations, we have combined these operations, and
            we have abstracted these composite operations by 
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>defining them as compound procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>declaring them as compound functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>. 
            But that is not enough to enable us to say that we know
            how to program.  Our situation is analogous to that of someone who has
            learned the rules for how the pieces move in chess but knows nothing
            of typical openings, tactics, or strategy.  Like the novice chess
            player, we don<APOS/>t yet know the common patterns of usage in the domain.
            We lack the knowledge of which moves are worth making 
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>(which procedures are worth defining).</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>(which functions are worth declaring).</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
            We lack the experience to predict the
            consequences of making a move (executing a 
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>).
          </TEXT>

          <TEXT>
            The ability to visualize the consequences of the actions under
            consideration is crucial to becoming an expert programmer, just as it
            is in any synthetic, creative activity.  In becoming an expert
            photographer, for example, one must learn how to look at a scene and
            know how dark each region will appear on a print for each possible
            choice of exposure and development<FOOTNOTE>The textbook was written
	    at a time when photography commonly involved photographic development,
	    a chemical process for making paper prints from photographic film.
	    </FOOTNOTE>
	    conditions.  Only then can one
            reason backward, planning framing, lighting, exposure, and development
            to obtain the desired effects.  So it is with programming, where we
            are planning the course of action to be taken by a process and where
            we control the process by means of a program.  To become experts, we
            must learn to visualize the processes generated by various types of
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  
            Only after we have developed such a skill can we learn
            to reliably construct programs that exhibit the desired behavior.
          </TEXT>

          <TEXT>
            <INDEX><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE><SUBINDEX>pattern@as pattern for local evolution of a process</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
            <INDEX>local evolution of a process</INDEX>
            <INDEX>process<SUBINDEX>local evolution of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
            A <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> 
            is a pattern for the <EM>local evolution</EM> of a
            computational process.  It specifies how each stage of the process is
            built upon the previous stage.  We would like to be able to make
            statements about the overall, or <EM>global</EM>, behavior of a
            process whose local evolution has been specified by a 
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  
            This is very difficult to do in general, but we can at least try to
            describe some typical patterns of process evolution.
          </TEXT>

          <TEXT>
            In this section we will examine some common <QUOTE>shapes</QUOTE> for processes
            generated by simple 
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>. 
            We will also investigate the
            rates at which these processes consume the important computational
            resources of time and space.  
            The 
            <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> 
            we will consider
            are very simple.  Their role is like that played by test patterns in
            photography: as oversimplified prototypical patterns, rather than
            practical examples in their own right.
          </TEXT>

      <!-- Subsection 1 : Linear Recursion and Iteration -->
      &subsection1.2.1;

      <!-- Subsection 2 : Tree Recursion -->
      &subsection1.2.2;

      <!-- Subsection 3 : Orders of Growth -->
      &subsection1.2.3;

      <!-- Subsection 4 : Exponentiation -->
      &subsection1.2.4;

      <!-- Subsection 5 : Greatest Comman Divisors -->
      &subsection1.2.5;

      <!-- Subsection 6 : Example: Testing for Primality -->
      &subsection1.2.6;

    </SECTION>
