    <SUBSECTION>
      <NAME>
  Memory as Vectors
      </NAME>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:memory-as-vectors"/>
      <TEXT>
  A conventional computer memory can be thought of as an array of
  cubbyholes, each of which can contain a piece of information.  Each
  cubbyhole has a unique name, called its 
  <INDEX>address</INDEX>
  <EM>address</EM> or 
  <INDEX>location</INDEX>
  <EM>
    location</EM>.  Typical memory systems provide two primitive operations:
  one that fetches the data stored in a specified location and one that
  assigns new data to a specified location.  Memory addresses can be
  incremented to support sequential access to some set of the
  cubbyholes.  More generally, many important data operations require
  that memory addresses be treated as data, which can be stored in
  memory locations and manipulated in machine registers.  The
  representation of list structure is one application of such 
  <INDEX>address arithmetic</INDEX>
  <INDEX>arithmetic<SUBINDEX>address arithmetic</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <EM>
    address arithmetic</EM>.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  To model computer memory, we use a new kind of data
  structure called a 
  <INDEX>vector (data structure)</INDEX>
  <EM>vector</EM>.  Abstractly, a vector is a compound
  data object whose individual elements can be accessed by means of an
  integer index in an amount of time that is independent of the
  index.<FOOTNOTE>We could represent memory as lists of items.
    However, the access time would then not be independent of the index,
    since accessing the <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>th element of a list requires <LATEXINLINE>$n-1$</LATEXINLINE> <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cdr</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>tail</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    operations.</FOOTNOTE> In order to describe memory operations, we use two
  primitive Scheme
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  for manipulating vectors:

  <UL>
    <!-- \indprim*{vector-ref}-->
    <!-- 
        \ind*{primitive
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
        (those marked <EM>ns</EM> are not in the IEEE Scheme standard)}[vector-ref@<SCHEMEINLINE>vector-ref</SCHEMEINLINE>]
        -->
    <LI><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(vector-ref </SCHEMEINLINE><LATEXINLINE>vector n</LATEXINLINE><SCHEMEINLINE>)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> returns the <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>th
      element of the vector.

      <!-- \indprim*{vector-set!}-->
      <!-- \ind*{primitive
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    (those marked <EM>ns</EM> are not in the IEEE Scheme standard)}[vector-set!@<SCHEMEINLINE>vector-set!</SCHEMEINLINE>]
    -->
    </LI>
    <LI><SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(vector-set! </SCHEMEINLINE><LATEXINLINE>vector n value</LATEXINLINE><SCHEMEINLINE>)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> sets
      the <LATEXINLINE>$n$</LATEXINLINE>th element of the vector to the designated value.
    </LI>

  </UL>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  For example, if <SCHEMEINLINE>v</SCHEMEINLINE> is a vector, then <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(vector-ref v 5)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> gets
  the fifth entry in the vector <SCHEMEINLINE>v</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(vector-set! v 5 7)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  changes the value of the fifth entry of the vector <SCHEMEINLINE>v</SCHEMEINLINE> to 7.<FOOTNOTE>For completeness, we should specify a <SCHEMEINLINE>make-vector</SCHEMEINLINE>
    operation that constructs vectors.  However, in the present
    application we will use vectors only to model fixed divisions of the
    computer memory.</FOOTNOTE>
  For computer memory, this access can be implemented
  through the use of address arithmetic to combine a <EM>base address</EM>
  that specifies the beginning location of a vector in memory with an
  <EM>index</EM> that specifies the offset of a particular element of the vector.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING> 
  <NAME>Representing <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> data</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <INDEX>pair(s)<SUBINDEX>represented using vectors|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>list structure<SUBINDEX>represented using vectors|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <TEXT>
  We can use vectors to implement the basic pair structures required for
  a list-structured memory.  Let us imagine that computer memory is
  divided into two vectors: 
  <!--  \indcode{the-cars}[vector] -->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cars</SCHEMEINLINE> and 
  <!--  \indcode{the-cdrs}[vector] -->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cdrs</SCHEMEINLINE>.  We will
  represent list structure as follows: A pointer to a pair is an index
  into the two vectors.  The 
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>car</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>head</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> of the pair is the entry in <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cars</SCHEMEINLINE> with the designated index, and the 
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cdr</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>tail</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> of the pair is
  the entry in <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cdrs</SCHEMEINLINE> with the designated index.  We also need a
  representation for objects other than pairs (such as numbers and
  symbols) and a way to distinguish one kind of data from another.
  There are many methods of accomplishing this, but they all reduce to
  using 
  <INDEX>typed pointer</INDEX>
  <INDEX>pointer<SUBINDEX>typed</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <EM>typed pointers</EM>, that is, to extending the notion of
  <QUOTE>pointer</QUOTE> to include information on data type.<FOOTNOTE>This is
    precisely the same 
    <INDEX>tagged data</INDEX>
    <INDEX>data<SUBINDEX>tagged</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <QUOTE>tagged data</QUOTE> idea we introduced in chapter<SPACE/>2 for
    dealing with generic operations.  Here, however, the data types are
    included at the primitive machine level rather than constructed
    through the use of lists.</FOOTNOTE> The data type enables the system to
  distinguish a pointer to a pair (which consists of the <QUOTE>pair</QUOTE> data
  type and an index into the memory vectors) from pointers to other
  kinds of data (which consist of some other data type and whatever is
  being used to represent data of that type).  Two data objects are
  <!-- \indprim{eq?}[equality@as equality of pointers]-->
  considered to be the same (<SCHEMEINLINE>eq?</SCHEMEINLINE>) if their pointers are
  identical.<FOOTNOTE>Type information may be encoded in a variety of
    ways, depending on the details of the machine on which the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    system is to be implemented.  The execution efficiency of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    programs will be strongly dependent on how cleverly this choice is
    made, but it is difficult to formulate general design rules for good
    choices.  The most straightforward way to implement typed pointers is
    to allocate a fixed set of bits in each pointer to be a 
    <INDEX>type field</INDEX>
    <EM>type
      field</EM> that encodes the data type.  Important questions to be
    addressed in designing such a representation include the following:
    How many type bits are required?  How large must the vector indices
    be?  How efficiently can the primitive machine instructions be used to
    manipulate the type fields of pointers?  Machines that include special
    hardware for the efficient handling of type fields are said to have
    <INDEX>tagged architecture</INDEX>
    <EM>tagged architectures</EM>.</FOOTNOTE> 
  Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:box-and-pointer-memory"/>
  illustrates the use of this method to represent the list <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((1 2) 3 4)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, whose box-and-pointer diagram is also shown.  We use letter
  prefixes to denote the data-type information.  Thus, a pointer to the
  pair with index 5 is denoted <SCHEMEINLINE>p5</SCHEMEINLINE>, the empty list is denoted by
  the pointer <SCHEMEINLINE>e0</SCHEMEINLINE>, and a pointer to the number 4 is denoted <SCHEMEINLINE>n4</SCHEMEINLINE>.  In the box-and-pointer diagram, we have indicated at the lower
  left of each pair the vector index that specifies where the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>car</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>head</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cdr</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>tail</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> of the pair are stored.  The blank locations in <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cars</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cdrs</SCHEMEINLINE> may contain parts of other list
  structures (not of interest here).

  \begin{figure}
  \epsffile{/zu/hal/sicp/chapter-5/figs/fig-13.eps}
  \figcaption {Box-and-pointer and memory-vector representations 
  of the list <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>((1 2) 3 4)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.}
  <LABEL NAME="fig:box-and-pointer-memory"/>
  \end{figure}                                                         
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  A pointer to a number, such as <SCHEMEINLINE>n4</SCHEMEINLINE>,
  might consist of a type indicating numeric data together with the
  actual representation of the number 4.<FOOTNOTE>This decision on the
    <!-- \indprim{eq?}[numerical equality and]-->
    <INDEX>equality<SUBINDEX>numbers@of numbers</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>number(s)<SUBINDEX>equality of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    representation of numbers determines whether <SCHEMEINLINE>eq?</SCHEMEINLINE>, which tests
    equality of pointers, can be used to test for equality of numbers.  If
    the pointer contains the number itself, then equal numbers will have
    the same pointer.  But if the pointer contains the index of a location
    where the number is stored, equal numbers will be guaranteed to have
    equal pointers only if we are careful never to store the same number
    in more than one location.</FOOTNOTE>
  To deal with numbers that are too large to
  be represented in the fixed amount of space allocated for a single
  pointer, we could use a distinct 
  <INDEX>bignum</INDEX>
  <EM>bignum</EM> data type, for which the
  pointer designates a list in which the parts of the number are
  stored.<FOOTNOTE>This is just like writing a number as a sequence of
    digits, except that each <QUOTE>digit</QUOTE> is a number between 0 and the
    largest number that can be stored in a single pointer.</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <INDEX>symbol(s)<SUBINDEX>representation of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  A symbol might be represented as a typed pointer that designates a
  sequence of the characters that form the symbol<APOS/>s printed representation.
  This sequence is constructed by the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> reader when the character string
  is initially encountered in input.  Since we want two instances of a
  symbol to be recognized as the <QUOTE>same</QUOTE> symbol by <SCHEMEINLINE>eq?</SCHEMEINLINE> and we
  <!-- \indprim{eq?}[implementation for symbols]-->
  want <SCHEMEINLINE>eq?</SCHEMEINLINE> to be a simple test for equality of pointers, we must
  ensure that if the reader sees the same character string twice, it
  will use the same pointer (to the same sequence of characters) to
  represent both occurrences.  To accomplish this, the reader maintains
  a table, traditionally called the 
  <INDEX>obarray</INDEX>
  <EM>obarray</EM>, of all the symbols it
  has ever encountered.  When the reader encounters a character string
  and is about to construct a symbol, it checks the obarray to see if it
  has ever before seen the same character string.  If it has not, it
  uses the characters to construct a new symbol (a typed pointer to a
  new character sequence) and enters this pointer in the obarray.  If the
  reader has seen the string before, it returns the symbol pointer
  stored in the obarray.  This process of replacing character strings by
  unique pointers is called 
  <INDEX>interning symbols</INDEX>
  <INDEX>symbol(s)<SUBINDEX>interning</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <EM>interning</EM> symbols.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING> 
  <NAME>Implementing the primitive list operations</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <LABEL NAME="sec:impl-list-ops"/>
      <TEXT>
  <!--  \indcode{the-cars}[register] -->
  <!--  \indcode{the-cdrs}[register] -->
  Given the above representation scheme, we can replace each
  <QUOTE>primitive</QUOTE> list operation of a register machine with one or more
  primitive vector operations.  We will use two registers, <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cars</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cdrs</SCHEMEINLINE>, to identify the memory vectors, and will
  assume that <SCHEMEINLINE>vector-ref</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>vector-set!</SCHEMEINLINE> are available as
  primitive operations.  We also assume that numeric operations on
  pointers (such as incrementing a pointer, using a pair pointer to
  index a vector, or adding two numbers) use only the index portion of
  the typed pointer.
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  For example, we can make a register machine support the instructions

  <!-- \indprim{car}[implemented with vectors]-->
  <!-- \indprim{cdr}[implemented with vectors]-->
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (assign ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^ (op car) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))

      (assign ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^ (op cdr) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>

  if we implement these, respectively, as

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (assign ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^ (op vector-ref) (reg the-cars) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))

      (assign ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^ (op vector-ref) (reg the-cdrs) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  The instructions
  <!-- \indprim{set-car!}[implemented with vectors]-->
  <!-- \indprim{set-cdr!}[implemented with vectors]-->
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (perform (op set-car!) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))

      (perform (op set-cdr!) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  are implemented as
  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (perform
      (op vector-set!) (reg the-cars) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))

      (perform
      (op vector-set!) (reg the-cdrs) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  <!-- \indprim{cons}[implemented with vectors]-->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>Cons</SCHEMEINLINE> is performed by allocating an unused index and storing the
  arguments to <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> in <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cars</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>the-cdrs</SCHEMEINLINE> at that
  indexed vector position.  We presume that there is a special register,
  <!-- \indcodeplus{free}{register}-->
  <SCHEMEINLINE>free</SCHEMEINLINE>, that always holds a pair pointer containing the next
  available index, and that we can increment the index part of that
  pointer to find the next free location.<FOOTNOTE>There are other ways
    of finding free storage.  For example, we could link together all the
    unused pairs into a 
    <INDEX>free list</INDEX>
    <EM>free list</EM>.  Our free locations are
    consecutive (and hence can be accessed by incrementing a pointer)
    because we are using a compacting garbage collector, as we will see in
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:gc"/>.</FOOTNOTE>
  For example, the instruction

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (assign ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^ (op cons) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{3}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  is implemented as the following sequence of vector
  operations:<FOOTNOTE>This is essentially the implementation of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> in terms of <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>set-car!</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>set_head</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>set-cdr!</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>set_tail</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, as described in
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:mutable-list-structure"/>.  The operation <SCHEMEINLINE>get-new-pair</SCHEMEINLINE> used in that implementation is realized here by the <SCHEMEINLINE>  free</SCHEMEINLINE> pointer.</FOOTNOTE>

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (perform
      (op vector-set!) (reg the-cars) (reg free) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
      (perform
      (op vector-set!) (reg the-cdrs) (reg free) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{3}$</LATEXINLINE>^))
      (assign ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^ (reg free))
      (assign free (op +) (reg free) (const 1))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  The <SCHEMEINLINE>eq?</SCHEMEINLINE> operation

  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (op eq?) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{1}$</LATEXINLINE>^) (reg ^reg<LATEXINLINE>$_{2}$</LATEXINLINE>^)
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  simply tests the equality of all fields in the registers, and
  <!-- \indprim{pair?}[implemented with typed pointers]-->
  <!-- \indprim{null?}[implemented with typed pointers]-->
  <!-- \indprim{symbol?}[implemented with typed pointers]-->
  <!-- \indprim{number?}[implemented with typed pointers]-->
  predicates such as <SCHEMEINLINE>pair?</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>null?</SCHEMEINLINE>, <SCHEMEINLINE>symbol?</SCHEMEINLINE>, and <SCHEMEINLINE>number?</SCHEMEINLINE> need only check the type field.
      </TEXT>

      <SUBHEADING>
  <NAME>Implementing stacks</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <INDEX>stack<SUBINDEX>representing</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <TEXT>
  Although our register machines use stacks, we need do nothing special
  here, since stacks can be modeled in terms of lists.  The stack can be
  a list of the saved values, pointed to by a special register <SCHEMEINLINE>the-stack</SCHEMEINLINE>.  Thus, <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(save ^reg^)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> can be implemented as

  <!-- \indcodeplus{save}{(in register machine)}[implementing]-->
  <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
    <SCHEME>
      (assign the-stack (op cons) (reg ^reg^) (reg the-stack))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  <!-- \indcodeplus{restore}{(in register machine)}[implementing]-->
  Similarly, <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(restore ^reg^)</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> can be implemented as
  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (assign ^reg^ (op car) (reg the-stack))
      (assign the-stack (op cdr) (reg the-stack))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>

  and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>(perform (op initialize-stack))</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>???</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> can be implemented as
  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
      (assign the-stack (const ()))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
      </TEXT>

      <TEXT>
  These operations can be further expanded in terms of the vector
  operations given above.  In conventional computer architectures,
  however, it is usually advantageous to allocate the stack as a
  separate vector.  Then pushing and popping the stack can be
  accomplished by incrementing or decrementing an index into that
  vector.
      </TEXT>

      <EXERCISE>
  Draw the box-and-pointer representation and the memory-vector
  representation (as in Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:box-and-pointer-memory"/>) of the
  list structure produced by

  <SNIPPET>
    <SCHEME>
(define x (cons 1 2))
(define y (list x x))
    </SCHEME>
  </SNIPPET>
  with the <SCHEMEINLINE>free</SCHEMEINLINE> pointer initially <SCHEMEINLINE>p1</SCHEMEINLINE>.  What is the final
  value of <SCHEMEINLINE>free</SCHEMEINLINE><LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE>?  What pointers represent the values of <SCHEMEINLINE>x</SCHEMEINLINE> and <SCHEMEINLINE>y</SCHEMEINLINE><LATEXINLINE>$\,$</LATEXINLINE>?
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE><LABEL NAME="ex:count-leaves-machine"/>
  <!--  \indcode{count-leaves}[as register machine] -->
  Implement register machines for the following
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.
  Assume that the list-structure memory operations are available as
  machine primitives.
  <OL>
    <LI>
      Recursive <SCHEMEINLINE>count-leaves</SCHEMEINLINE>:

      <SNIPPET>
        <SCHEME>
    (define (count-leaves tree)
    (cond ((null? tree) 0)
    ((not (pair? tree)) 1)
    (else (+ (count-leaves (car tree))
                (count-leaves (cdr tree))))))
        </SCHEME>
      </SNIPPET>
    </LI>
    <LI>
      Recursive <SCHEMEINLINE>count-leaves</SCHEMEINLINE> with explicit counter:

      <SNIPPET>
        <SCHEME>
    (define (count-leaves tree)
    (define (count-iter tree n)
    (cond ((null? tree) n)
    ((not (pair? tree)) (+ n 1))
    (else (count-iter (cdr tree)
                (count-iter (car tree) n)))))
    (count-iter tree 0))
        </SCHEME>
      </SNIPPET>
    </LI>
  </OL>
      </EXERCISE>

      <EXERCISE>
  <!--  \indcode{append}[register@as register machine] -->
  <!--  \indcode{append!}[as register machine] -->
  Exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:append!"/> of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:mutable-list-structure"/>
  presented an <SCHEMEINLINE>append</SCHEMEINLINE>
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  that appends two lists to form a
  new list and an <SCHEMEINLINE>append!</SCHEMEINLINE>
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
  that splices two lists
  together.  Design a register machine to implement each of these
  <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Assume that the list-structure memory operations are
  available as primitive operations.
      </EXERCISE>
      <INDEX>pair(s)<SUBINDEX>represented using vectors|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
      <INDEX>list structure<SUBINDEX>represented using vectors|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

    </SUBSECTION>
