<CHAPTER>
  <NAME>Computing with Register Machines</NAME>

  <HISTORY>
    % Feb '98 Add tex '\label's for manual to reference.
    % 4/13-4/15 Indexing [after final printout of chapters]
    % 4/13/96 Last-minute pagination change to get compiled-code figs on
    %         facing pages
    % 4/12    Pagination adjustments from proofreading
    % 4/11/96 minor fixes; checked against before-indexing
    % 4/9/96  fix a word
    % 4/6-... Julie index fixes (and 4/8 change 'ns')
    % 4/5/96  Hal indexing
    % 4/3/96  indexing changes
    % 4/2/96  adjusted pagination in 5.1-5.3, paginated rest of 5.5
    % 4/1/96  Julie: paginated 5.4 and part of 5.5
    % 3/29/96 Julie: indexing fixes
    % 3/22/96 Julie: paginated 5.2-5.3
    % 3/21/96 Julie: paginated 5.1
    % 3/20-3/21/96 Julie &amp; Hal indexing
    % 3/17/96 Julie: a couple of index entries consistent with ch4
    % 3/4/96  reword to 'fix' most triple and quadruple hyphenation
    % 3/3/96  change countleaves to count-leaves (to match ch2 change)
    % 2/26-3/3/96 fix some bad line breaks
    % 2/24/96 flush \noindent after {lisp} by closing up space with 
    % 2/24/96 use smalltt to make some stuff fit nicely in 5.2
    % 2/23/96 use Stabular instead of point-size changes
    % 2/22/96 new spec for epigraph
    %2/19/96 change exp-iter - -&gt; expt-iter
  </HISTORY>

  <EPIGRAPH>

    My aim is to show that the heavenly machine is not a kind of divine,
    live being, but a kind of clockwork (and he who believes that a clock
    has soul attributes the maker<APOS/>s glory to the work), insofar as nearly
    all the manifold motions are caused by a most simple and material
    force, just as all motions of the clock are caused by a single weight.

    <INDEX>Kepler, Johannes</INDEX>
    <ATTRIBUTION><AUTHOR>Johannes Kepler</AUTHOR>
      <DATE>(letter to Herwart von Hohenburg, 1605)</DATE>
    </ATTRIBUTION>

  </EPIGRAPH>

  <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

  <TEXT>
    We began this book by studying processes and by describing processes
    in terms of
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    written in <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  To explain the meanings of
    these
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, we used a succession of models of evaluation: the
    substitution model of chapter<SPACE/>1, the environment model of chapter<SPACE/>3,
    and the metacircular evaluator of chapter<SPACE/>4.  Our examination of the
    metacircular evaluator, in particular, dispelled much of the mystery
    of how <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>-like languages are interpreted.
    But even the metacircular evaluator leaves important questions
    unanswered, because it fails to elucidate the mechanisms of control in
    a <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> system.  For instance, the evaluator does not explain how the
    evaluation of a subexpression manages to return a value to the
    expression that uses this value, nor does the evaluator explain how
    some recursive
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    generate iterative processes (that is, are evaluated
    using constant space) whereas other recursive
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    generate recursive
    processes.  These questions remain unanswered because the metacircular
    evaluator is itself a <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> program and hence inherits the control
    structure of the underlying <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> system.  In order to provide a more
    complete description of the control structure of the <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> evaluator,
    we must work at a more primitive level than <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> itself.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    In this chapter we will describe processes in terms of the step-by-step
    operation of a traditional computer.  Such a computer, or 
    <INDEX>register machine</INDEX>
    <EM>
      register machine</EM>, sequentially executes 
    <EM>instructions</EM> that
    manipulate the contents of a fixed set of storage elements called 
    <INDEX>register(s)</INDEX>
    <EM>
      registers</EM>.  A typical register-machine instruction applies a
    primitive operation to the contents of some registers and assigns the
    result to another register.  Our descriptions of processes executed by
    register machines will look very much like <QUOTE>machine-language</QUOTE>
    programs for traditional computers.  However, instead of focusing on
    the machine language of any particular computer, we will examine
    several <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    and design a specific register machine to
    execute each
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>.  Thus, we will approach our task from the
    perspective of a hardware architect rather than that of a
    machine-language computer programmer.  In designing register machines,
    we will develop mechanisms for implementing important programming
    constructs such as recursion.  We will also present a language for
    describing designs for register machines.  In
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:simulator"/> we will
    implement a <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>Lisp</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>JavaScript</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE> program that
    uses these descriptions to simulate the machines we design.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    Most of the primitive operations of our register machines are very
    simple.  For example, an operation might add the numbers fetched from
    two registers, producing a result to be stored into a third register.
    Such an operation can be performed by easily described hardware.  In
    order to deal with list structure, however, we will also use the
    memory operations <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>car</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>head</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cdr</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>tail</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, and <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>cons</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>pair</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>, which require
    an elaborate storage-allocation mechanism.  In
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:storage-allocation"/> we study their implementation in
    terms of more elementary operations.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    In section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:eceval"/>, after we have accumulated experience
    formulating simple
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedures</SCHEME><JAVASCRIPT>functions</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    as register machines, we will design a
    machine that carries out the algorithm described by the metacircular
    evaluator of section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:mc-eval"/>.  This will fill in the gap in
    our understanding of how Scheme expressions are interpreted, by
    providing an explicit model for the mechanisms of control in the
    evaluator.
    In section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:compilation"/> we will study a simple compiler that
    translates Scheme programs into sequences of instructions that can be
    executed directly with the registers and operations of the evaluator
    register machine.
  </TEXT>

  <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

  <EXCLUDE>

  <!-- Section 1 : Designing Register Machines -->
  &section5.1;

  <!-- Section 2 : A Register-Machine Simulator -->
  &section5.2;

  <!-- Section 3 : Storage Allocation and Garbage Collection -->
  &section5.3;

  <!-- Section 4 : The Explicit-Control Evaluator -->
  &section5.4;

  <!-- Section 5 : Compilation -->
  &section5.5;

  </EXCLUDE>

</CHAPTER>
