  <MATTER>
    <NAME>
        Foreword
    </NAME>

    <TEXT>
      I had the pleasure of meeting the amazing Alan Perlis and
      talking with him a few times, when I was still a student. He and
      I had in common a deep love and respect for two very different
      programming languages: Lisp and APL. Following in his footsteps
      is a daunting task, even though he blazed an excellent
      trail. Still, I would like to reexamine one comment he made in
      the original foreword to this book (and, please, I suggest that
      you read <EM>his</EM> foreword, which immediately follows this one,
      before you finish this one). Is it really true that it is better
      to have 100 functions operate on one data structure than to have
      10 functions operate on 10 data structures?
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      To answer that question carefully, we first need to ask whether
      that one data structure is <QUOTE>universal</QUOTE>: can it
      conveniently fulfill the roles of those 10 more specialized data
      structures?
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      For that matter, we can also ask: do we really need 100
      functions? Is there a single universal function that can fulfill
      the roles of all those other functions?
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      The surprising answer to that last question is
      <QUOTE>yes</QUOTE>; it is only slightly tricky to construct a
      function that accepts (1) a data structure that serves as a
      description of some other function, and (2) a list of arguments,
      and behaves exactly as that other function would when applied to
      the given arguments. And it is only slightly tricky to design a
      data structure capable of describing any computation
      whatsoever. One such data structure (the tagged-list
      representation of expressions and statements, paired with
      environments that associate names with values) and one such
      universal function (<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>apply</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>)
      are described in Chapter 4 of this book. So maybe we need only
      one function and one data structure.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      That is true in theory. In practice, we find it convenient to
      draw distinctions that help us, as human beings constructing
      descriptions of computations, to organize the structure of our
      code so that we can better understand them. I believe that
      Perlis was making a remark not about computational capability,
      but about human abilities and human limitations.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      One thing the human mind seems to do well is to name things; we
      have powerful associative memories. Given a name, we can quickly
      recall some associated thing to mind. This is why we typically
      find it easier to work with the lambda calculus than the
      combinatory calculus; it is much easier for most people to
      interpret the Lisp expression
      <SCHEMEINLINE>(lambda (x) (lambda (y) (+ x y)))</SCHEMEINLINE>
      or the JavaScript expression
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>x => y => x + y</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
      than the combinatory expression
      <BLOCKQUOTE>
	((S ((S (K S)) ((S ((S (K S)) ((S (K K)) (K +)))) ((S (K K)) I)))) (K I))
      </BLOCKQUOTE>
      even though there is a direct structural correspondence, easily
      expressed in five lines of Lisp code.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      So while in principle we could get by with just one universal
      function, we prefer to modularize our code, to give names to the
      various pieces, and to mention the names of function descriptions
      rather than constantly feeding the descriptions themselves to the
      universal function.
    </TEXT>
    <DO_BREAK_PAGE/>
    <TEXT>
      In my 1998 talk <QUOTE>Growing a Language,</QUOTE> I commented
      that a good programmer <QUOTE>does not just write programs. A good
      programmer builds a working vocabulary.</QUOTE> As we design and
      define more and more parts of our programs, we give names to
      those parts, and the result is that we have a richer language in
      <SHRINK_PARAGRAPH lines="1"/>
      which to write the rest.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      But we also find it natural to draw distinctions among data
      structures, and to give them names.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      It may be that nested lists are a universal data structure (and
      it is worth noting that many modern and widely used data
      structures, such as HTML and XML and JSON, are also
      parenthetically nested representations, only slightly more
      elaborate than Lisp<APOS/>s bare parentheses).  There are also
      many functions, such as finding the length of a list or applying
      a function to every element of a list and getting back a list of
      the results, that are useful in a wide variety of
      situations. And yet, when I am thinking about a specific
      computation, I often say to myself, <QUOTE>This list of two
      things I expect to be a personal name and a surname, but that
      list of two things I expect to be the real and imaginary parts
      of a complex number, and that other list of two things I will
      regard as the numerator and denominator of a fraction.</QUOTE>
      In other words, I draw distinctions<EMDASH/>and it may be useful
      to represent those distinctions explicitly in the data
      structure, in part to prevent mistakes such as accidentally
      treating a complex number as a fraction. (Again, this is a
      comment about human abilities and human limitations.)
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      Since the first edition of this book was written, almost four decades
      ago, a lot more ways of organizing data have become relatively
      standard, in particular the <QUOTE>object-oriented</QUOTE> approach, and many
      languages, including JavaScript, support specialized data structures
      such as objects and strings and heaps and maps with a variety of
      built-in mechanisms and libraries. But in doing so, many languages
      abandoned support for more general, universal notions. Java, for
      example, originally did not support first-class functions, and has
      incorporated them only relatively recently, greatly increasing its
      expressive power.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      APL, likewise, originally did not support first-class functions, and
      moreover its original single data structure<EMDASH/>arrays of any number of
      dimensions<EMDASH/>was not so conveniently useful as a universal data
      structure because arrays could not contain other arrays as
      elements. More recent versions of APL do support anonymous function
      values and nested arrays, and these have made APL dramatically more
      expressive. (The original design of APL did have two very good things
      going for it: a comprehensive set of functions applicable to that one
      data structure, and moreover an extremely well chosen set of names for
      those functions. I<APOS/>m not talking about the funny symbols and Greek
      letters, but the spoken words that APL programmers use when mentioning
      them, words like
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>shape</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>,
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>reshape</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>,
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>compress</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>,
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>expand</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>, and
      <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>laminate</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>;
      these are names not for the
      symbols, but for the functions they represent. Ken Iverson had a real
      knack for choosing short, memorable, vivid names for functions on
      arrays.)
    </TEXT>
    <SHORT_PAGE lines="2"/>
    <TEXT>
      While JavaScript, like Java, was originally designed with objects and
      methods in mind, it also incorporated first-class functions from the
      beginning, and it is not difficult to use its objects to define a
      universal data structure. As a result, JavaScript is not as distant
      from Lisp as you would think, and as this edition of
      <EM>Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</EM>
      demonstrates, it is a good
      alternate framework for presenting the key ideas.
      <EM>SICP</EM>
      was never about a programming language; it presents powerful, general
      ideas for program organization that ought to be useful in any
      language.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      What do Lisp and JavaScript have in common?  The ability to abstract a
      computation (code plus some associated data) for later execution as a
      function; the ability to embed references to such functions within
      data structures; the ability to invoke functions on arguments; the
      ability to draw a distinction (conditional execution); a convenient
      universal data structure; completely automatic storage management for
      that data (which seems like a no-brainer, given everything else, until
      you realize that many widely used programming languages don<APOS/>t have
      it); a large set of useful functions for operating on that universal
      data structure; and standard strategies for using the universal data
      structure to represent more specialized data structures.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      So maybe the truth is somewhere in between the extremes that Perlis so
      eloquently posited. Maybe the sweet spot is something more like 40
      functions general enough to operate usefully on a universal data
      structure such as lists, but also 10 sets of 6 functions each that are
      relevant when we take one of 10 specialized views of that universal
      data structure. This is manageable if we give good names to these
      functions and specialized views.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      As you read this book, please pay attention not only to the
      programming language constructs and how they are used, but also to the
      <EM>names</EM> given to functions and variables and data
      structures. They are not all as short and vivid as the names Iverson
      chose for his APL functions, but they have been chosen in a deliberate
      and systematic way to enhance your understanding of the overall
      program structure.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      Primitives, means of combination, functional abstraction, naming, and
      conventions for using a universal data structure in specialized ways
      by drawing distinctions: these are the fundamental building blocks of
      a good programming language. From there, imagination and good
      engineering judgment based on experience can do the rest.
    </TEXT>

  <SIGNATURE>
    <ATTRIBUTION>
      <AUTHOR>Guy L. Steele Jr.</AUTHOR> 
      <TITLE>Lexington, Massachusetts, 2021</TITLE>
    </ATTRIBUTION>
  </SIGNATURE>
  
  </MATTER>
