<MATTER>

  <NAME>JavaScript Adaptation Making-of</NAME>

    <NAME>Background</NAME>

    <TEXT>
      Like the Source Academy, the JavaScript adaptation of SICP is an open-source community effort.
      The software and data required for making these web pages and the PDF edition are contained
      in the repository <LINK address="https://github.com/source-academy/sicp">Source Academy / sicp</LINK>,
      and improvements, extensions and discussions are handled in this repository as with many other
      open-source software projects.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      Martin Henz started translating SICP to JavaScript in 2008. He obtained the original
      <LaTeX/><SPACE/>sources of the textbook from the Gerald Sussman, and converted it to an XML
      format that allowed
      him to retain the original sources along with the JavaScript adaptation in a single file.
      He developed a processing system to generate HTML from XML, using XSLT, resulting in the
      first version of the JavaScript adaptation.
    </TEXT>

    <NAME>Mobile-friendly Web Edition</NAME>

    <TEXT>
      The <LINK address="https://sicp.comp.nus.edu.sg">mobile-friendly web edition</LINK>
      of SICP JS was designed and implemented by Liu Hang
      in 2017 and then further developed by Feng Piaopiao in 2018. Liu Hang decided to use Ruby on
      Rails for generating the HTML pages from the XML sources. 
      The XML documents are processed using Nokogiri. For that, the website is originally
      hosted as a Ruby on Rails application and the generated HTML files are then collected as
      a pure-HTML5 website. Formulas are retained in the resulting HTML files
      and are type-set by the reader's browser on-the-fly, using the MathJax system.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      In the textbook, program fragments often require other program fragments.
      In order to collect and execute the necessary programs, the corresponding
      <TT>SNIPPET</TT> tags in the xml files include <TT>REQUIRES</TT> tags. The Rails
      server uses these tags in order to assemble the executable programs. 
    </TEXT>

    <NAME>PDF Edition</NAME>

    <TEXT>
      The <LINK address="https://sicp.comp.nus.edu.sg/sicpjs.pdf">PDF edition</LINK>
      of SICP JS was designed and implemented by Chan Ger Hean in 2019.
      Ger Hean decided to use Node.js for generating <LATEX/> files from the XML sources.
      The <LATEX/> files are then typeset using the PdfLaTeX system.
    </TEXT>

    <NAME>E-book Edition</NAME>

    <TEXT>
      The <LINK address="https://sicp.comp.nus.edu.sg/sicpjs.epub">e-book edition</LINK>
      of SICP JS was designed and implemented by Jolyn Tan in 2019.
      Jolyn decided to use Node.js for generating <LATEX/> files from the XML sources.
      The <LATEX/> files are then processed into the EPUB 3 format using the
      pandoc system.
    </TEXT>

    <NAME>Figures</NAME>

    <TEXT>
      The figures are adapted from <LINK address="https://github.com/sarabander/sicp">HTML5/EPUB3 version of SICP</LINK>
      by Andres Raba. The figures are licensed under Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International
      License <LINK address="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0">(cc by-sa)</LINK>. JavaScript adaptations
      of figures were done by manually by Tobias Wrigstad using Inkscape and gratuitous use of sed. 
    </TEXT>

</MATTER>
