<MATTER>

  <NAME><WEB_ONLY DIFFERENT_TEXT="yes">About the SICP JS Project</WEB_ONLY></NAME>
  
  <WEB_ONLY DIFFERENT_TEXT="yes">
    
 <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>Background</NAME>
  </SUBHEADING>
  
    <TEXT>
      The JavaScript adaptation of SICP is an open-source community effort.
      The software and data required for making these web pages and the PDF edition are contained
      in the github repository
      <LINK address="https://github.com/source-academy/sicp">Source Academy / sicp</LINK>,
      and improvements, extensions and discussions are handled in this repository using <TT>git</TT>.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
      Martin Henz started translating SICP to JavaScript in 2008. He obtained the original
      <LaTeX/><SPACE/>sources of the second edition from Gerald Jay Sussman, and converted them to
      a custom-built XML format. The original sources are retained in the XML format, which
      allows for generating the
      <LINK address="https://sicp.sourceacademy.org">comparison edition</LINK>.
      A processing system written in XSLT resulted in the
      first version of the JavaScript adaptation around 2009, covering the first few sections of SICP.
      The content of SICP JS contained in the
      XML files are undergoing continuous improvement by the adapters Martin Henz and Tobias
      Wrigstad, and by the community of SICP JS readers, using the github repository.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
      In the book, program fragments often require other program fragments.
      In order to collect and execute the necessary programs, the corresponding
      <TT>SNIPPET</TT> tags in the xml files include <TT>REQUIRES</TT> tags. The 
      XML processors use these tags in order to assemble the executable programs.
      The project thus can be seen as a <EM>literate programming system</EM>, custom-made
      for authoring SICP JS.
    </TEXT>

    <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>Interactive SICP JS</NAME>
    </SUBHEADING>
    
    <TEXT>
      <LINK address="https://sourceacademy.org/sicpjs">Interactive SICP JS</LINK>
      was designed and implemented by Samuel Fang
      in 2021. The XML textbook sources are translated to a JSON format, which
      are then read and rendered by a dedicated component of the Source Academy.
    </TEXT>

    <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>Comparison Edition</NAME>
    </SUBHEADING>
    
    <TEXT>
      The precursor of the comparison edition was the 
      mobile-friendly web edition
      of SICP JS, designed and implemented by Liu Hang
      in 2017. Feng Piaopiao improved the system in 2018.
      He Xinyue and Wang Qian developed the
      <LINK address="https://sicp.sourceacademy.org/">comparison edition</LINK>
      in 2020.
      Formulas are retained in the resulting HTML files
      and are typeset by the reader's browser on the fly,
      using the MathJax system.
      Currently (2021), the comparison edition is maintained by Martin Henz.
    </TEXT>

    <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>PDF Edition</NAME>
    </SUBHEADING>
    
    <TEXT>
      The early PDF editions (2010-2018) used XSLT for generating <LaTeX/> from
      the XML sources.
      The first Node.js version of the PDF edition
      was designed and implemented by Chan Ger Hean in 2019.
      Currently (2021), Tobias Wrigstad and Martin Henz are the main developers of this system.
    </TEXT>

    <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>E-book Edition</NAME>
    </SUBHEADING>
    
    <TEXT>
      An e-book edition
      of SICP JS (currently not available) was designed and implemented by Jolyn Tan in 2019,
      using Node.js for generating <LaTeX/> files from the XML sources.
      The <LaTeX/> files were processed into the EPUB 3 format using the
      pandoc system.
    </TEXT>

    <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>Figures</NAME>
    </SUBHEADING>

    <TEXT>
      Most figures are adapted from
      <LINK address="https://github.com/sarabander/sicp">HTML5/EPUB3 version of SICP</LINK>
      by Andres Raba. The figures are licensed under Creative Commons
      Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International
      License <LINK address="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0">(cc by-sa)</LINK>.
      JavaScript adaptations
      of figures were done by manually by Tobias Wrigstad using Inkscape and gratuitous use of
      <TT>sed</TT>. 
    </TEXT>
    
  </WEB_ONLY>
  
</MATTER>
