<SUBSECTION>
  <NAME>
    The Nature of Time in Concurrent Systems
  </NAME>

  <LABEL NAME="sec:nature-of-time"/>
  <INDEX>time<SUBINDEX>concurrent@in concurrent systems|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

  <TEXT>
    On the surface, time seems straightforward.  It
    is an ordering imposed on events.<FOOTNOTE>To quote some graffiti seen on a Cambridge
    <INDEX>time<SUBINDEX>purpose of</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    building wall: <QUOTE>Time is a device that was invented to keep everything
    from happening at once.</QUOTE></FOOTNOTE>
    For any events <LATEXINLINE>$A$</LATEXINLINE> and <LATEXINLINE>$B$</LATEXINLINE>,
    either <LATEXINLINE>$A$</LATEXINLINE> occurs before <LATEXINLINE>$B$</LATEXINLINE>,
    <LATEXINLINE>$A$</LATEXINLINE><SPACE/>and<SPACE/><LATEXINLINE>$B$</LATEXINLINE>
    are simultaneous, or <LATEXINLINE>$A$</LATEXINLINE> occurs after
    <LATEXINLINE>$B$</LATEXINLINE>.  For instance,
    returning to the bank account example, suppose that Peter withdraws
    <DOLLAR/>10 and Paul withdraws <DOLLAR/>25 from a 
    <INDEX>bank account<SUBINDEX>joint, with concurrent access</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    joint account that initially
    contains <DOLLAR/>100, leaving <DOLLAR/>65 in the account.  Depending on the order
    of the two withdrawals, the sequence of balances in the account is
    either <LATEXINLINE>$\$100 \rightarrow \$90 \rightarrow\$65$<LATEXINLINE>
    or
    </LATEXINLINE>$\$100 \rightarrow \$75 \rightarrow\$65$</LATEXINLINE>.
    In a computer implementation of the banking system, this changing
    sequence of balances could be  modeled by successive assignments to
    a variable <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE>.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    In complex situations, however, such a view can be problematic.
    Suppose that Peter and Paul, and other people besides, are
    accessing the same bank account through a network of banking machines
    distributed all over the world.  The actual sequence of balances in
    the account will depend critically on the detailed timing of the
    accesses and the details of the communication among the machines.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    <INDEX>order of events
    <SUBINDEX>indeterminacy in concurrent systems</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    This indeterminacy in the order of events can pose serious problems in
    the design of concurrent systems.  For instance, suppose that the
    withdrawals made by Peter and Paul are implemented as two separate
    processes sharing a common variable <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE>,
    each process  specified by the
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME>procedure</SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>function</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    given in
    Section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:local-state-variables"/>:
    <SNIPPET>
      <REQUIRES>balance_concurrency</REQUIRES>
      <EXAMPLE>withdraw_example_concurrency</EXAMPLE>
      <SCHEME>
            <!--  \indcode{withdraw}[problems in concurrent system] -->
(define (withdraw amount)
   (if (&gt;= balance amount)
     (begin (set! balance (- balance amount))
            balance)
     "Insufficient funds"))
      </SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
            <!--  \indcode{withdraw}[problems in concurrent system] -->
function withdraw(amount) {
    if (balance &gt;= amount) {
        balance = balance - amount;
        return balance;
    } else {
        return "Insufficient funds";
    }
}
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>

    <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
      <NAME>balance_concurrency</NAME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
let balance = 100;
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>
    
    <SNIPPET HIDE="yes">
      <NAME>withdraw_example_concurrency</NAME>
      <SCHEME>
	(withdraw 25) ;; output: 75
      </SCHEME>
      <SCHEMEOUTPUT>
	75
      </SCHEMEOUTPUT>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
withdraw(25); // output: 75
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>
    
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    If the two processes operate independently, then Peter might test the
    balance and attempt to withdraw a legitimate amount.  However, Paul
    might withdraw some funds in between the time that Peter checks the
    balance and the time Peter completes the withdrawal, thus invalidating
    Peter<APOS/>s test.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    Things can be worse still.  Consider the expression
    <SNIPPET EVAL="no">
      <SCHEME>
        (set! balance (- balance amount))
      </SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
balance = balance - amount;
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SNIPPET>
    executed as part of each withdrawal process.  This consists of three
    steps: (1) accessing the value of the <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE>
    variable; (2) computing the new balance; (3) setting
    <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> to this new value.  If Peter and
    Paul<APOS/>s withdrawals execute this statement concurrently, then the
    two withdrawals might interleave the order in which they access
    <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> and set it to the new value.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    The timing diagram in Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:bank-access"/> depicts
    an order of events where <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> starts at 100,
    Peter withdraws 10, Paul withdraws 25, and yet the final value of
    <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> is 75.  As shown in the diagram,
    the reason for this anomaly is that Paul<APOS/>s assignment of 75 to
    <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> is made under the assumption that
    the value of <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> to be decremented is 100.
    That assumption, however, became invalid when Peter changed
    <SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE> to 90.  This is a catastrophic
    failure for the banking system, because the total amount of money in the
    system is not conserved.  Before the transactions, the total amount of
    money was <DOLLAR/>100.  Afterwards, Peter has <DOLLAR/>10, Paul has
    <DOLLAR/>25, and the bank has <DOLLAR/>75.<FOOTNOTE>An even worse
    failure for this system could occur if the two
    <SPLITINLINE>
      <SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>set!</SCHEMEINLINE> operations</SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>assignment statements</JAVASCRIPT>
    </SPLITINLINE>
    attempt to change the balance simultaneously, in which case the actual data
    appearing in memory might end up being a random combination of the information
    being written by the two processes.  Most computers have interlocks on
    the primitive memory-write operations, which protect against such
    simultaneous access.  Even this seemingly simple kind of protection,
    however, raises implementation challenges in the design of
    multiprocessing computers, where elaborate 
    <INDEX>cache-coherence protocols</INDEX>
    <EM>cache-coherence</EM>
    protocols are required to ensure that the various processors will
    maintain a consistent view of memory contents, despite the fact that
    data may be replicated (<QUOTE>cached</QUOTE>) among the different
    processors to increase the speed of memory access.</FOOTNOTE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    <INDEX>state<SUBINDEX>shared</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
    <INDEX>shared state</INDEX>
    The general phenomenon illustrated
    here is that several processes may share  a
    common state variable.  What makes this complicated is that more than
    one process may be trying to manipulate the shared state at the same
    time.  For the bank account example, during each transaction, each
    customer should be able to act as if the other customers did not
    exist.  When a customer changes the balance in a way that depends on
    the balance, he must be able to assume that, just before the moment of
    change, the balance is still what he thought it was.
  </TEXT>

  <SPLIT>
    <JAVASCRIPT>
      <SUBHEADING>
        <NAME>JavaScript and concurrency</NAME>
      </SUBHEADING>

      <TEXT>
	In its initial design, JavaScript did not allow for two
        processes to apply functions such as
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>withdraw</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
        concurrently. In fact, the concurrency model of the language enforced
	strict sequential execution of activities resulting from <EM>events</EM>,
	with the use of an <EM>event queue</EM>. In the early 2000s, multicore
	computers became common and around 2010, the JavaScript designers
	responded with the introduction of concurrent processes via
	the concept of <EM>web workers</EM>. As of 2019,
	most internet browsers support this feature. As originally conceived,
	web workers were not able to share data such as the variable
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>balance</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> above. However,
	a shared data structure called
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>SharedArrayBuffer</JAVASCRIPTINLINE> is included
	in the latest
	<LINK address="http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/files/ECMA-ST/Ecma-262.pdf">ECMAScript specification</LINK>.
	Using <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>SharedArrayBuffer</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>, it is
	possible to program a <JAVASCRIPTINLINE>withdraw</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	function as described above.<FOOTNOTE>As of 2019, browsers differ
	in their support for
	<JAVASCRIPTINLINE>SharedArrayBuffer</JAVASCRIPTINLINE>
	objects.</FOOTNOTE>
      </TEXT>
    </JAVASCRIPT>
  </SPLIT>
  
  <SUBHEADING>
    <NAME>Correct behavior of concurrent programs</NAME>
  </SUBHEADING>

  <INDEX>concurrency<SUBINDEX>correctness of concurrent programs|(</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <TEXT>
    The above example typifies the subtle bugs that can creep into
    concurrent programs.  The root of this complexity lies in the
    assignments to variables that are shared among the different
    processes.  We already know that we must be careful in writing
    programs that use
    <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>set!</SCHEMEINLINE>,</SCHEME>
    <JAVASCRIPT>assignment,</JAVASCRIPT></SPLITINLINE>
    because the results of a computation depend on the order in which the assignments
    occur.<FOOTNOTE>The factorial program in
    section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:costs-of-assignment"/> illustrates this for
    a single sequential process.</FOOTNOTE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    With concurrent processes we must be especially careful about
    assignments, because we may not be able to control the order of the
    assignments made by the different processes.  If several such changes
    might be made concurrently (as with two depositors accessing a joint
    account) we need some way to ensure that our system behaves correctly.
    For example, in the case of withdrawals from a joint bank account, we
    must ensure that money is conserved.
    To make concurrent programs behave correctly, we may have to
    place some restrictions on concurrent execution.

    <FIGURE>
      <IMAGE src="img_original/ch3-Z-G-31.svg"/>
      <LABEL NAME="fig:bank-access"/>
      <CAPTION>Timing diagram showing how interleaving the order of events
      in two banking withdrawals can lead to an incorrect final balance.
      <!-- TODO: update file with JavaScript content -->
      </CAPTION>
      <INDEX>timing diagram</INDEX>
    </FIGURE>
  </TEXT>

  <!-- 
       %above figure shows the following:
       %time     Peter (withdrawing 10)       Paul (withdrawing 25)
       %- - - -  - - - - -                    - - - -
       % |
       % |       access balance, get 100
       % |                                    access balance, get 100
       % |        compute new balance as  
       % |        100 - 10 = 90                compute new balance as
       % |                                     100 - 25 = 75
       % |       set! balance to 90
       % |                                    set! balance to 75
       % V                         
  -->

  <TEXT>
    One possible restriction on concurrency would
    stipulate that no two operations that
    change any shared state variables can occur at the same time.  This is an
    extremely stringent requirement.  For distributed banking, it would
    require the system designer to ensure that only one transaction could
    proceed at a time. This would be both inefficient and overly
    conservative.  Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:two-shared-accounts"/> shows
    Peter and Paul sharing a bank account, where Paul has a private account
    as well. The diagram illustrates two withdrawals from the shared account
    (one by Peter and one by Paul) and a deposit to Paul<APOS/>s private
    account.<FOOTNOTE>The columns show the contents of Peter<APOS/>s wallet,
    the joint account (in Bank1), Paul<APOS/>s wallet, and Paul<APOS/>s
    private account (in Bank2), before and after each withdrawal (W) and
    deposit (D). Peter withdraws <DOLLAR/>10 from Bank1; Paul deposits
    <DOLLAR/>5 in Bank2, then withdraws <DOLLAR/>25 from Bank1.</FOOTNOTE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    The two withdrawals from the shared account must not be
    concurrent (since both access and update the same account), and Paul<APOS/>s
    deposit and withdrawal must not be concurrent (since both access and
    update the amount in Paul<APOS/>s wallet).
    But there should be no problem
    permitting Paul<APOS/>s deposit to his private account to proceed
    concurrently with Peter<APOS/>s withdrawal from the shared account.

    <FIGURE>
      <IMAGE src="img_original/Fig3.30.svg"/>
      <LABEL NAME="fig:two-shared-accounts"/>
      <CAPTION>Concurrent deposits and withdrawals from a
      joint account in Bank1 and a private account in Bank2.
      </CAPTION>
    </FIGURE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    A less stringent restriction on concurrency would ensure that a
    concurrent system produces the same result
    as if the processes had run sequentially in some order.
    There are two important aspects to this requirement.
    First, it does not require the processes to actually run sequentially,
    but only to produce results that are the same <EM>as if</EM> they had run
    sequentially.  For the example in
    Figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:two-shared-accounts"/>, the designer of the bank
    account system can safely allow Paul<APOS/>s deposit and Peter<APOS/>s
    withdrawal to happen concurrently, because the net result will be the same as
    if the two operations had happened sequentially.  Second, there may be more
    than one possible <QUOTE>correct</QUOTE> result produced by a concurrent
    program, because we require only that the result be the same as for
    <EM>some</EM> sequential order.
    
    For example, suppose that Peter and Paul<APOS/>s joint account starts out
    with <DOLLAR/>100, and Peter deposits <DOLLAR/>40 while Paul concurrently
    withdraws half the money in the account. Then sequential execution could
    result in the account balance being either <DOLLAR/>70 or <DOLLAR/>90
    (see exercise<SPACE/><REF NAME="ex:joint-account"/>).<FOOTNOTE>A more formal
    way to express this idea is to say that concurrent programs are inherently 
    <INDEX>nondeterminism, in behavior of concurrent programs</INDEX>
    <EM>nondeterministic</EM>. That
    is, they are described not by single-valued functions, but by
    functions whose results are sets of possible values.
    <SPLIT>
      <SCHEME>
        In Section<SPACE/><REF NAME="sec:nondeterministic-evaluation"/> we will
        study a language for expressing nondeterministic computations.
      </SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
        <!-- FIXME: remove split and replace with Scheme text when Chapter 4.3.3 is adapted to JavaScript  -->
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SPLIT>
<LABEL NAME="foot:nondeterministic"/></FOOTNOTE>
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    There are still weaker requirements for correct execution of
    concurrent programs.  A program for simulating 
    <INDEX>diffusion, simulation of</INDEX>
    diffusion (say, the flow of heat in an object) might consist of a large
    number of processes, each one representing a small volume of space,
    that update their values concurrently.  Each process repeatedly changes
    its value to the average of its own value and its neighbors<APOS/> values.
    This algorithm converges to the right answer independent of the order in
    which the operations are done; there is no need for any restrictions on
    concurrent use of the shared values.
  </TEXT>

  <EXERCISE>
    <LABEL NAME="ex:joint-account"/>
    Suppose that Peter, Paul, and Mary share a joint bank account that
    initially contains <DOLLAR/>100.  Concurrently, Peter deposits <DOLLAR/>10, Paul
    withdraws <DOLLAR/>20, and Mary withdraws half the money in the account, by
    executing the following commands:
    <SPLIT>
      <SCHEME>
        <!-- The below works but renders terribly -->
        <!-- <LATEX> -->
        <!--   \[ -->
        <!--   \begin{array}{ll} -->
        <!--   \textrm{Peter:} &amp; \texttt{(set! balance (+ balance 10))}            \\ -->
        <!--   \textrm{Paul:}  &amp; \texttt{(set! balance (- balance 20))}            \\ -->
        <!--   \textrm{Mary:}  &amp; \texttt{(set! balance (- balance (/ balance 2)))} -->
        <!--   \end{array} -->
        <!--   \] -->
        <!-- </LATEX> -->
        <table>
          <tr><td><kbd>Peter:</kbd></td><td><kbd>(set! balance (+ balance 10))</kbd></td></tr>
          <tr><td><kbd>Paul:</kbd></td> <td><kbd>(set! balance (- balance 20))</kbd></td></tr>
          <tr><td><kbd>Mary:</kbd></td> <td><kbd>(set! balance (- balance (/ balance 2)))</kbd></td></tr>
        </table>
      </SCHEME>
      <JAVASCRIPT>
        <table>
          <tr><td><kbd>Peter:</kbd></td><td><kbd>balance = balance + 10</kbd></td></tr>
          <tr><td><kbd>Paul:</kbd></td> <td><kbd>balance = balance - 20</kbd></td></tr>
          <tr><td><kbd>Mary:</kbd></td> <td><kbd>balance = balance - (balance/2)</kbd></td></tr>
        </table>
        <!-- The below works but renders terribly -->
        <!-- <LATEX> -->
        <!--   \[ -->
        <!--   \begin{array}{ll} -->
        <!--   \textrm{Peter:} &amp; \texttt{balance = balance + 10}          \\ -->
        <!--   \textrm{Paul:}  &amp; \texttt{balance = balance - 20}          \\ -->
        <!--   \textrm{Mary:}  &amp; \texttt{balance = balance - (balance/2)} -->
        <!--   \end{array} -->
        <!--   \] -->
        <!-- </LATEX> -->
      </JAVASCRIPT>
    </SPLIT>
    <OL>
      <LI>
        List all the different possible values for
        <SPLITINLINE><SCHEME><SCHEMEINLINE>balance</SCHEMEINLINE></SCHEME>
	<JAVASCRIPT><JAVASCRIPTINLINE>balance</JAVASCRIPTINLINE></JAVASCRIPT>
	</SPLITINLINE>
	after these three transactions have been completed, assuming that the
	banking system forces the three processes to run sequentially in some
	order.
      </LI>
      <LI>
        What are some other values
        that could be produced if the system allows the processes to
	be interleaved? Draw timing diagrams like the one in
	figure<SPACE/><REF NAME="fig:bank-access"/> to explain
	how these values can occur.
      </LI>
    </OL>
  </EXERCISE>
  <INDEX>time
  <SUBINDEX>concurrent@in concurrent systems|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
  <INDEX>concurrency
  <SUBINDEX>correctness of concurrent programs|)</SUBINDEX></INDEX>

</SUBSECTION>
